Hello and welcome back to the next section where we'll dive deep into the advanced use reducer Hook.
This special hook gives us another powerful way of managing state, and since state is super important
in React, use reducer is a super important hook and it's also important to master it in order to later
understand Redux.
So that's why I dedicated an entire section to the use reducer hook.
Now, this section does run pretty long, but that's because we're going to use use reducer to build
this entire new project, reinforcing all the other skills that you have already learned so far.
So if you're looking to save some time, you only need to watch like the first 5 or 6 videos in this
section.
And with that being said, let's now jump right in.