Now, in this lecture, we are going to implement the logic for handling a new answer.
And to understand what that means, let's check out our demo project here and then let's give a new
answer.
So a new answer is basically when we click on one of these options here.
So let's do that.
And you see that basically three things happened.
So first, the correct and the wrong answers are displayed.
Second, the points that we got were updated.
And third, the next button was displayed down here.
So basically when we click on one of these options, we need to rerender the screen.
And so once again, that means that we need a new piece of state.
And so that state should basically store which of the options was selected.
So in other words, which was the answer?
So answer zero one, 2 or 3.
So basically the answer is just going to be the index number of this option here.
So let's come back to our app.js and add yet another piece of state to our initial state.
So let's just call it answer.
And in the beginning it will be null.
So there will be no answer initially.
And so that makes sense, right?
And now next, let's then create an action in our reducer to update that answer.
So let's do that.
Well, after this one here.
So let's keep them in order.
And here, let's call this one new answer.
So then later we will dispatch a new action with the new answer type.
Right.
And so here, let's return, as always, the state, and then the answer.
We'll get set to the action dot payload.
So very simple stuff.
And so now we need to go here into our question or actually into these options because here is where
the click on the button will happen.
So here is where we will now need to dispatch a new action.
So that means that we need to pass the dispatch function into questions.
Well into question, actually.
So this patch.
And then the dispatch function.
And we will also need the answer that we gave.
So this one we need so that we can then display the answer that was given was correct or not.
So painting it basically with one of these colors.
And again, we need to destructure.
This first year.
So we need our answer.
Yeah.
So dispatch and answer.
So let's grab them here.
And then passing them in here.
So a bit of prop drilling you can maybe identify here, but that's not a big deal if it's like just
this one level.
So then accepting these two props here.
And there we go.
Now we can from here, dispatch the action.
So on click.
So this patch and the type of this event.
Well, let's see.
I don't remember.
So that's new answer.
And the payload should then be the answer that was given.
So new.
Answer.
And the.
Payload again is the answer.
Now, what is the answer?
Well, remember how we said earlier that the answer is basically the index of the option?
So in this case, that would be here index number one.
Right.
And the reason for that is that the correct option is also marked using these same indexes.
So I just want to show you that because I think that besides learning the React part, it's also important
that you learn how to build applications, basically.
Now here are app changed to a different state.
So the finished state.
But never mind.
So what I was saying is that the correct option here is also using these indexes.
And so indeed here the correct option is react.
And so that's index number one.
All right.
So then how do we get the current index here?
Well, we can just get it here as the second argument of the map method.
So that's just how this method works, where the first option is the current element of the array,
and the second argument is the current index.
And so this is all we need.
So let's check that.
Let's click maybe here this time.
And so then when we come to our state, we should have the answer of two.
And.
Well, where is that?
Well, that's not really anywhere.
So let's.
Reload.
Maybe I forgot to reload the application.
Let's try that again.
Uh, and apparently I did.
So now we got the answer right here.
Nice.
And so next up, let's then do some formatting based on this answer.
And so that's why this options here received that answer prop.
So that state right here.
So what we're going to do is to basically change the class names here conditionally.
So let's create a template literal.
And then first of all, let's create a class for the selected option.
So here, let's say if the current index is equal.
To the answer.
Then add the answer class and otherwise don't add anything.
So when we're doing conditional CSS, we should always use the ternary operator so that in the opposite
case.
So in this third branch here, then we return no string at all.
And so you saw that here.
The question that we selected actually got this special class where it moved a bit to the right.
And if we select this one, well, then that one would get that special class.
So that's the first thing.
And now we also then basically need to paint them in the right color, depending if the option is the
correct option or not.
So let's again enter here the JavaScript mode and then let's say if the current index is equal.
To question Dot?
Correct.
Option, then add the class.
Correct and otherwise.
Wrong.
And beautiful.
So that's working.
And again, let's just check or state here so we see what's going on.
So again, each of these options or of these questions actually has the correct option as a property
here.
So that's number one here.
And so number one in this case here.
So in this option is equal to the index.
And so therefore it was then marked as correct and all the other ones as wrong.
Okay.
And now we can actually click multiple times here.
But of course that should not be allowed.
So once the user clicks on one of these options, then it should be logged in.
And so we then can no longer click.
And so let's just disable the button.
With the disabled prop.
And in here, basically, we want to know if there was an answer.
So any answer at all would then disable this button.
So since we know that the initial state of the answer is null, we can just check if the answer is not
null.
So if it's not null means that there was an answer and then we want to disable the buttons.
So let's try that again.
Ah, but we have some problem here.
So all our options are already painted.
So that's very bad because it gives away the correct option here.
And so actually what we did here was not really correct.
So basically classifying each of them as correct and wrong.
We only want that to happen if there was an answer at all.
So basically in this situation.
So we need to reuse that.
So let's just.
Place that in a special variable and let's say has.
Answer it.
Okay.
And then let's use that here.
And here as well.
Now, here, this will become a bit confusing.
So we use a ternary and then another one.
So we have nested ternaries, which is pretty ugly.
So we could actually do this outside as well.
But let's just keep it like this so it is readable if you understand the logic behind this.
And so it looks as though now it is correct.
So let's select something here.
And yeah, now we cannot click on the other ones and also everything is marked in the correct way.
So we selected this one.
So this one got the special class, but it is wrong.
So it's then yellow and only this one is blue because it is correct.
So it has the correct class then?
Great.
So we took care of one of the three things that should happen.
So again, the correct answers should be displayed.
Then the user score should be updated and the next button down here should be displayed.
So let's now quickly take care of the second part.
So basically that the user score should be updated.
So that is something that needs to again, update on the screen, which means that we need yet another
state variable.
So let's call this points and the user starts at zero.
Okay.
And now where do we update these points?
Well, it makes sense that it is exactly in the same place where we received the new answer.
So right here, we will also update the points.
So how are we going to do that?
Because, of course, the points should only be awarded if the answer was correct.
So we need to first figure out which is the current question.
Then if the answer is correct and only then we want to add the points to the current points.
So that sounds confusing.
So let's just do it.
So first of all, let's figure out which is the current question.
Because we actually don't have that stored in the state.
So we only know the index, but not the question itself.
So let's grab state.
Thought questions.
ET state.
Dot index.
And so here really we are leveraging the current state that we get into the reducer to compute the next
state.
So really relying on that current state.
So with this we know which is the current question.
And so now we can then check if the current question is equal to the received answer.
So that received answer is again action dot.
Payload.
And now let's check if it is equal to question dot.
Correct.
Upton again.
So this property that we have used before already here.
Right.
So if that is the case, then we want to add some points to the current points.
And so that is state dot points plus something.
Let's just do one for now and otherwise the points will just stay the same.
So then we will just return again State.
Dot points.
Okay.
Now here we are, adding one for now, but that is not what we want to add in the end.
Because notice again, how.
Each of our questions object, actually.
Let's give a lot more space.
So each of them has this points property, which is because each of them actually has a different points
value.
So the easier ones only give ten points, but then if there are more difficult.
Well, let's.
Maybe this one.
Well, not really.
So there are some hard ones.
Yeah.
Like this one.
So this one adds 30 points.
And so we need to get actually that value.
So that is at the current question.
Dot points.
All right.
So I understand that this year might seem a bit confusing, but this is really just understanding what
kind of data we have and then working with that data.
And also, you notice that here we now have for the first time quite a more complex state updating logic
in our reducer.
And this is perfectly fine and actually encouraged.
So whenever it's possible, we should try to put as much of the logic for calculating the next state
right into the reducer.
So it's better for this logic here to be in the reducer then in the place where the event is actually
first handled.
So basically, we could probably also do this calculation right here in the option where we handle the
event.
But that would go against the logic of the Usereducer hook.
So it's much better to do it like this.
All right.
So this should be working.
Let's check it.
So we know that this question is worth ten points.
And so if we select the correct one, then you notice that our points have indeed been updated to ten.
So that's zero plus ten.
And if we select the wrong one, then our points stay at zero.
Great.
So of course we will later then display these points in the UI.
But let's leave that for a bit later because next up, we need to take care of displaying the next button
and handling the logic of actually moving to that next question.
So basically when we finish here, then we want to click and go to the next one.
And so that is what we will do in the next video.