So now we have the simple task of moving to the next question as soon as an answer has been given.
So as soon as the user clicks on one of these options, we want a button down here to appear that we
can click.
And so then we will move automatically to the next question.
Now, as we have discussed before, moving to the next question basically means increasing this index
here, right?
Because it is based on this index that the current question is being read and then displayed.
So that's what we do right here.
So we're passing in the questions object that corresponds to the current index.
And so let's now here.
Create yet another possible action in our reducer.
Now let's call this one just next.
Question.
So here we will just return.
The current state.
And all we want to change is the index property which will be set to state dot index plus one, and
that should be it.
At least for now.
And so now we need to create, actually that button.
So besides the question, we want to then display the button.
And so let's actually always display a button component, but that button component will then only render
the button element itself if there has been an answer.
So we could also do it the other way around and do the conditional rendering right here.
But instead we're going to do that conditional rendering inside the button.
So we will allow this next button to basically decide if it wants to render itself or not.
And so since we want to dispatch an action from there, we need to pass that in.
And so now, of course, we need to create this component.
But before we do that, here, we have a problem because we need a fragment now.
Okay.
And now, as I was saying, we need to create this new component.
Right here.
Okay.
And then let's already receive the dispatch function.
But we also need the answer.
And so that's because of what I was saying earlier, so that we want this component here to allow,
if it wants to render the button or not in case there has been an answer.
So let's pass in also.
The.
Current answer.
And of course we then need to import also this component here.
So just duplicate that and.
Yeah, I think that should be it.
So let's go back here and accept that answer prop.
And so now we can say.
So doing an early return, we can say if the answer is null, which remember means that there has been
no answer, then just return nothing here.
So just return null and otherwise, then we actually create.
A button.
So here we say next.
And the class name should be BTN and BTN UI.
And then finally the onClick handler will be.
A you function.
And then, of course, we dispatch a new action.
And so remember, this one is the one we just created, which is next question.
And for this state transition that this will trigger our reducer doesn't need any data and therefore
there is no payload here necessary.
Okay.
And let's see if this works.
So let's start and let's click.
And indeed, there is our button.
And so let's now test.
And yeah, it moved forward to the next question.
But we still have a problem, which is that our answer has not been reset and so therefore we are still
showing the previously given reply.
So that's easy to fix.
But what matters is that we can now actually move through these different questions.
So let's then just quickly fix that problem.
And so all we need to do is to again, come to our central place where all these state updating takes
place.
So what should we do here?
Well, we just need to set the answer.
Back to null.
And that will fix it.
And once again, we can really see here in action how all these different state variables closely belong
together.
And so the use reducer hook really was the perfect solution for managing our state in this application.
But anyway, let's now again test this.
And yeah, that fixes it.
So let's try another one here.
And this one is components just to see if our points are correctly updating.
Yeah, and they are.
So now we have 30 points, which is ten points for each question that we just successfully answered.
And speaking of these points, we now actually want to display them up here.
So the current points out of all the possible points together with the progress that we have been doing,
so basically displaying this part right here.
So don't wait and let's move together right to the next video to do that.