So let's continue building our application and display the progress that the user has been making in
the quiz.
So basically what we want to show is this right here.
So the current question out of the number of question and the current points out of the number of points
and then also this nice progress bar.
So basically what we want to do is to, besides the question at the next button, also display a progress
component.
And let's actually first go build that component.
So a new file.
Just calling it progress.
And then scaffold our new component like this.
And then let's get to work.
Now here, let's actually use a more semantic header element.
So a header inside the main part.
So that's perfectly semantic and so.
I think it's a good element to use here.
And let's give it the class name of progress.
Okay.
And let's start with one paragraph for each of these sites right there.
So here we need the current question.
So remember, that is the index.
And then let's place it inside the strong tag.
Just write it again.
That's easier then to copy and paste that.
And then here we also need the number of questions.
So these things we will need to receive.
As props.
And this, of course, is called index, not just I.
So index and num questions.
I believe it is called.
And so let's already try this out.
So progress.
And I'm selecting this one here from the list again, because here this shows me that this will then
automatically import the component into this page.
So into this file.
So we need again, the index and we need the number of questions.
Okay.
So let's see.
And yeah, we already have something.
Let's just start from scratch.
And so now we see that we have question zero here.
And so that's of course, because the index is zero based, but our users don't know that.
So it looks a lot nicer if we just start at one, right?
The next step.
We want the current points.
And again, let's make them bold.
So that's points.
And then out of all the possible points.
So that will basically be the sum of all the points of all the questions.
However, we don't have that value yet.
And so.
Well, let's go compute it.
Let's just write an X here.
Take the points so that we can correctly display our component.
So points.
All right.
Apparently we haven't destructured that yet, but it should be in our state because I remember how we
updated it earlier.
And yeah, now it is zero.
Okay.
And now let's get the maximum amount of points that the user can make.
And so that again is derived state because we can just compute that from the questions array.
So let's say Max.
Possible points.
So that's questions dot reduce because we want to reduce this into just one single value.
And so here the callback always gets the previous value and the current value in the array.
So that's the first argument.
And then the second argument is the initial value.
And so now all we need to do is to add the previous value.
So the one that starts at zero with the current question.
Not points.
So just a normal regular reducer right here.
So that should be nothing strange for you at this point.
And so let's then pass that in.
And copy that.
And then replace our X right here.
So let's see.
And beautiful.
The only thing that we are missing is.
Well here we now need to restart because this one times out after a few minutes.
So we also want this progress bar here that keeps going as soon as we complete more questions.
So you see that it keeps going and this element is actually a progress bar.
So this one is a new one, or at least one that I haven't really used before.
And so here we can define the max value that this can take.
And here it makes sense that this is the number of questions.
So it will go basically from 0 to 15 in this case.
And then we can also define the current value.
So this is basically like an input element.
And so here we are making it a controlled element in a way, even though we cannot really set the state
on the progress bar.
But anyway, here at the current value will be the current index.
And here it's actually the index, not the index plus one because we actually want this to start empty.
So when we come here, we want it to be empty at the beginning.
And so let's see.
Let's click here.
And now you see that it didn't really move.
It will only move once we click here.
So then it moved here to one.
So if we inspect this element, we will see that the max is 15.
Of course.
And the value is one.
So we can change that here just to see, for example, this is what it would look like with ten and
then with 15, it would be completely full.
But anyway, the behavior here is slightly different because here when we click, then it immediately
moves to the next one.
So right after we click so somehow basically this detects if there is an answer and if so, it then
immediately moves this value forward.
So let's implement that here so we can just pass in the answer.
And then I will show you a very nice trick that we can use.
So we can.
Convert to a number.
The boolean that will result from checking again if there is an answer or not.
So doing this.
So basically what this does is that if there is no answer, then this is false.
And so then number will convert that false to a zero.
But if there is an answer, then this will of course be true and then that true will be converted to
one.
And so then we add one to the index.
So let's see.
And.
Well, that's already at one here.
But that's because I didn't pass in the answer.
So right now the answer is then undefined and undefined is different from null.
And so that then gives already one.
So of course we also need to pass the answer as a prop.
But this will then fix it.
So as you see, it's just completely normal that these unexpected small mistakes happen.
But in any case, now that's fixed.
And so this is what we were looking for.
So it keeps going forward all the way until the end, which I will not do now as that takes just a bit
too much time.
But anyway, with this, we successfully finished the task that we had for this lecture.
So let's close this one.
We don't need anymore, nor this one or this one.
And so with this, let's now move forward.