Our next task is to implement the functionality of actually finishing the quiz.
So after the user has given an answer to the last question, we no longer want to display all of this
here inside the main component.
But instead we will want our application to move into a finished status so that then we can display
like a finished screen here.
So in the beginning we have a start screen.
So when the application is ready, then while it is active we show the progress question and next button.
And then when the user is actually finished, we will have the status set to finished.
And so let's.
Handle that state here, that status state even though we don't have.
Any button yet or so that will trigger the status to become finished.
But let's implement this anyway.
So we want or actually let's create the component first.
So finish screen.
Dot JS.
Now down here, let's return a paragraph that says.
Use chords.
And then the score.
And let's actually wrap this into.
A strong tag.
And then out of all the maximum amount of points.
So that's Max possible.
Points.
And then let's also calculate a percentage.
So let's do that outside here.
So as a derived state, basically.
So let's say that's the points divided by the max.
Possible points.
Times 100.
So let's take that and use it here.
So let's round that down then.
Per Senate.
Okay.
But of course, our code is complaining that none of this exists because of course we will have to receive
this as perhaps.
Okay, so now our component is happy, but.
Of course, it's not yet being displayed because we need to include it here.
So finish screen.
Just make sure that it got automatically imported.
I'm not sure it did.
Yeah, actually, it didn't.
So let's try that again.
Yeah.
Just like this.
So we pass in the points.
And the max possible points as well.
No.
Okay.
But as I mentioned earlier, nowhere in our code we can make the status change to finished.
But just to test this, let's do that here.
And so that's one of the great advantages of having these dev tools.
So right here we can change any value that we want.
For example, to finished.
And so then we see that we got the the component that we just created here.
We're just missing the class name.
Of result.
So that looks a lot better with the percentage sign as well.
And then later we will also include like an emoji here.
But let's leave that for a little bit later because for now we actually want to trigger the status to
become finished.
So when should that happen?
So let's just restart here.
And now let's go to one of the last questions.
And again, I will simply change the index now here, let's say to 13.
And so with this, we are almost on the last question.
So let's just reply anything here next again.
And so now we are on the last question, right?
So with the index of 14.
So when we select anything here now, what's going to happen?
Once we click here, the index will just go to 16 or to 15 actually, and then we will have no question
to display.
And so it is in this situation where we actually want this button here to not go to the next index,
but instead to change the status here to finished.
Okay.
And so that's what we will implement next.
So as I click here now again, then we get an error because there is no question with that index.
All right.
And so let's go here to our next button and say that actually we only want to return this kind of button
that dispatches the next question event if a certain condition is met.
And so that condition is that the index is less than the number of questions.
So for that we will then of course, have to pass that in here.
And here it's actually minus one because the index is zero based, but the number is not.
Okay, so let's pass in the index and the Num questions.
So there we received them.
And here is where we pass them in.
So num questions equals num questions and then the index.
So you see there is a lot of props being passed around in this application, but we will actually learn
a nice solution to this problem.
So it's not really a problem, but we can make it a bit nicer with some tools that we will learn about
later.
But anyway, let's just simulate this again.
And so if we now go to the index of 14.
Then as we finish, we should no longer see that button there.
And that's right.
So this time we cannot move forward.
And so with that, we prevented that bug that we saw earlier.
But now we then, of course, need another button.
So let's say then, if the index is equal to the number of questions minus one.
So that's our 14 in this case.
So in this case, we say finish.
And then here we will want to dispatch something else.
So let's say an event called Finish.
So let's then add or basically handle that right here in our reducer.
So finish and this one is going to be quite simple.
Again, at least for now, because here all we do for now is to set the status.
Two finished.
So let's reload here again.
So I really don't feel like going through the whole quiz manually.
And so let's just type 14.
Click on anything.
And yeah, here we got our finish button.
And so now as we click here, yeah, beautiful.
So our status change to finish and we got, of course the finish screen right here.
Okay, let's just make this screen a little bit nicer with some emoji here, which will express basically
how well the user did.
So let's create a let variable here.
So I think I'm doing that for the first time in this course, but that's just because we will now have
a lot of conditions here.
And so this is the easiest way of doing that.
So basically, according to different values of the percentage, we will now assign a different value.
To the emoji, so giving it a different emoji.
So here, let's go for a medal.
Like this.
Then we can say else if or actually since these will be mutually exclusive, we don't even have to do
that.
So just a normal if is good enough so greater equal 80 and here if you don't want to spend the time
doing this, you can just.
Uh, fast forward a little bit.
But less than 100.
Then our emoji.
Let's see.
Let's use the party emoji this time.
And let's just do a couple few more.
So if it's more than 50 and less than 80 and then if it's greater than zero, but less than 50.
And finally, let's do one if the user fails, all of the questions.
So let's use a face palm for this one.
And here let's just use like a thinking emoji.
Well, not there.
And then here.
Let's just use.
Well, not.
To use a happy.
Face.
For example, just this one here.
And so then let's just include that right here.
So that looks a little bit better.
Gives the user like an immediate feedback.
Great.
So this works really great.
Right now there's just one more feature that I actually want to implement, which is a high score.
So if the user does the quiz and then they score 100 points, but then the next time they do it again,
then they score 200, then we want to store that 200 as the high score.
And so if they then do it for a third time, but then they score, let's say 150, then the 200 stays
as the high score.
And so we want to also display that here as a paragraph.
So use the class name of high score.
And then let's just write here between parentheses.
That the high score is for now X points.
And then here, let's actually return a fragment because we don't want to pollute our markup here with
some unnecessary divs.
Okay, so when and where and how is the best way of calculating this high score?
Well, I think that the best place to do so is exactly when the user finishes the game.
And so that is right here in this finish event.
Right.
So when this happens, the game finishes.
And so here we can perfectly fine calculate the high score.
So this is another piece of state because of course, we need it to be remembered across Rerenders.
So here we also start at zero.
And.
Yeah.
Then let's update the high score as the game finishes.
So we can just do state dot points, which are the current points at the end of the game.
And then we can compare that to the current high score.
And so if it is greater than the current high score, then here we want to assign that new value to
the high score.
So then that's going to become state dot points.
But otherwise, here actually is the question mark.
But otherwise, then the high score will simply stay at state dot.
High score.
So let's manually reload so that our state gets that new high score.
And will now manually set it to, let's say, 20.
And then let's start our game.
Let's just do a few of them here.
Just so we get more points.
So now we already have 30 points.
And so let's then move on to the last one.
So we skipped all of them.
So hopefully our users don't do this.
But yeah, let's now just click anyone.
Oh, that wasn't even on purpose.
But anyway, we have 30 points.
The highest score is 20.
And so let's see what happens.
And you saw that the high score got indeed updated to 50 because, of course, those 50 were more than
the current high score.
Okay, so let's get that out.
Here so destructuring out of the state so that we can then pass it into the finished screen.
So high score will be equal to high score.
And then.
Yeah, let's write that here as well.
So high score and then accepting it here.
High score.
But now I'm not going to test that again because we can be pretty sure that it works.
Now, here we now have one final thing, which is this button to restart the quiz.
So right now, we are still missing that.
So again, I'm not going to show that.
But so basically, in the end, we will want to have one button to start the quiz over.
And so that is what we will implement in the next video where we are then almost done with the application.