So after a quick break, let's now finally build the simple feature that allows a user to restart a
quiz.
And with our reducer that we already have in place, this is almost too easy now.
So we have updated related pieces of state so many times in this section so far that I think that you
could actually implement this on your own.
So this entire feature, you might be able to just build it on your own now.
So I think that might be a really nice challenge.
So just add a button here with the same classes as I think this one here, or at least the same classes
as this one.
So basically it's just the same thing here.
And then you just create a new action and then basically reset the state there.
So that should not be too hard.
And so please do that now and meet me back here once you are finished.
So I hope that was fun.
So I will just now copy and paste this button here.
So place it right underneath this one right here.
And then, of course, we need access to the dispatch function.
From here, the text will be restart.
Quiz.
And then here, let's dispatch an action with the type of restart.
So very creative.
All right.
And going back to our reducer.
Case.
Restart.
And so here we could now do this in two different ways so we could define all the variables that we
want to reset to their initial state.
So just like this, for example, setting the score back to zero and basically doing all of this here
because actually we want to restore all of them except for the questions array.
So this one, we don't want to refetch, of course.
And while probably we also want to reset this one here to ready, but these other ones, they should
become exactly the values that we have right here.
So let's try to do this.
So we expand the entire initial state back here and then we just add the questions back in.
So we say questions is equal state dot questions so that we don't lose them.
And then finally the status should become ready.
But again, you could just as well have done this.
So return the entire state.
But in overwrite like the points back to zero.
The high score back to zero.
The index back to zero as well.
And there was just one more.
Which was it?
The answer back to null.
Answer back to null and of course the status.
To ready.
So both of these work.
I just prefer this one here because it's a bit more explicit that we basically want to reset to something
similar to the initial state.
So this was really easy, wasn't it?
And so I actually really, really like this pattern.
So it makes the state logic that we have here, all of it so decoupled from all the different components.
And that's especially helpful when we later come back to the code and want to understand what is happening.
So then all we will have to do is to basically read through these cases.
And by that we can then understand what happens in our application and how the state transitions.
So even without understanding much of the application, just by reading the reducer, we will know that
some data might be received, that it might fail, that something will start, that there can be a new
answer, that there can be a next question, and so on.
So again, just from reading the reducer and so because of this, our state updates are really a lot
more declarative.
So we just map these different actions here to the state transitions that we then write out right here.
So really, really amazing pattern, but I will talk more about that again by the end of the course
when we summarize everything that we learned here.
So now let's actually just test this.
So let's start.
And then I will cheat again.
And going back.
Or actually going forward automatically to index number 14.
Then let's click here.
Oh, actually, this is the demo version.
So that is then really cheating, right?
Because that's already working.
So.
Yeah.
Again.
14.
And so we have just 20 points.
So I guess we won't be the high scorer or actually we will because of course it's also reset to zero.
And so here we then have the same as before, but now we can restart the quiz.
So let's see.
And this patch is not a function.
Nice.
So we didn't pass it in I guess.
So, of course, we need that here.
So let's do it all again.
And if you want, you can, of course, go through the entire quiz, which I really hope you do.
That's why I added 15 questions to it so that you can practice a little bit.
But anyway, let's now click here and.
Nice.
So the questions remain the same.
But everything else is reset.
Great.
So that was actually it.
So we finished that part as well.
All we have to do now is to get this timer here to run.
So when this timer runs out, then basically the quiz stops.
So you see here that it keeps updating.
So let's set it like to five seconds so we see what happens here at the end.
So let's wait for it.
And so then you see that it automatically moves to the finish screen.
And so let's now implement this functionality in our own application.