Let's start this section by getting a first high level overview of how to use the Usereducer hook in
practice over this lecture and the next one.
And as always, it is time to create yet another project.
So let's move to our folder and then let's run Npx Create.
React app at version five.
And then the app that we're going to build in this section is going to be called.
React quiz.
All right.
And now let's wait until create React app finishes installing all the packages that we need.
Okay.
And now it's time for our usual clean up.
So first I'm going to rename this here.
So we're already in our 10th project.
And now let's get rid of all this stuff here.
As always.
Okay, then getting our starters from here.
And this time we have five starter files.
So I think that might be a record.
Then just replace the file and then let's just drag and drop our folder onto VS code.
And then as always, let's also delete all the stuff we don't need from here.
And the rest is okay.
So we need the up component and we need to include the CSS file, which as always is part of the starter
files right here.
So let's start by opening up the app file and the date count file.
Which we will need soon.
And then here, let's delete everything and start the app component from scratch.
So export default function.
App.
And then here, let's just create a div and in this div I will immediately call the date counter component.
So date counter and then I need to import that.
From date counter.
So let's take a look.
So opening up or integrated terminal and then NPM start.
And so this is what you should see if you successfully started your application.
So let's also close the app, because in these first two lectures, we will only be working with the
date counter.
So this date counter is identical to what we implemented in one of the previous challenges.
So basically here, as we click on one of these values, it will then increase the date.
We can also update that number here and you see that then it also increases the date and we can change
the value on this slider, which is basically the step.
So if we then click here, it increments by whatever the step value is here.
Okay.
And so what we're going to do now is to basically replace these two use state hooks with usereducer
hooks.
So it's very important that you understand exactly what this code here does and how it works.
And so in case you didn't do the challenge or don't really remember, then please take a few minutes
now to really check out this code.
So all the event handlers that we have here and how they update these two states and how the states
interact with one another so only proceed in this lecture once you are really sure how everything works
here.
Okay.
But anyway, let's now finally talk about the Usereducer Hook.
So the Usereducer Hook is basically a more advanced and more complex way of managing state instead of
the use state hook.
Now the Usereducer Hook works with a so called reducer function, which is a pure function that will
always take in the previous state and the so-called action as an argument and will then return the next
state.
But instead of talking about it, let's actually use it.
And I will start by replacing this first count state right here.
So let's write.
Again count and then dispatch.
And I will explain what these mean here in a minute.
And so then use reducer.
And so this hook takes in not only the initial state, but also the reducer function that I was just
talking about.
So let's already write that here and I will then create this function in a minute.
So that's the first argument.
And the second argument is, again, the initial state.
And so that's again, zero.
So let's then comment out this state and then let's create outside of the component that reducer function.
So that's just function reducer.
And so as I was saying, this reducer function takes as the arguments the current state and an action.
And so the first thing that we're going to do is to just log these two to the console.
Okay.
Now, here we got a couple of errors, so let's just comment out all of this code here.
So we actually no longer need any of this.
And then we also need to include the use reducer hook into our application.
Okay, let's maybe reload here and there we go.
Okay, so we have our reducer function, but when does this function actually get called?
Well, that's where this dispatch here actually comes into play.
So we see that the use reducer hook does return the current state.
So just like the use state hook, but then instead of also returning a state updating function, the
reuse reducer hook returns as a second thing.
This dispatch function.
And so this dispatch function can also be used to update the state.
It just works in a slightly different way.
So let's just call this function right here.
And then let's pass in the number one and actually let's do that in the increment event handler.
So the one that is going to be called when we click here on this button.
So let's actually click on this button and.
Here we get our output.
Let's make this a bit bigger.
And so the output that we get so the console dot log from here is zero and one meaning that the state
is zero and the action is one.
So why is that?
Well, it is because the reducer function gets access to the current state, as I was saying in the
beginning, which right now is zero.
So it's this initial state and then it also gets access to the action, which right now is simply this
one that we passed into the dispatch function.
So this is basically going to become the action in the reducer.
And so the idea of the reducer is to take these two things so the current state plus the action and
based on that, return the next state.
And so let's do that.
So all we want to do is to return the state.
Plus the action in this case.
And so whatever we return here will then become the new state.
And so this means that right now, our value here should become one.
Let's just reload.
And there we go.
So our state was indeed successfully updated.
Now, when we click here, of course nothing's going to happen, but let's fix that.
So let's then again call the dispatch function, which in the terms of use reducer we call dispatching
an action.
So here we will dispatch an action of minus one.
And so then that minus one will get added to the current state, which will then decrease the value.
And so that works just fine.
Great.
Now, at this point, this isn't really useful, is it?
I mean, we had to do a lot of additional work to get the same functionality as just this.
Right.
But trust me, it will get a lot more useful as we keep going here.
So next up, let's think about how we can set this date.
Because remember, when we type some number here, we actually want the state to update to that number.
So that's what we have here in the define count.
However, this is not going to work really in the same way that we have been doing.
So here if we just dispatch.
E dot target dot value, then that will simply be added to the current state.
Right.
So let's write something here and I will now write a zero so that we then have ten here.
But then as I wrote the Zero, it actually added that to the state because, well, here we are just
adding the action to the current state.
And so if I now write another zero, that will just get added to the state that is already here as well.
So that's not at all what we want.
And so therefore, now it's time to actually start thinking about actions here.
So basically, in this case, we have three actions.
We have decreasing the count, we have increasing it and we have setting it.
And so we should actually name these actions.
So what we're going to do is to not just pass in this value, but an object which contains the action
as well as this value.
So.
Let's write type and then let's call this deck for decreasing.
And then.
And payload and then set it to one.
No.
Okay.
So this object is what we now call an action when we work with reducer functions.
And in theory, this object here could have any shape that we wanted.
But it is kind of a standard to always just have the type property and the payload property.
So actually not payload, but really payload.
So this is the standard that you will always see when using the use reducer hook.
And the same is actually true later in Redux.
So in case you heard of that.
So let's do the same thing here as well.
So type.
This one will be ink and then the payload here.
We'll just be one.
Okay.
And so now here instead of just doing this, we now need to account for these different types.
So let's say if the action type is inc.
Well, then return the current state.
Plus action dot payload.
Then if it is decrease, then minus.
And if the action dot type is set count, which we will create later.
Well then actually simply return action dot payload.
But let's experiment now with this so that it makes more sense.
So let's reload.
And first of all, let's see if this works now.
And beautiful.
So really nice.
And now here, let's dispatch also.
Actually an action object with the type of set count.
And then here the payload will be whatever value is typed into this field.
And so now this actually works.
So whatever value I type here now is this e dot target dot value.
And this will become the payload in this action right here.
And so then we dispatch this action to our reducer.
And so then that action contains that value.
So this 700 right here and the type.
And so then based on that type, we decide that the next state should become exactly that value.
So that's 700 in this case.
And if all this sounds and looks really confusing, then please don't worry at this point.
So now we are only getting like a overview of how all this works in practice, but I will explain you
exactly what the use reducer hook is, how it really works.
And yeah, we will have some nice diagrams and hopefully by then all of this will make a lot of sense.
Now, just to finish here, let's think a little bit more about this.
So actually, is there a need to pass in the payload right here and right here?
Well, not really, because the reducer should actually know itself what happens when we want to decrease.
Right.
So decreasing and increasing is really just adding or subtracting one.
And so we should add that logic here directly in our reducer.
So our reducer should know by himself or by itself how to perform these types of actions.
And so then we can remove the payload from here and make it a little bit easier to dispatch this action.
So the payload property here is optional.
And of course, here in this case, we still need it.
So we basically still need to pass our reducer this value here because otherwise, of course, it would
have no way of setting the next state.
Okay.
And so this still works.
And with this, we finished the first part of transforming this current state here from a simple use
state to a use reducer.
And so let's quickly recap what happened here.
So this new hook takes in not only the initial state, which was zero, but also a reducer function,
which will always get access to the current state and the action that we pass into the dispatch function.
So where does this dispatch function come from?
Well, it is one of the things that use reducer returns.
So this returns always the current state, which here we decided to call count and then it also returns
the dispatch function which we can then use to dispatch actions like this one.
So the convention is to dispatch actions that contain a type and then optionally also a payload with
the goal to pass in some value into the reducer.
And so then our reducer function takes the current state and it takes all the information that is contained
in the action in order to compute the next state.
So usually based on the action type, the reducer then takes some kind of decision.
For example, if it's inc so increment, then it simply adds one.
If it's decrement, then it subtracts one from the current state.
And if it's set count then it will simply set the new state as the value that came in as the payload.
And so those values are returned.
And so this return value is what will become the next state.
And so then as always, the component is re rendered and the UI is updated as well.
Okay.
So hopefully this made a bit of sense, but if not, well, we will have lots of opportunities to practice
this throughout this section and the rest of the course.
Next up, we will also incorporate this step here into our reducer.
And so let's do that in the next video right away.