Welcome back.
So let's now also incorporate the step state into the reducer that we have been building.
So usually we use reducers when we have some more complex state to manage.
So not just one single value as we have been doing here.
So what this means is that usually the state is going to be an object and not just one single value.
So let's now comment out this here as well.
And then let's define an object called initial state.
And this again, is a pretty common name.
And so here, let's define our count as zero.
And then the step as one.
So exactly the same default values that we had before.
And then here we will now pass in that initial state instead of just the zero.
And then here now, our state will no longer be called count, but well, let's call it just state.
And we could also immediately destructure that state object there.
But let's do that here.
So let's say count.
And step.
Restructuring from state.
And so now again, we have.
These function here that we had before, which now no longer exist.
Okay.
And now also what we have here is not going to make a lot of sense anymore.
And so let's just go back for now to our console dot log here.
Also don't need this anymore.
And so let's just quickly reload and click on one of these buttons here, which will then dispatch an
action.
And here we have our first problem for some reason.
Uh, maybe we actually need to return something from there, but let's just try that again.
Yeah.
So that doesn't really work.
So let's just try to return some object from there.
So you maybe don't have to even do this.
So this is just to avoid that error.
And so, yeah, now that works.
So all I wanted to do here is to now show you the state and the action again.
So the state that we now get in the reducer is the same as this initial step that we passed into use
reducer.
And so then we need to return an object with the same shape, so which also contains the count and the
step.
And so let's now adapt our reducer function here for that.
Now, actually, it is very common to use a switch statement inside of a reducer function like this.
So instead of multiple ifs, we just do usually a switch.
At the value that we want to evaluate is of course the action dot type.
And then we just do one case.
For, well, all the possible cases that we can have.
So what do we want to return in the case that the action type is decrease?
Well before we were just returning the state plus one.
But now we can no longer do that.
So now we need to return an object with this shape, remember?
So how do we do that?
Well, first of all, let's set the count based on.
State.
Dot count plus one.
And then we also need to set the step.
But instead of writing it out explicitly, what we do is to spread out the entire current state object
here.
And then with this part here, we basically overwrite the count property there.
And so this is exactly the way that we have been updating objects in the past as well.
So basically creating a brand new object which contains all the information of the previous object and
then whatever we want to overwrite.
Now here I'm getting this warning because we need also a default.
And so here in case.
We basically get an action that is not recognized by our switch.
We just throw a new error which says.
Unknown.
Action.
Well, this is still not happy, but.
Well, let's just keep going here for now.
So don't really see what the problem there is.
So let's do the other case as well.
So to increment is minus one and the error is still not disappearing.
But the reason for that is that here we are already returning.
And so then this code here would be unreachable.
Okay.
And finally, we have this other set count case.
So here I'm basically just converting the code that we already had into a switch statement and also
to returning an object with the shape again of count and step.
All right.
So spreading out the state and then the count will be equal to action dot payload.
Okay.
So for now, this is going to work exactly the same way as before.
Except that I did switch here.
So here it is.
The plus.
And here the minus.
So let's.
Yeah, now that works.
And if I type here, then that also updates the state.
Great.
And now let's actually do the same thing here for the step.
So here we now also want to dispatch an action.
With the type.
Of.
Set step right and the payload is going to be exactly the same.
So again, we convert to a number.
E dot target.
But value.
Okay, so set step.
And so now here we need to then add a new case for that.
And so in this case, we want to return the entire state and set the step this time.
To action.
Dot payload.
So that's state.
Let's reload.
And.
Yeah, beautiful.
That works.
And so now the only thing that we have to do is to actually take this step here into account when we
increase and decrease here.
So that's easy enough.
So that's just state dot step.
And then here, of course, the same thing.
And so now this should become two.
Yes, eight and so on and so forth.
Now.
Okay.
Let's just get rid of this here.
And, well, up until this point, maybe all of this still doesn't seem so interesting.
So everything that we did so far could easily have been achieved with the use state hooks as well.
Right.
But now let's actually do something different.
I'll also get rid of these here.
Okay.
So as I was saying, let's do something different.
So which is this reset function?
So what we did before was to simply take the two state setters and then call both of them.
But now we can do one big state transition, which does all that at the same time.
And so that's going to be one of the huge advantages of the use reducer hook.
So especially, of course, if we had even more states than just these two.
So let me show what I mean in practice.
So here we can just dispatch an action with the type, for example, reset.
And here we don't need to pass any data into the reducer and therefore we don't need to specify the
payload because we can do that right inside the reducer function.
So let's then add that case here as well.
So reset.
And so then here all we need to do is to return a new object where the count is reset to zero and the
step is reset to one.
And so here we can essentially update these two pieces of state at the same time and we can do even
better.
Let's cut this from here.
So this can actually live outside.
And then here we can just return.
The initial state.
All right.
And so if I click on Reset, then bam, there we go.
So our entire state just got reset to its initial state.
So all in one go, just with one dispatch right here.
So all we're doing here actually in these event handlers is to just dispatch and so we could just move
all of these dispatches in here right into the JS X.
So that would actually make a lot of sense.
But I won't do that right now.
But yeah, we could just replace all these event handlers that we have here because all of them, all
they do is to dispatch actions, the logic itself.
So the real logic of what they do is now all centralized in this one reducer function.
And so that is the beauty and the big advantage of the reducer function.
So basically we have all the possible state updates that can happen in our application in this one central
place here.
And so this makes it really easy to understand the entire application without having to go into all
the different components and all the different functions.
I mean, of course, here we only have one component and it's all really simple, but maybe you can
start seeing how nice this can be in a bigger application.
And in fact we will see that in action once we start building the big application for this section.
But all these advantages will become more clear later on.
For now, in these two lectures, I just wanted to focus on the mechanics of the usereducer hooks,
so really how it works and especially how this reducer function here works.
But I know that this all looks very confusing right now because I perfectly remember how I felt when
I first learned about this quite complex hook.
But since we are in the advanced React part now it's time to learn about these more difficult things.
But anyway, in the next lecture we will have some nice diagrams that will really illustrate the flow
of the data and of the state here.
And so stay tuned for that.