So we just learned how to use the Usereducer hook to centralize all the state updating logic in one
central place, which is the reducer function.
So let's now dive deeper into the concept of reducers and how and why they can make our applications
a lot better in certain situations.
So up until this point, we have been using the state to manage all our state, right.
However, as components and state updates become more complex, using use state to manage all state
is, in certain situations not enough.
For example, some components have a lot of state variables and also a lot of state updates that are
spread across multiple event handlers all over the component or maybe even multiple components.
And so this can quickly become overwhelming and hard to manage.
It's also very common that multiple state updates need to happen at the same time.
So as a reaction to the same event, for example, when we want to start a game, we might have to set
the score to zero set and is playing status and start a timer.
And finally, many times updating one piece of state depends on one or more other pieces of state,
which can also become challenging when there is a lot of state.
And so in all these cases, use reducer can really help.
So these are the problems that reducers try to solve.
And so let's now see how.
So first of all, Usereducer is an alternative way of setting and managing state, which is ideal for
complex state and for related pieces of state.
Now.
We already used Usereducer in the last two lectures, and this is what that looked like.
So we call Usereducer with a reducer function and its initial state and it returns a state and a dispatch
function.
So starting from the beginning, when we use Usereducer, we usually store related pieces of state in
a state object that is returned from the use reducer hook.
Now, it could also be a primitive value, but usually we use objects.
Now, as we already know, use reducer needs something called a reducer function in order to work.
So this function is where we place all the logic that will be responsible for updating the state and
moving all state.
Updating logic from event handlers into this one central place allows us to completely decouple state
logic from the component itself, which makes our components so much cleaner and so much more readable.
So when we manage state with use reducer, it's ultimately this reducer function that will be updating
the state object.
So in a way it's a bit like the set state function in new state but with super powers.
Now, in practice, the reducer is simply a function that takes in the current state and an action and
based on those values returns the next state.
So the updated state.
Now keep in mind that state is immutable in react.
This means that the reducer is not allowed to mutate the state and in fact no side effects are allowed
in the reducer at all.
So a reducer must be a pure function that always returns a new state and again, based on the current
state and the received action.
And speaking of the action, the action is simply an object that describes how state should be updated.
It usually contains an action type and a so-called payload, which is basically input data, and it's
based on this action type and payload that the reducer will then determine how exactly to create the
next state.
And now the final piece of the puzzle is this How do we actually trigger a state update?
Well, that's where the dispatch function comes into play.
So use reducer will return a so-called dispatch function, which is a function that we can use to trigger
state updates.
So instead of using set state to update state, we now use the dispatch function in order to send an
action from the event handler where we're calling dispatch to the reducer.
And as we already know, the reducer will then use this action to compute the next state.
Okay, so these are all the pieces that need to fit together in order to effectively use the use reducer
hook.
So an action object, a dispatch function, a reducer and a state object.
But now let's also look at the diagram to really see how all of these pieces actually fit together in
order to update state.
So let's say that we're in an event handler in some component and we now need to update some state.
So what do we do?
Well, that's right.
We call it the dispatch function that we got back from use reducer in order to dispatch an action to
the reducer.
And this action, as we learned before, is an object that contains information for the reducer.
So information about how the reducer should update the state.
In this case, the action type is update De and the payload is 23, which probably means that the reducer
will set the de state to 23.
Now the object doesn't need to have this exact shape with a type in the payload, but it's a standard
that has been adopted by most developers.
Now, basically the reducer takes in this action together with the current state, and it will then
return a brand new state object which we usually call the next state in the context of reducers and
as always with state updating, the state will then trigger a rerender of the component instance.
Now, if you're wondering why the reducer function is actually called a reducer, the answer is that
it's because it follows the exact same idea as the array reduce method.
So just like the reduce method accumulates all array values into one single value, the react reducer
accumulates all actions into one single state over time.
Okay, Now, behind the scenes, the dispatch function has access to the reducer because we passed it
into the use reducer hook.
Right.
So dispatch is really coordinating this whole thing and also giving the reducer access to the current
state.
And now to understand this even better, let's compare the mechanism of use reducer with the much simpler
use state mechanism.
So when we use use state, we get back a setter function and let's just call it set state.
And then when we want to update state, we just pass the new updated state value that we want and react
will simply update the state, which in turn will trigger the rerender.
So it's a lot simpler and more straightforward than use reducer.
But since use reducer solves the problems that we saw earlier in this lecture, it's a great choice
in many situations, even though it's a bit more complicated to set up.
But we will talk more about the big advantages of use reducer and also when to use it later in the section.
Now, I understand that this whole idea of dispatching actions and writing reducers is super confusing
in the beginning.
I know because I do remember how confused I was back in the day.
And so let me show you now a really helpful analogy that made all this really clear to me when I first
learned about this.
So imagine that you needed to take $5,000 out of your bank account for some reason.
Now, since this is a large amount, you can just do it from an ATM.
So you need to go physically to a bank.
Now, once you're at the bank, how do you actually get those $5,000?
Do you walk straight into the bank's vault, grab the cash and then go home?
Well, I don't think so.
Right.
That's usually not how it works.
How it does work is that you go into the bank and there you'll find a person sitting at a desk ready
to assist you.
Now, when you arrive at the bank, you already know how much cash you want to withdraw and from what
account number.
And so you walk right to the person and tell them that you would like to withdraw $5,000 from account.
923577, for example.
What happens then is that usually the person will type something into his computer check if you actually
have the cash in your account.
And if so, he goes to the bank's vault and gets the money to finally hand it over to you.
It's your money after all.
Right?
But note the big difference between this real version and the previous version of the story where you
just grabbed the cash yourself.
In this real version, you told the person what to do and how to do it.
And he then got the money for you on your behalf.
And so you didn't take the money directly yourself.
And that's a huge difference.
So does this maybe start to sound familiar?
Well, I hope it does.
And so let's now bring this analogy back to use reducer and identify what each of these pieces represents
in the use reducer mechanism.
And let's start with the most important thing, the state.
So what do you think the state is in this analogy?
Well, the state is represented by the bank's vault because this is where the relevant data.
So the money is stored and also updated.
So the vault is what needs to be updated.
And so that's our state.
Nice.
So with that out of the way, let's think about how the money is taken from the vault.
So about how state is actually updated.
So starting from the beginning, what do you think the customer going to the bank represents in this
analogy?
Well, the customer going to the bank and requesting the money is clearly the dispatcher because it
is who is requesting the state update.
Right.
And they are doing so by going to the person and requesting to withdraw the $5,000.
So what is the reducer here and what is the action?
Well, the reducer is going to be the person working at the bank because that's the one who actually
makes the update.
In this case, it's the one who goes to the vault to get your money.
But how does the person know how much money to take and from what account they know?
Because you told them so Exactly.
In your request message.
And so that request message is clearly the action.
In this example, the action can be modeled like this with the action type being withdraw and the payload
being the data about the withdrawal that you want to make.
So summarizing, you went into the bank with a clear action in mind.
You then dispatched that action to the reducer.
So to the person working there who took the action and followed the instructions to take the right amount
of money from your account.
So from state, he then gave you your money.
Finishing this cycle so you did not go directly into the vault and took your money.
Instead, you had the person as a middleman who knows a lot better than you how to perform different
actions on the vault.
So he knows how to deposit, how to withdraw, how to open and close an account, how to request a loan
and more.
And he does all this without you having to worry about the details.
So exactly like a reducer function which also decouples and abstracts all the state updating logic away
from you so that you can have clean and easy to understand components.
Okay.
So I hope that this now made the relationship between dispatcher reducer action and state crystal clear,
and you will get plenty of opportunities throughout this section to practice all this.