Let's start building a brand new app that will hopefully show you how extremely helpful the use reducer
hook can be.
And so this is the application that we are going to build and it's called the React Quiz.
So as the name says, this is basically a very simple quiz about some react concepts.
So this starts by actually loading the questions from a fake API.
And so at this point, we have received those 50 questions.
And so then we can start the quiz right here.
So here then we have the question with the four different options.
And up here we can see our progress and the number of points that we have won so far.
So here then we can of course, click on the correct option.
In this case, react is the most popular framework.
And so then immediately it is marked as correct.
And also the next button here appears so that we can move to the next one.
And now this time let's choose a wrong option.
And so, of course, the correct one is still marked here as correct.
Now, of course, I will not go through the entire quiz here, but we will see what the end result.
So when we reach the end of the quiz looks like.
Now just notice that here we also have a timer running.
And so when this timer finishes, then we automatically lose or we actually finish the quiz by then
automatically.
And we only get the points that we have gathered up until that point.
So all the state that we see here on the screen.
So which question was selected?
The number of points.
Which question we are right now.
The timer.
And really all the state is just managed by one big reducer because that's what this section is all
about.
Right?
Now, in this lecture, all I want to do is to just set up here the app skeleton.
So basically just setting up the structure with the header and the app itself.
And so then in the next lecture we can start fetching the questions and start building the application.
So we no longer need this component here.
And instead, let's come back to App and here we then remove that date counter.
Okay.
So our parent div here will have the class name of app.
And then inside that app we will have a header.
So basically this part here with the logo and the name of the application.
Now, as I said in one of the previous sections, we will now start to actually create one file per
component.
So making this project development a bit more real world.
Now, in case of the header, I actually already created that component for us.
So it's just this very simple component that doesn't even have any logic or any state and it doesn't
even accept props.
So it's just a very simple presentational component that has the image.
So the logo and the title.
And so let's include that here.
Just like this.
And of course we then need to import that component.
From that file.
So in the current folder and then header.
And there we go.
So there we have our header and then here below that we will have basically the main content.
And so for that main content, let's create a main component.
And before we do that, I will just write the markup here.
So let's say that we want a main element with the class actually of Main as well.
And then, for example, let's say we want a paragraph with the progress, let's say one of 15.
So this is just some dummy content here.
And then the question itself.
Right.
So let's say that we just have this.
But we want it to be not inside the main element here, but instead we want it to be inside its own
component so that then here our up component stays nice and clean.
So just having like different components, but not these elements with their class names.
So let's then create a new file with a new component.
So this one will be called Main.js because Main will be the name of the component.
And now let's actually, for the first time, use that snippet that I gave you at the very beginning
of the course.
So remember that.
Let's come here to the user snippets and then it should be one of these.
Yeah.
So the snippet that I mean is the RFC snippet.
And if for some reason you didn't add this to your own snippets at the beginning of the course, then
you can just maybe copy the code from here.
Or you can go back to that setup lecture at the beginning of the course, because again, we will now
use that snippet and it will be extremely handy.
So all we have to write is our fork hit enter and bam!
It creates a brand new component for us even with the name of the file.
So it got the name here from the file and then it accordingly named the component.
And so now all we have to do is to change right here or markup.
Now here we want to change from a div to a main element.
And so remember how many times it was quite annoying that we had to change this opening tag and the
closing tag.
And so to fix that, let's install this extension right here.
So auto rename tag.
So I already have it installed, but just go ahead and do that.
And so then when I change this div to main, then you see that both of them change at the same time.
So here the class name again of Main.
And now here.
What will we place as the content?
Well, basically here we want this content to stay in this component, so we want to just pass it in
to the main.
And so for that we use the children prop.
Remember.
So basically doing component composition here.
And we have done this multiple times already at this point.
So this should be nothing new.
And so with this, all we have to do is to replace this right here with Main.
And again, it then automatically replaced the tier.
And then all we have to do is import main.
From.
Main.
No, right now it looks the same here.
But now we have a bit of a better structure.
And also I think the component tree is a lot more complete like this.
Well, actually, this hasn't updated yet.
Yeah.
So then also in the tree, we can see that we have the app, a header and a main part.