Okay, so let's now set up a fake API on a fake web server and then use that to load the question's
data into our application.
So this time we're not going to use a real API because I created these questions myself.
And so then there's no API with that.
But I still want to basically pretend that we are loading these questions from somewhere and so therefore
we can create a fake API using an NPM package called Json server.
So let's come here to our terminal.
Create a new tab basically here.
So with this, we keep this process here running.
So the one that is running or up and then here we have another terminal.
Just make sure that we are in the correct folder and then let's do NPM install Json.
Server.
And in the meantime, I'm going to get some data here from the starter data that I forgot to include
at the beginning of this section.
So when you copied the files, you probably already got this questions Json.
But again, I did forget actually to place this file here earlier.
So let's come here into a React quiz and paste this file here.
Or actually what I want to do is to create a new folder out here.
So let's call this folder data and please make the same thing here in your file structure.
So creating a new file there.
And then let's move this questions dot Json file in there.
Okay.
So make sure you have that file in that folder.
And in the meantime, this finished running the installation.
And now what we need to do next in order to be able to call that package.
So to run the Json server command, we need to add a new NPM script here to this file.
So this NPM scripts that we have right here are basically the commands that we write here.
So each time that we write NPM start, we are able to do that because here this start command exists.
No.
Right.
And so let's now create our own script here with the name of server.
And so what should happen here then is that we want to call.
So we want to basically run the Json server package.
And we want to watch a certain file.
And so that file is going to be our questions data.
And actually, let's take a look at that data here.
So basically it is just one object with the questions property and then that property has one array.
And so then the array is our usual array of objects.
So each object then has a question.
The options, the correct one and the number of points.
And so this is the file that we now want to watch.
So basically to create an API from.
And so we just do data which is the folder and then questions dot Json.
And finally, we also need to specify the port.
Let's say 8000.
And that should be enough to get us going.
So let's do NPM run server.
So here we need to run keyword.
It's not just npm server but NPM run server.
Okay.
And so now we should have our API running.
But somehow I see that here at Sports 3000.
So here it's probably all lowercase, so give that a save.
Close that here.
So it was running basically before at the same URL.
So in the same port as our React application.
So let's reload that.
Let's retry this.
And now it is running on Port 8000.
And so we can just copy this URL.
Change this to 8000 and well, then we should see our data here.
But apparently there was some problem.
So let's see.
Well, now it thinks that it is already in use.
So let's maybe quit our other process here as well and then run.
NPM start again.
And then here, let's run NPM run server.
Okay, that's still not working.
So we can just change to any other port.
So this doesn't really matter.
So if for you it worked like this, then just go with that one.
And change the 8000 to 9000.
And actually, we also need to then add questions, which is basically the endpoint we are creating
here.
And it is called questions because that is the name here of this field.
So if it was called like this, then here we would have to add these two s as well.
So now this no longer works and or data would be here in this URL.
But of course, that doesn't make a lot of sense.
So let's just use this.
And also, you notice that this is actually just the array.
So here we see the array is exactly this one.
So let's now grab this URL and then fetch it.
Into our application.
So we want to load that data on mount.
And so for that, let's use our friend the use effect hook.
And as I mentioned, let's just run it on mount.
So here we want to fetch now from this URL and here, let's actually not even bother with an async function,
but let's just use the then method to handle this promise.
So this will give us a response that we need to convert to Json.
Which will then in turn return another promise.
So we chain another den handler there.
And so this should then give us our data.
For now.
Let's just lock that to the console then.
And also, let's catch a possible error here.
But also logging it to the console.
Let's do console error here.
And just like this.
Okay, so let's actually try that.
So let's reload.
Come to our console.
And beautiful.
Here is our data.
But now, of course, we will at one point need to display that data here in the UI.
And so for that, we are going to need state.
And as you can imagine, we will now use the Usereducer hook to create that state.
So let's do that.
So here we will get the state object and the dispatch function.
Remember?
And then.
We use our use reducer hook, which was then added here to the imports.
And here we pass the initial state, which we don't have yet, but we will create this object in a second.
And actually first we pass in the reducer function, which we also don't have yet.
And so let's create both of them outside here of this component.
So initial state.
And.
D reducer.
Which will take in remember the current state.
And the action that was dispatched.
Okay.
And now let's start by creating our initial state and here.
Let's create questions which by default will just be an empty array.
Now, besides this, what we also want is the loading state.
So to tell the user that questions are being fetched.
However, this time around we will do it in a different way.
So we will not create the loading state as always, but instead we will this time have a status state.
And so this status will basically be a string of the current status of the application that will change
throughout the time.
So in the beginning, our application will be in the loading state, but throughout time we will be
able to be in different states.
So let me write them right here immediately so we can be in loading state.
We can be in an error state.
We can be in a ready state.
Once the data has arrived and we are ready to start the quiz, we can be in an active state once the
quiz is actually running and we can be in a finished state once the quiz is finished.
Okay.
And so this is a bit of a nicer way of handling all these different statuses that the application can
be in.
So instead of having a is loading or is error or is ready or is active states, we just have the status
and then inside the status, we then tell the application what is currently going on.
So this has nothing to do with Usereducer, it's just another technique.
But anyway, let's now come here to our reducer function and then let's again set up that switch statement
that we already saw earlier.
So this is now basically a recipe that you will always follow.
So which is always the same.
So at least the setup here.
So we switch.
The action.type.
So we basically want to test for different types.
And let's start with the case of data.
Received.
So this will be the action that we're going to dispatch right here as soon as we actually have the data.
So right here.
And actually, let's do that first.
So here we will now no longer lock the data to the console, but instead we will dispatch an action
to the reducer.
And let's create our common usual event here.
So that's simply with the type.
And so that's the data.
Received type, which we can also think of, of an event.
So basically it's like here we are now creating this data received event which our reducer will then
basically respond to.
So that's the first part.
And now here we also need a payload because we want to actually send some data.
So send some information to the reducer so that the reducer can then use this to compute the next state.
And so here that payload will be the data that we just received.
Okay.
And so here then, remember, we need to return a new state object.
And so we will grab all the current state.
And then we will set questions to the data that we just received.
So that's action dot payload.
But what is really great about this is that we can now set this other piece of state that is related
to the question.
Or two questions, and that is the status.
So the status and the questions many times will change at the same time.
And so that's why having a reducer is so useful because now we can hear in the same place also set the
status to ready.
So basically we updated these two state variables.
So these two pieces of state all in one go in this one dispatch.
So just by dispatching this one event right here, we updated both the questions and the status.
And so we say that we transitioned to a new state by simply dispatching this simple event here.
Okay.
But anyway, let's also create then our default case.
And so here we will just like before, throw a new error saying that the action is unknown.
So give this a save and let's see what happens.
So we are no longer logging to the console, but we should now have those questions in our state already
so we can see it on the UI yet.
But let's take a look at our dev tools.
And yeah, we have our questions in the state and the status has also successfully been changed to ready.
So we transitioned to this new state where we changed these two properties of our state object.
So that's working great.
And now let's just create another event here, basically.
For the case.
There is an error.
So case.
Data.
The failed, for example.
That's just one possible name.
And so here, let's again return the entire state.
And then we simply set the status.
Here to error.
And so then later on, we will use, of course, the status to display different things here in our
UI in the JS.
So when there is an error, we will display that error and if we are ready.
So if the status is ready, then we will display the questions.
No.
Right.
But now let's actually dispatch that action.
So the type is this time data.
Failed.
And here actually, let's not pass in any payload because we're not really interested in the error that
we're going to receive.
So all we will do is tell or state that now the status is an error.
So just to test this, let's quit the process here where we load the data.
So with control C, we can finish this.
And so now we can no longer fetch data from that endpoint, of course.
And so we see that we get some error already.
And.
Also here we see that the status has been set to error.
So that's also working.
But of course, let's go back to having our work.
And so if we load now again, then we have our questions here in the state.
Okay.
So we did a lot of things.
So let's just quickly recap all that we did.
So we installed the Json server package to create basically this fake API and then we created our NPM
script.
In this case called server to then run that package and then watch the file where we actually have this
question's data as an array.
So this array right here.
And so then here inside our application, we use the Useeffect hook to fetch that data on the initial
render.
Then to store that data in state.
This time we used the Usereducer Hook.
And so then we created the initial state object and the reducer.
So that's pretty standard stuff.
So we have the questions array and we have a status.
And of course, as we keep building the application, we will add a lot more information here.
So we will add like 3 or 4 more pieces of state.
But for now, we are just working with these two.
And so then as soon as our data is successfully fetched, we dispatch the action here where we tell
our reducer that the type of the action is data received, and then as the payload, we pass in the
actual data.
And so then our reducer receives that action and handles it right here.
In this case where we then assign the payload.
So that data that we received from the API onto the questions array.
But that's not all, because at the same time we now were able to set our status to ready here all in
one go.
So just with the call of one dispatch function.
Now the advantage of this reducer is of course not really clear yet because we only have these two cases
yet and only these two state variables.
But it will become really clear and really helpful as we go through this section.