So with our reducer now in place, it's time to handle the different states that the application can
have.
So remember that at the beginning our application is in the loading status.
So that's how it starts.
And then when we receive some data, the status changes to ready.
And so that's when we will then want to display the list of questions.
And also there can be an error.
And so then the status changes to error.
And so now we want to display different UIs for these three situations and all of these situations will
be always displayed inside this main component right here.
So let's get rid of this.
And now we will conditionally display some components.
And so here we can use state dot status.
But that's maybe a bit too much work.
And so let's actually destructure our state object.
Now, we could do that outside, so creating these variables here, but we can do it on the fly.
So basically right here with nested destructuring so we can have.
The questions and the status state destructured right here.
And so now state of course, no longer exists, but we have status and so now we can just check.
For example, if it is loading and if it is, then we want to display something.
Now, in this case, we want to show a loader.
And I actually also already have that loader component here.
So it's again, a very simple presentational component.
And so there was no need to create it from scratch.
So it doesn't even receive any props.
And the same thing also for the error component.
So exactly the same thing doesn't receive props, has no state.
And so I thought we could save some minutes and not write them manually here in the video.
So here, if the status is loading, we want to display that loading component.
And let's include that here.
But just duplicate this line.
And actually it's called loader.
And then let's also already import the error.
So here that is loader.
And then we have some problem here.
State is not defined.
But while I'm using state nowhere, maybe let's just try to reload and that fixes it.
Okay.
And now we can just do the same thing again because these different states are, of course, mutually
exclusive.
So we don't need any ternaries or even nested ternaries.
So only this one or this 1 or 1 of the next ones will be true.
And yeah, so we can just use the end here.
All right.
But here, let's use the error and let's already try this out.
So let's see if we briefly see the loading.
And we saw.
But it was very short.
So just to make sure, let's do some throttling here.
So make our app a little bit slower.
It does can be a bit smaller.
Yeah, There we go.
So there we are, loading our questions.
And now let's also pretend that we have a no network connection so that we are offline.
And so then when we reload, well, then of course the entire page doesn't work.
So that experiment actually doesn't really work.
But so to check the error state here, let's again quit our fake API.
And so then we should see some error and indeed.
Now hear this dispatch was called with this event type here, which then set our status to error.
And so therefore, then we got this error component.
But of course, let's restart our server.
And so then.
It should be back to working?
Yes.
Okay.
And we have another state or status that we can handle, which is the ready status.
So ready basically means that the questions have arrived and that we are ready to start the quiz.
So status ready.
And here we will want to create yet another component.
So let's just check that out.
So here in the demo and this actually is what we want to show in the very beginning, so when the app
is ready.
So when we load the app, you briefly saw the loading indicator there flash.
And then this here is the start screen.
So just with this text number of questions and then the button to start.
So very simple stuff.
So let's create a new file here for that component.
And I'm going to call it the start screen.
JS.
And then again using that snippet RFC, which by the way stands for React Functional component.
And so here let's place some text.
So starting with welcome to the React Quiz.
Like this.
That any paragraph with the number of questions, let's just place an X for now.
To test your react.
Mastery.
And then this div should actually have the class name of start.
And here let's use an H three instead.
And then finally.
Also that button which says, let's start.
Okay, so that's enough for now.
And then let's indeed include that right here.
So start and then here vs code this time actually suggests the import for us.
So you can see that here by the path name to the file.
And so if we click that then that import is nicely automatically added.
So if we save this now, then here we go.
So we basically reacted or we handled to that ready status there.
Now, what we want here is actually the number of questions.
And so that's basically the length of the questions array right here.
So the questions array has the length of 15.
And so 15 is what we want to see there.
So where do we calculate that value?
Should we maybe place it here also into our state object?
Well, that's actually not necessary.
So just like we have always been doing, we can just calculate derived state right here in the app component
because in fact this is just derived state because we can simply calculate it from the question array
itself.
So let's just do num questions is just equal.
Two questions.
So it should be questions here.
Let's see.
Yeah, it's questions everywhere.
So just questions dot length.
And of course, we could also pass the entire array into this component, but there's really no need
to.
And also we will need this in other places.
So let's pass the number of questions equal to number of questions.
So then we can receive that here.
So destructuring.
And then num.
Questions.
And finally.
Num questions here as well.
And beautiful.
Now we get 15 questions.
Like this.
And now all we need to do is to add some more class names here, which is the BTN and BTN UI class.
And as always, feel free to check those out in the CSS file.
Okay.
And so with this, we actually fulfilled our goal for this lecture.
And so in the next one, we will then finally start our game or our quiz by clicking here.