Now it's time to implement the functionality of starting a new quiz.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, after we click here on this button, we basically want to display the first question here inside
this main component.
So basically right here and since we have been using this status state here to basically decide what
will be rendered in the main, all we have to do now is to change that status to something else and
then display that question here.
And let's actually start with that.
So let's say if the status was.
Active.
Then here we want to display the question component.
So that component doesn't exist yet.
And so let's create it.
So yet another.
The component file here.
Let's close that and then our nice snippet again.
So here I will just write question for now.
And then of course we need to import that.
Okay.
Well, that's not correct.
But yeah, now it is.
So here, remember that Active is one of the five different states that the application can have.
And so now we are here basically handling that active state.
So right here.
So again, we are using these different status to decide what will be displayed here in this main part
of the app.
And it's a bit like a flow as well.
So first the status is loading.
Then we display this in case there was an error.
Then we display this.
But if everything went well, well, then we display the next one.
And then once the user clicks here, then we display the next one.
So this question right here.
But now the question is how do we actually set this status to active or in other words, how do we now
start the game?
Well, all we have to do is to create basically a new action type here in our reducer, which will set
the status to start or to active actually.
So let's create a new action type here.
And let's call this one start.
And so here we want to return.
A new state, as always, which is comprised of the current state and the status set to.
Active.
All right.
And so now it's very easy.
We just have to dispatch an action from this button here with the action type of start that we just
created.
So we're going to do that here.
So here we will want to dispatch that action.
And so therefore, we now need access to that dispatch function.
So it needs to be a prop.
And so let's pass that here into the start screen.
And so as you see, we are basically passing the dispatch function around just like before we were passing
around event handler functions or the set state functions.
Right.
So if we were still using use state, then we would now probably create some new event handler here
and then we would pass that event handler into the start screen.
But now we don't need to do any of that anymore because we are handling all the state transitions in
the reducer.
And then all we do is to pass the dispatcher functions around because then it's very easy.
All we have to do here is to then call that dispatch function with the action that we want to dispatch.
So creating a new function here, as always.
And then.
Dispatch.
Antitype of the event will be as we just defined earlier start.
And this should actually be enough.
So if we click here now, then the question component should be displayed instead of this.
So let's see.
And bam, there it is.
So here we finished this component.
And so actually we finished what we wanted to do in this lecture.
So we're going to leave the actual displaying of the question for the next one.