So let's now render and display the current question.
So of course we will not render all the questions at the same time here, but instead one by one.
And so therefore we need a way of knowing which the current question is.
So basically we need some way of keeping track, which question is the current one?
And so let's add a new piece of state to our initial state here.
And we could call this the current or the current index, but I would like to just call it index.
No.
Okay.
At this index starts at zero because we will use this index here to take a certain question object out
of the questions array.
And so the first element of this questions array is element number zero.
Therefore, our index starts at zero.
And so then in the future, at some point, if we want to display the next question, we can already
imagine that we will do that by changing this index.
So then in the future, when we change that index from 0 to 1, that should display the next question.
So it should then rerender the screen and therefore this needs to be a state variable.
All right.
So that's the reasoning behind why we need this variable right here or this piece of state and also
why it needs to be state in the first place.
And again, it's because it needs to rerender the screen once it is updated.
But anyway, let's now take this index to pass in the right question object into our question component.
So this component will, of course, need access to that current question.
And as we just said, that will be questions.
So the array at the current position, which is index.
Okay.
Now here, that is not available because we haven't yet Destructured.
This index out of the state.
But there we go.
And now let's go to this component.
And just like before, if I hit the command key and then click here, it will automatically go to that
component even if it is in another file.
All right.
So here, let's now receive that question.
And then let's display it.
Well, first, let's even take a look at the shape of this object so that we actually know what we are
dealing with.
So let's come to the console and as we click here, that should appear.
So inside the question we have the question property.
So that's what we want to use first.
So here we have basically question dot, question.
And so with this, we get the question already here in the UI.
Great.
But then we also have this array of the options.
And so next we will want to loop over this array and of course display these options as well.
Now this time I will not use a unordered list for that because we will not have list elements but actual
buttons.
So here, let's.
Call this the options.
And so then here we loop over question.
Dot options.
And then dot map.
So here each of them is a question or actually it is an option.
And so then for each of them, what I want to do is to return a button with the class name of BTN and
BTN.
Upton.
No.
Okay.
And then as for the text, it should simply be the option itself, because as we see, this is just
a simple string.
So each of the options is just the string.
And so that's already looking great.
Let's just see what we have here.
Ah, of course we are missing the key property.
So very important for optimization, as we have already learned at this point.
So the options are unique and therefore we can use each of them as a key.
So as we reload, then let's start.
And there is our first question together with the options.
Nice.
Now here.
Actually, I would like to split this component into.
So whenever there is a list like this, I personally prefer to have a smaller component in a situation
like this.
So based on the logical separation of the content of this component, I would say that we can now split
this component.
So let's grab this entire part and let's create a new component.
And actually we are creating so many components that it is a common practice to create a new folder
called components.
And so this is where we then create a components.
So let's do this one right here and then I will later put all the other ones there as well.
So options dot JS.
And then our snippet again.
And here we already have the X.
So let's place that there.
Now here, this is missing the question.
But let's first of all place all the other components into this components folder.
So that's app the date counter error header.
Loader main question and start screen.
So we already have a lot of components here.
And so let's place them all in there.
Now, of course we will have a problem in the Index.js file because it is still trying to read the app
component from the same folder as before.
But so now it's in the components folder.
So we need to change that here.
But then all the other will still work because we are importing them here inside App.js.
And so here we are importing them from the same folder.
And so that's why this still works.
No.
Right.
But anyway, coming back here to our options here, we now need to receive the question.
And so then, of course, we need to.
Pass it in there.
So we need to even import that here.
So options.
And then with the current question and then just importing that here.
So import options from.
And again, it's the same folder.
And let's test.
And there we go.
Now, of course, when we click here now, nothing happens.
And so that's what we will take care of in the next video.