Let's now put some of the things that we just learned in the previous lecture into practice and also
magically synchronize our search query with the movie search results.
And actually want to start this lecture with a couple of experiments.
And to do that, let's first do a couple of changes here.
First, let's set this back to Interstellar.
And I also want to rename this variable here to temp.
Query.
And that's because now we actually want to get the query state that right now lives here inside search
into the app, so into its parent component.
So let's cut this from here and we will then later pass in both of these back in.
So query and set query.
Okay.
So we're basically lifting this date up because we will need it here inside the app component.
So now let's pass those props in.
So that's query equals query.
And set query is, of course.
Set while not error.
Set query.
Apparently I wrote the name of the movie Wrong here.
Interstellar.
And then also, let's get rid of this console dot log here.
Okay, let's reload.
Just to clean this up.
And now let's do those experiments that I was talking about.
So basically, I want to write a couple of effects here, and then I want you to guess in which order
they will be executed.
At least that's going to be our first experiment.
So let's write one effect.
And then as always, we need to specify a function.
And this one will lock to the console.
The string A.
All right, then let's get another one.
And notice how this one doesn't have a dependency array.
Well, let's actually add it to this one.
But the second one here won't have any.
So this one will just lock the string be.
And then finally.
I will simply do a console dot log right here in the top level.
Okay.
And now, without running this code, let's try to guess in which order these three strings here will
appear in the console.
So have you thought about it?
Well, I will now save.
And then we will discuss the results.
Okay.
And actually, we have a lot of renders here, a lot of results, but that's because the application
has rendered and re rendered a couple of times.
And so then we got all these logs.
And also keep in mind that these effects actually run twice.
But what matters here is that first we got C, then A and then B.
So why did we get C first, even though it appears later here in the code?
Well, the reason is that, as we just discussed before, effects actually only run after the browser
paint.
While the render logic itself runs well, as the name says during render.
And so then it makes sense that of course, this console dot log here is executed first.
So during the render of this component and then we have A and B, which comes from these two effects.
And so A is rendered first simply because it appears first in the code.
Okay, Now let's actually clear the console.
And now what I'm going to do is to type something here.
And so let's see what happens then.
And we get some more outputs.
So we get C and B, So is this what you were expecting?
Well, let's again analyze what just happened here.
So we updated the state here, which is the query state, and as a result the component was re rendered.
And then just like before this code here was executed.
And so therefore we see the letter C first and then after that we also have a B log.
And so that is this effect here, which has no dependency array, which remember basically means that
this effect is synchronized with everything.
And so therefore it needs to run on every render while this other effect here, this first effect is
synchronized with no variables at all, which is the meaning of this empty array.
And therefore this effect was not executed as the component was re rendered with the query state.
Okay, so now we can change here the strings and we can actually say that this here is during render.
This year is after every render.
And this is after.
The initial render.
No.
Okay.
And of course, this is only for you to keep as a reference here, just so we're understanding what's
actually happening.
So now let's do another one.
So one final experiment here, which will be yet another effect.
Let's call this one D.
Now, in here, in the dependency array, we will have the query state.
So give it a save.
And now watch what happens when I type here.
So you see that this one here during render, of course, always gets executed.
Then this one here after every render as well, and still not this one.
But we now have this other effect which is synchronized with the query state variable.
And so this query just changed and therefore this effect was executed and logged.
And if we keep doing this, then D keeps getting logged to the console.
While if we changed some of these other states here, then we would not get the logged here.
So we cannot really simulate that here now.
But you can still trust me on that one.
But anyway, let's now use what we just did here to our actual advantage in the application.
So I will now.
Just comment these out.
And reload here.
And so now the time has come where we actually want to use the query from here, right inside this URL
where we fetch the movies.
So basically we want to fetch movies based on the search query right here.
So instead of the temporary query, let's now use query here.
Give it a safe.
But of course, like this, it is not going to work.
So as we change this here to something, nothing is going to happen.
And why is that?
Well, it's because this effect is not yet synchronized with the query state.
So we are using this state variable inside the effect, but the effect doesn't know yet that it will
have to rerun each time that the query state changes.
And so to fix that, we need to include that query here in the dependency array.
And actually you see already that React is complaining.
So here as we hover, we see that this hook has a missing dependency.
So this error or this warning actually is really, really helpful so that we never forget to correctly
declare the dependencies of this effect.
And so as we give it a safe now, let's again reload it here.
Now we get this error that the movie is not found, which is because our query by default is just this
empty string.
But if we try now, let's say test then, well, it still doesn't work.
So let's come again to our network tab.
So let's just check out if actually the Http request has been correctly made.
And so by doing this, you're also learning about these very important developer tools here.
Okay, so here we see some new Http requests.
And as we click here, we actually do see a response.
So there is something there.
But somehow our movies are still not being shown here.
And I think I know the reason for that, which is that we are never resetting the error state.
So at some point we had some error here, but now we no longer have an error.
But at no point in the application we are actually resetting it.
So we need to also do that here in the finally or actually better yet, we should do it right here at
the very beginning.
So basically always before we start fetching for data, we reset the error.
So set error.
And then back to the empty string.
Give it a save.
And now we get some results for test.
No.
Okay.
And then as we delete this, then we are back to movie not found.
The same for Inter for some reason.
And then stellar.
And now we get some movie here.
It's not the same as before.
And the reason for that is something called a race condition, but at least something is working here.
So if I write this a bit slower, then it works just fine.
And of course, this works with any other movie as long as for now you type slow enough.
Now I want to fix this problem that when we have no search query here, then it tells us movie not found,
which is not really true.
I mean, it is true because the API actually searched for a movie with an empty string.
But in this situation where we have no query, we actually don't even want to search.
Right?
And so let's do that here in our effect.
And actually, let's do it before we even call this function here.
So we can say if there is no query dot length.
So it's going to be zero in this situation.
Then simply set.
Two movies back to an empty array.
So basically then removing all the movies from the user interface.
And let's also reset the error.
Back to nothing and then return.
And so in this situation, then the fetch movies function will not even be called.
And here we can actually go even further.
So we can say like if the query length is less than three, then it's not even worth searching as well.
So it doesn't even make sense to have a query just like this, right?
So there's no movies really called like that.
So going back again to our network tab.
If we just type like this, you see, then no new fetch requests were made.
But now if I keep writing.
So now we have more than three characters.
Then we had our first Http request to the API.
Then we got these results.
And if I type again, then you see we got another one.
And now when I delete all this, then it simply goes back to empty.
So we deleted all the movies from our state, basically.
Okay.
And so with this we have the basic functionality already implemented.
So let's recap what we just did here and what is going to happen whenever we type a new query here.
So the query is, of course, a piece of state, right?
So that is pretty obvious.
And so we are referencing that query variable a couple of times inside our effect here.
Right.
And so therefore we then included this query variable also in the dependency array of this effect.
And so now our use effect hook is basically like an event handler that is listening for the query to
change.
And so then when it changes, the entire effect is executed again, which in our case means that a new
request is going to be made to our movie's API.
So again, this effect that we just wrote here basically reacts to an update to this state variable,
which makes the entire effect basically reactive, so reactive to that state.
But at the same time, our effect will also be still executed during the initial render.
Just right now.
That is the empty string which we just basically told our effect to ignore.
So let's write another amazing movie here.
And so as we save this now and so as our application first loads, it will immediately fetch the data
right here.
And so indeed, as we just learned in the previous lecture, this effect basically now runs on the initial
render and whenever this date variable here updates.
So it is synchronized with this variable here.
And as you see, this is really, really powerful and can be used in all kinds of situations.
So make sure that you really understand everything that we just did here as this was a really, really
important lecture.
And then let's move on to the next video where we will finally add the ability to select one of these
movies so that we can then load some additional details here into the right side.
So that's going to be really, really fun.
And so I hope to see you there soon.