Let's keep working on our application and allow users to select a movie so that they can see some details
about it.
So checking our demo app, what we want to do now again is to add the ability to select a movie like
this.
And so then our app will load some additional data about that movie and display it here.
And then we can also go back by clicking on this button, which will then close that movie.
All right.
So basically that is adding some more dynamics to the application.
And so what that means once again, is that we need a new piece of state.
And so that state will basically store which movie has been selected here.
Now the selection itself.
So updating the state will happen here in this box on the left side.
Right.
But the displaying of the movie happens here on the right side.
So in this box.
So this box will also need to know about the selected ID.
And so this means that this new piece of state, so the selected ID state will have to live here in
the parent component.
So right in app.
So select ID.
ID and set.
Selected ID.
Use state and we are going to start with null.
And here it's, of course, selected.
Then here, let's get rid of this, which we don't need anymore.
And now you might be wondering why.
Here we are only going to store the ID and not the entire movie object itself.
Well, the reason for that is that the movies that we get here from the search are very limited.
So we only get the data really about the title the year and the poster here.
While here on the right side, we will want all kinds of details that are not included in this first
search.
So there will have to be another API call and we can see that here when we click it loads the movie
again.
And so only then all of these details here are fetched and this fetch here.
So this movie will be fetched based on the ID that we got here in this array.
So let's take a look at that quickly.
So it's very important that you understand how we actually built this application.
So it's not just about the React concepts themselves, but also about the logic of how we build an application.
So I think that's also pretty important.
So.
Let's see.
So taking a closer look at our results, each of the objects has the poster, the title, the Type the
Year and the ID.
And again, it's based on this ID that we then will search for details.
And actually, let's copy this ID here and I will.
Temporarily use that here.
All right.
So just so we can see what happens when we actually have a selected movie.
Then we no longer need this.
And now let's create a new component.
And so that component will then be displayed if there is a selected ID.
So basically that's like a selected movie.
So movie list movie.
Let's do it right here.
Function selected movie.
And this one will get as an input as you can guess, the selected ID.
So here, let's for now just return a div with the class name of detail.
And then for now, all we are going to do is to display that selected ID in there.
All right.
And now going back up here into our DJs here on the right side, we now want to display not this, but
instead that component that we just created in case that there is a selected ID.
So let's wrap all of this into a JavaScript code block and then let's do a ternary operator.
So all we have to do is to say, if there is an selected ID, then display movie detail.
So not sure why that's not appearing here.
Maybe I gave it some other name.
My selected movie.
Well, actually, I wanted to call it movie detail or movie details even.
So that makes a bit more sense, I think.
Yeah.
So movie details.
And then we pass in the selected ID.
Okay.
And if not, then that's where we want to display these two.
However, this is not going to work.
So let's see.
And indeed, once again, it's because here we have a piece of JS X, So all this which has basically
two root elements so it doesn't have just one single parent element which remember is always necessary
in a piece of JS.
And so this is yet another great use case of a fragment because of course we don't want to create like
a new div element or something like that around these two.
So just like this.
And again, the reason for that is here as the third part of the ternary operator, we needed a new
piece of JSX, which cannot have two elements as the root element.
And so we just created one root element with the fragment.
Okay, so now we can indeed see this ID that we passed in.
So the selected ID, but of course we don't want this to be hardcoded.
So let's set it back to null and then this will disappear.
Indeed.
And so the final step, as always, is to update the state.
So where are we going to do that?
Well, basically, as the user clicks one of these movie objects or actually movie components.
So let's go to the movie component then.
And let's do that here with the trick where we hover and then command or control click.
So movie list.
And then right here on the movie on the fly, we can attach the on click handler.
However, we don't have access to any function here yet, so let's first go back and create that function.
So let's do that.
What may be before the effect.
Okay, so let's do that here.
So this is just what we have done many times before, which is in the component that owns the state.
We write some event handler functions that we then pass down to some child component to update the state
in the parent.
So here.
Now we'll call it handle select movie.
And so then this will pass in a movie ID.
Set selected ID to that ID, And so we could also have simply pass down the set selected ID.
But I think like this, it is a little bit cleaner in some situations.
All right.
So it's cleaner, in my view, because like this, we give it a really clear name and so then we know
exactly what's happening.
Ah, of course we didn't pass it yet into the movie.
So.
That movie is inside movie list.
And so we need to pass it there first.
So here we are going to need a little bit of prop drilling.
But if it's just one level, then that's not a big deal at all.
So let's call this here on Select.
Movie.
Will be handle select movie.
And then let's just grab this move to our movie list.
Then we accept that prop here and pass it right into the movie.
So just like we have been doing so many times.
Except that here and then here, we need to create a brand new function.
Remember, not just calling a function now, okay?
And then we pass in the movie dot IMDb ID so we can see that right from here.
So in each of the movie objects, the ID has this name right here.
Okay.
Give it a save.
And now let's see what happens.
So we click here, then we get this ID, then we get another one.
And then here we get this, which is exactly the same as this one.
So this is working great.
The only thing I noticed is that here we don't have these styles, which here we have.
Let me just see if we are missing.
If we are missing some styles here.
And apparently this list here also needs the list.
Of movies class, so I forgot that one earlier.
And yeah, so now as we hover over each of these movies, we get this nice highlighting.
Okay.
And now just to finish, let's quickly add the ability to also close basically the movie detail, which
is simply to set the selected ID back to null.
So.
Let's create that function as well.
So handle.
Close.
Movie and this one doesn't need anything because all it will do is to set the selected ID.
To null.
Okay.
And then, of course, we need to pass this function into the movie detail.
So right here on close movie.
And then let's grab that move there.
Pass it in.
And now let's just create a button here.
And this one has the class of btn a back.
And on click.
Well, it's simply on close movie.
And so since in this case, we are not passing in any ID here or anything, there's no need to create
a new function.
So of course we could do this, which would be exactly the same thing.
But that doesn't make sense in this case because again, there is no need to pass anything into this
function.
So let's just do this.
But of course, we also need some content into that button.
So let's use this entity, which means left arrow.
And there we go.
So if we click this, then we go back to what we had before.
Now, finally, we could also implement that when we click here again.
Then it will also close the movie.
So of course, if we click on one of the other ones, then we see the ID here change.
But if we click on the same again, we could also make it so that the movie then closes.
And so let's do that to finish this lecture.
So going back here, that's not too hard.
So right here we can simply do a ternary operator.
So basically we can ask if the ID is equal to the current one, then set the new selected ID to null.
So this means that we will now set the new state based on the current one.
So let's just use the callback.
So selected ID, and then we just say ID equal to the already selected ID, and if so, set the new
one to null and otherwise to the passed in ID.
So let's try that.
And if I click again, then it closes.
Beautiful.
And so with this, we are now ready to, in the next lecture, actually fetch the movie that corresponds
to the selected ID here.