So let's now load movie details about individual movies.
So essentially, whenever this movie details component here is going to mount, we will want to fetch
the movie corresponding to the selected ID.
So basically loading the currently selected movie.
So since we want to do that, each time that this component mounts, that means that we will want a
use effect.
Right.
So our effect function.
And then, as I just said, we want this to happen each time the component renders.
And so that's simply the empty dependency array.
Now.
Okay?
And now we want an async function.
And so.
Well, let's actually write async.
So async function.
And let's call this one get movie.
Details.
Okay.
And now let's actually come here to our API documentation.
And so now here what we want to do is to search by ID.
So here the parameter is.
Now this I.
Which will receive exactly this type of IMDb ID that we have been working with.
So let's actually grab.
The fetch from here because it's very similar.
So basically just this.
And.
Let's place it right here.
And so now this is why we had the key in a separate value, because here we, of course, need that
key again.
Now, here it is.
I and then it is here, the selected ID.
All right.
Now you see that vs code and eslint are already complaining here, but we will for now not give them
what they want, basically.
So we first want to see what's going to happen.
So then let's grab the data here from the response and of course, await this data.
And then for now, let's just log it to the console.
Okay.
And this should already be working at this point.
So let's reload.
And nothing happens, of course.
I mean vs code is even telling me about it by saying that I didn't.
A call.
The function there.
So let's try that again.
And immediately, actually, it loaded my movie here.
So we see that this time we actually get all this data about the movie, which again, we didn't get
simply here when we searched for the movies.
Okay.
But now we want to get some of this data here into our visible user interface.
So in the visible part of the component.
And so how do we do that?
Well, as always, we need a new piece of state.
So movie and set movie.
And here the default will now be an empty object because an object is exactly what we got back here
from this API call.
And so now instead of logging that to the console, let's just do set movie to the data.
All right.
And so now we should be ready to use that data here in our.
So actually, let's destructure now the object, because I really don't like these variable names here.
All uppercase.
I have no idea why they did it this way.
So we will basically now destructure data out of this movie.
So the title.
We will call title in our own code.
Then we will want the year.
Which is simply called here.
We will want the poster.
We want the runtime.
We want the IMDb rating as well.
So this one is actually correct.
We want the plot.
The released date.
So released like this.
The actors array.
Director.
And finally, also the genre of the movie.
Okay, so we have all these variables which you see we haven't used yet.
Let's just use them here in or a rendering logic just so I can see you.
What's going to happen?
So maybe the title and the year.
And so let's reload.
Let's select this one.
And then you see that first we get undefined, undefined.
And then after a second we get the indeed the title and the year.
So why is that?
Well, here in the very beginning, of course, when the component is initially mounted, then the movie
is still this empty object here.
And so then title and year read from that empty object are simply undefined.
So then this effect here starts and it gets the movie and will then store it into our movie state.
And so then the component is rerendered.
And then of course, this object is no longer empty.
And so then the rendering logic here will read all of this data out of the object.
And so then we successfully log that to the console over here.
All right.
But anyway, let's now actually use this right in our JS here.
So let's start with a header element.
So not.
A component, but really an element.
And in there we have an image, which is the poster.
And then the alt image or the alt tag, actually.
So poster of.
The movie.
So this is a template literal, so it works a bit differently.
So what's the problem here now?
Oh, of course.
I didn't close the image.
Next we have a div with a class of details overview and so in vs code we can actually just type dot
and then the class name then hit tab and well that should.
Uh, actually then create a div with that class.
So that has always worked.
For some reason now that's not working, so let's just do it manually then.
So H2 for the title.
And here we are typing a lot of JS and if you don't want to do that then you can just.
I get the code here from the final files of this lecture?
So here we want the run time.
All right.
Released is not defined.
Re.
Well, I didn't type that correctly.
Now that's already starting to look like something there.
Uh, yeah.
Let's keep going here.
Next up, we have the genre.
And then also the rating.
So here we're going to have like a star emoji.
And then here basically just the IMDb rating.
Let's actually write that there.
IMDb.
A rating.
Yeah, that's looking really nice.
So that's the header part here.
And so now let's do.
A section.
Element like this.
So a paragraph in there.
I want some emphasized text, which is going to be the movie plot.
Then starring the actors.
So this is just a string.
And then just directed by the director.
All right.
And there we go.
Nice.
We still have the selected ID here, which we now no longer need.
All right.
And now there's just one thing missing.
So if you come here, you see that we have this rating component.
And does this look familiar to you?
Well, we spent like an hour or more building that.
So hopefully this is still familiar to you.
And so let's actually now grab that star rating component that we built earlier.
So let's write star rating and thought that it would actually get automatically imported.
But let's then do it manually.
So I think it should be right here in the same folder.
Yeah.
So import star.
Reading from and then star.
Rating.
Okay.
Now, here we need the dot for the relative file.
And there it is.
Now it is a bit too big.
And also we want ten stars, not just five.
So on IMDb, if you know the site, then you know that their movies are rated from 1 to 10.
That's also why we have here the 8.8.
So here we can now use that API basically that we built for this component.
So that's max rating to ten and then the size of 24, let's say.
So that's half the size by default, I think.
And then let's also place this into a div with a class name of.
Rating.
Okay.
Beautiful.
Now, of course, for now, this rating is not being stored anyway or anywhere.
And so if we reload now, then of course it is gone.
But for now, the component here is working pretty nice, isn't it?
But watch what happens if I now try to select another movie here.
So let's say this one.
So nothing happened, right?
Now, if I close this and then open up the second one here, for example, then you see that it's working
fine.
But again, if I now click on another one, then we get the same problem or component here is not updating.
So why do you think that is?
What might be happening here?
Well, we told our effect here to load the movie data whenever the component first mounts.
Right.
However, when we click here on one of these other movies, this component is actually not mount again.
So the initial render will not happen again because the component is already mounted.
Now, the reason for that is the one that we learned in the previous section.
It is because this component here so the movie detail component is rendered in exactly the same place
in the component tree.
And so as we click here on another movie, simply another prop will be passed into the component, but
the component itself will not be destroyed.
It will stay in the component tree.
And so the only thing that is changing as we click on one of the other movies is the ID prop that is
being passed in.
So the selected ID prop, that's the only thing that is changing.
And so therefore, right now this effect here will not run again because again, it is only running
when the component mounts, which really only happens once.
Now, of course, if I close this and then go to another one, then the component has been unmounted
first and then it is mounting again.
And so therefore then it is going to work.
So how do we solve this?
Well, the answer lies again, right here in the dependency array.
So here if we now pass in the selected ID, which is the prop that changes, then let's see what happens.
So you saw that.
Now it did actually work.
And so the reason is that now as the selected ID prop changes, then the effect will indeed be executed
again, because remember, this dependency array is a little bit like an event listener that is listening
for one of the dependencies to change.
And so now as we click on another movie, this prop here will change.
And so yeah, our effect is then executed again, which gives us exactly the functionality that we were
looking for.
So that's really great and a really powerful and it's therefore also really important to understand
how exactly this dependency array works.
And now just one final thing, which is that watch what happens when I click on one of the other movies
actually here.
Well, probably you cannot really see it because you can't really see when I click.
But there is a visible delay between the click and something changing here.
And so of course, that's because in the background the movie needs to be fetched.
So just like before, what we want now is a quick loading indicator just to let the user know that something
is happening.
And so let's do that exactly as before.
So we create a new is loading state and then set is loading.
And we start with false.
Yeah.
Then.
Immediately before we start fetching.
We set isloading to true and as soon as it is done.
We set it back to false.
So just as simple as this.
And by the way, in this time here, we are not handling errors.
But you could do that just like we did in the beginning.
So if you want, you can just go ahead and copy that, basically.
But here, in order to save some time, I will just ignore the possibility of there being an error.
But anyway, let's now use that loading state.
And so let's do it right here.
So inside the details.
So we always want to return this div here.
But if.
We are still loading.
So it's loading.
Then we want to now use again our loader components.
So a reusable component.
But if not, then we want the header and the section and immediately you see the problem once again,
which is that this piece of JS has to.
Root elements, basically.
So it's the header and the section.
Which is not possible.
And so let's close that.
And actually here we need the JavaScript mode.
And yeah.
So you see the loading indicator there is very short.
But of course if our network was just a little bit.
Uh, slower.
Then it makes a lot of sense to have that loading indicator right there.
Great.
So this was another very important part of our application, and we did it pretty fast because some
parts were just the repetition of before.
And we also wrote a lot of JS here.
But yeah, of course the main part is here the effect and understanding how the dependency array works.
So make sure to really get that and then let's move on and actually make this rating here work so that
we can add a movie to our watch list.