Let's now make our watched movies list work and let's do it all in one go.
So this is going to be a long one.
And so let's quickly get started.
And let's actually get started by quickly recapping what this watch list actually is.
So remember how we already have this watch state here, which right now is this empty array, but it
used to be this.
Temp watched data.
So let's close this here.
And so you see that?
Then we had these two movies with a few details with the user rating and then also this summary right
here.
Now, of course, we will start from zero here and then we can add each of the movies here to our list.
So they will then appear over there.
So we already have the list component.
So it should be somewhere down here.
So we have the watch summary.
We have the watched movie list and we have the watched movie itself.
So each of these movies needs the poster, the title, the rating, the user rating and the runtime.
So basically we need to create a brand new object for each of these movies.
And then pass each of these objects here into this watched array.
So actually, let's start by creating that function with which we can add a new item to that array.
So let's call it handle ad watch.
Then we get a movie.
Let's call this watched.
And then let's do it as always.
So we call, set, watched, and then we get the current watched movies array, and then we create a
brand new one based on that one.
So based on all the elements of that array.
And then the brand new movie object.
Okay.
And now we just need to pass that in.
So again, as a prop and you see that this component is getting really big at the same for this entire
file.
So if you want, feel free to split up this file into multiple files.
So one component per file.
But anyway, I will just keep working here.
That's all.
Let's pass that function that we just created here as on Add.
What?
Handle at what?
So we're passing that into movie details because again, that is where we will actually have the button
to add the movie to the watch list.
So it will be right here.
And so then here in this component, we set the state, it will get updated in the parent and from there
it goes back here into the statistics and then into this list, of course.
Okay, but now let's then move to the movie details component and let's add a button.
Right here.
So under this rating.
So here, let's say.
Button with the class name of BTN add.
And then add.
To list.
Now here, of course, we need our event handler and let's actually create a.
Another event handler right here, which will then call the one that we passed into the component.
Because here we actually need to do a lot of stuff.
So function handle add.
And so again, this one will then eventually call that function that we passed here as a prop.
So that was on ad watched.
So again, in the end, we will call that function here, which remember, needs a new movie object
as the input.
So new movie basically.
So like a new watched movie.
So let's create that object here.
Let's actually call it new watched movie, just so we understand what we are doing here.
So this movie object will also need an IMDb rating, and here we can simply use the one that is currently
selected.
So the currently selected ID is of course the IMDb rating of that movie that we are going to add.
Then remember, we also need the title, of course, of the movie The Year, the Poster.
The IMDb, IMDb rating.
And here we actually need to convert that to a number.
And the reason for that is that the rating needs to be a number so that we can then do the statistics
here.
So calculating the averages.
So let's just use the number function on the IMDb rating.
And finally, we also need the runtime.
Now, if we take a look at one of the movies, you see that the runtime includes the minutes here.
And so again, with this, we can then later not do any calculations.
So we need to basically split that.
So runtime dot split.
Buy an empty string, which will just get us that first part.
And then from there we can just take that first part and then we just convert everything to a number
again.
Now here we get some problem.
It's because we have a duplicate.
Key.
And that's because here of course, it is the IMDb ID.
So thinks he has lint here for letting me know.
That was a pretty big problem, actually.
So let's see if this already works at this point.
So maybe it does.
Maybe it doesn't.
But let's see.
That's your console.
So there are a lot of moving pieces here, so let's check.
So let's add this to our list.
And we didn't get any error.
So let's go back to our list.
And there it is.
I mean, there are still some problems here, but something did work, so that's great.
Now.
I think it is because down here.
We are using some of these properties with their uppercase.
Uh, letters here.
So this should be title and tidal like this.
And.
Yeah, beautiful.
The only thing that we are missing here is the stars.
And so that's actually what we're going to take care of next.
So let's go back here.
And I just remembered that actually there's something else.
So let's say we also want to add this one.
So we add it to the list, but then nothing happens.
So I think that as we click here, we should probably close this movie and then basically go back.
And so then we can immediately see the new movie that has been added.
So that's not too difficult because we already have a function for that.
So it's this handle close movie.
And so this is the function that we now want to call here as well.
As soon as a new movie is added there to that list.
So into movie details.
Ah, we already have the function there.
Well, that's very convenient.
And yeah, of course we do have it because of.
Uh, this button here.
Okay.
But anyway.
Uh, yeah, here it is.
So after adding a movie, we then want to immediately also close the movie.
Okay, let's add this.
And so there it is again.
Now, you immediately see that there is a problem because we already have the movie on the list.
But we will take care of that a little bit later.
For now, let's take care of the user rating here.
So let's maybe just reload, which will clear our list.
And.
Yeah.
So basically, we want to be able to get this rating here from the user.
And then as we add to the list, that should be the rating that should be added here to this new watched
movie.
Right?
Or in other words, we now need this state that we have here.
So like this nine rating, we need it outside the star rating component and inside our movie details
component.
So how do we do that?
Well, remember that we actually created a way of getting that state outside the component by adding
in a function.
So we defined the on set rating prop.
And so into this we can pass a state set or function.
So then we need that state setter function.
So let's create yet another piece of state here for that rating.
So user.
Rating and set user rating.
So use state.
And here let's just start at an empty string.
Okay.
Now, for some reason we are already using this somewhere.
Well, not really.
So I was saying that because it wasn't with the yellow Underline.
But anyway, let's get this set user rating and then pass it here into.
Our star rating component.
Then let's reload.
Then let's open up this.
Give a rating.
And if we now check in here in our component.
So this we haven't done in a long time.
But again, this is really helpful.
So.
Here we have.
Oh, that reset everything.
Sometimes that happens when you click.
But anyway, here in our movie details, we see all the props, like the selected ID and the state.
So here we have, of course, the movie object that has been loading.
Then we have the is loading state and finally the current rating.
So as we click here now, you see that this changes.
And so therefore, that means that now we have this state inside our movie details component.
Of course, it's also still inside the star rating.
So here we have the same.
So of course, now that changes to ten.
But now it also changed to ten in movie details.
All right.
So that's really helpful.
And so now we can just add that new state right here to that object.
So user rating.
And now as we have this user rating, we only want to allow a movie to be added to the list if the user
actually gave it a rating.
So let's translate that requirement into code.
And so what I just said is basically.
This.
So if user rating is greater than zero, then display the button.
So let's reload that here manually.
Okay.
And so now the button is gone.
But then as soon as I click here, the button will appear.
And now edit And there it is.
So there is our eight.
Now, I haven't watched any of these other ones.
Let's just give it something.
And then indeed, we get this movie with the IMDb rating and with my own rating.
And so then the average between these two is actually correctly calculated with five and a half.
Great.
Now, next up, we need to ensure that I cannot just add this movie here as many times as I want.
So of course I can keep going and I can keep going over and over again.
So now I have the exact same movie here three times in my list, and that should not be allowed.
So basically when we come here to this component, we want to check if this movie is already in the
list.
And if it is, then we don't want to display any of this here.
So then we can no longer rate it and it should then simply display the rating that we already gave.
All right.
Now, does that maybe sound like something that you might want to try on your own?
I know it sounds probably a bit scary, but I think you could actually do it.
So if you are up to speed with how the data flows through this application, I think you will be able
to do this.
So maybe take a minute or two now and then I see you back here once you are done with that.
All right.
So maybe you tried it.
And if not, that's also absolutely no problem.
So what we need to do is to now pass the watched array into that component, Right?
So that is right here.
So the watched array, we simply pass it as a prop.
And so then with that, we can check for each of these movies if it is already part of the watched list.
Okay, so let's calculate that here.
So a new piece of derived state, which is.
Is watched.
So what we need to do now is to basically check if the watched array that we need to accept here still
as a prop.
So we need to check if this array of objects includes the array that is currently selected.
So let's do that.
So what?
And let's first transform this simply into an array of IDs.
So we grab all the movies and then we simply take out the movie dot IMDb DB.
So let's just lock that to the console here just to make sure.
No.
Right.
Well, let's check that.
Somehow.
It's taking a lot of time here.
So right now, we have nothing on the watch list.
So let's add a couple of movies there.
All right.
And for some reason, we are getting undefined here.
Ah, but I see.
That's because here it should be IMDb.
I'd.
And indeed, now it works.
So we have this array now.
And so now all we need to do is to check whether this array includes the currently selected ID.
All right.
And now based on that, we will basically display this entire thing here.
So all of this.
So let's say.
If is watched.
Well, let's start with if it's not watched, then display what we have here.
And if not, then let's just create another paragraph here.
You rated this movie And then we can also later calculate or derive the rating that we actually gave.
Now here we need to return yet again.
A piece of.
With a fragment.
So just like this.
That.
Yeah.
So here is where we then place that paragraph.
So working with Jayesh, as you see, can always be a bit confusing.
And even after you have done it for years, it can still take a little bit of time.
No.
Right.
And now you see you rated this movie.
And the same with this one.
But this one we haven't rated, so it's not on our list.
So only these two.
And so for all the other ones, we can still rate them.
So we tried the third one.
And so now as we click on that again, then you see that we can no longer edit to the list.
So that option is now gone.
And so we fixed that problem.
Now all we have left to do is to then place the current rating there.
So let's again derive that from the watched array.
So let's say const watched user rating.
And then let's take watched dot find.
So we will just find the movie.
Where?
The movie dot IMDb ID is equal to the selected ID and then if that exists.
And so here we are now using optional chaining because there might be actually no movie already in the
list.
So if we haven't watched the movie then here this find method will return nothing.
So here then we need optional chaining so that the user rating is only taken from that object in case
it actually exists.
All right.
So again, pretty standard JavaScript right here.
But if that's confusing, then yeah, as I said many times, I have a review section for all this stuff
right at the beginning of the course.
So what?
User rating and.
Yeah.
Here we go.
You rated this movie seven?
Maybe let's add some nice emoji here once again.
So the star.
Where is it?
No.
Okay.
And so with this, we are now almost, almost done.
So all this works almost the same way as before.
So you see now it is here.
And our inception, for example, has the eight, which it also had here, and all the other ones have
the seven.
Okay.
And now the only thing that is left to do is the ability to also remove movies from the list.
So that's the only thing that is here in the demo app.
But which we do not have yet.
So this button right here where we click and it will then remove it from the list.
All right.
So let's go again back up here where the state actually lives.
And then.
Let's add the function for handle delete.
What?
So then, here.
Let's pass in the ID.
And then here we do it just like we always do.
So we use the current watched movies array, and then we filter out the one that we no longer want.
So we get the current movie and then if movie.imdb.id is different from the passed in ID, then that
movie will stay basically in the array.
But if it's the same, then that movie will be filtered out, so it will be deleted basically.
And so now let's pass in this function into the list here.
So that is the what?
Movies list.
So the movies.
So these movies are right here.
They are inside the watched movies list.
And so therefore, we need to pass this function into there so that we can then pass it into each of
these movie components right there.
So on delete watched.
Is handle.
Delete watched.
And let's move there.
So on delete, watched, and then let's immediately pass that down into the child component.
So on delete watched is on.
Delete.
Watched.
Okay.
And then let's go there.
Oh, that's right.
Here.
On delete.
What?
And don't worry if it's taking you a lot longer to process all of this.
So to write all the code, that's just completely normal, of course.
So when I built this app here for the first time, it also took me a few hours to build this.
So it was not nearly as fast as right now.
But of course here we cannot take like 30 hours just to build one small application, right?
But anyway, here, let's now create this button.
We need to give it the class of BTN Delete.
And then on click.
And don't forget, it needs to be a function, not a function call.
So on delete, watched.
And then all we have to do is to pass in the ID.
So once again, that's movie dot imdb id.
And that should be it.
So you see that the buttons are here and let's see.
Yes, that works and our statistics get updated.
Now here we have still this weird thing where JavaScript is like really bad at math.
Or actually this time it looks like it's not even JavaScript's fault.
But let's just fix that because that looks just like really bad.
So we should be able to just append a.
To fixed here, hopefully.
Yeah, that's a lot better.
Let's do the same here for the rating.
To fixed.
So the to here is the number of decimal points basically that we are allowing.
Uh, yeah, but anyway, that's actually it.
So you see our stats update in real time, Of course.
And now everything is back to zero.
All right.
So as I said in the beginning, it was a long lecture, but we also got a lot of stuff done.
Now, I'm aware that we moved a lot of like data up and down the tree at the same for some handler functions.
And so please, again, just make sure that you really understand what we just did here.
And with that, I think our component tree can really help you out a lot.
So just analyze all the props that all these components receive, how the state changes over time.
And so all of that will really help you out in becoming a better react developer because as I mentioned
many times before, you will also have to learn to work with other developers code.
And so then these skills of really analyzing the code and the data flow will become very handy.