In this video.
Let's change the page title in the browser to the movie that we are currently watching.
So to show you, let's again come to our demo here.
And so watch what happens here to the browser tab title as I click on one of the movies.
So you see that now the title of the page is equal to the movie that we are currently checking out.
And if I then click on another one, then of course that changes to the new movie.
All right.
And so let's do the same thing in our application as well.
Now to start, as we see, the initial title of the page is actually use Popcorn, so the name of the
application and not just React app.
So let's come into our public folder and in index.html, let's just change the title here to.
Use popcorn.
Give it a save.
And then immediately it changed up here.
Okay.
But anyway, let's now actually try to implement changing the title to the currently watched movie.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, changing the page title in the browser.
So outside here of the application is a side effect because we are very clearly going to interact with
the outside world.
So basically with the world outside of our React application.
And so again, this is then considered a side effect.
So what this means is that we will want to register a side effect using again, the use effect hook.
Now where exactly are we going to do that?
So in which component are we going to use use effect?
Or in other words, in which component do we actually want to register the side effect?
Well, thinking about it, we want this title here to change as soon as we click on one of these movies,
which will then trigger the movie details component here to mount.
And so it's in exactly that situation where we want to change the browser title here.
And so that component is where we want that effect.
So let's come to movie detail.
And yeah, so this is the component.
And so let's simply add another effect here.
So we should always use different effects for different things.
So basically that each effect has only one purpose.
So it only does one thing.
So this will be our effect.
And then we want to run that effect on mount.
Okay.
And now it's very easy.
So we can just change the title of the page in the browser by setting document dot title.
And for now, let's just use something else here.
And you see that actually it already changed to test right here.
But let's just reload.
And so then it goes back to use popcorn.
And then when I click, it changed to test.
Nice.
So that's already working.
But of course we now want the actual title there.
So let's use a template literal and then I will just write movie.
And then the actual title of the movie.
Give it a save and immediately we get Inception here.
And here in the title.
But again, let's just reload.
And you see that now it actually says undefined.
So why is that?
That looks very weird, right?
But let's think about it, because after we do that, it will actually make sense.
So our effect here will right now only be executed as the component first mounts.
Right now, at that point.
So when the component first mounts, what is the title going to be?
And remember how actually we already inspected that earlier, But let's just do that again.
So logging to the console.
Here we notice.
Well, actually, we don't notice anything, so let's just reload.
Then clear this, then click.
And so you see that initially the title is undefined, which is because in the beginning this movie
object is still empty and only after the movie actually arrives from the API, the component will rerender.
And then we have the correct title that is then logged to the console.
So moving back to our effect, basically what happens here is that again, in the beginning the title
is undefined.
And so since this effect only runs exactly once, when the component mounts, it will just stay undefined
forever.
So when the component rerenders with the correct movie object and the correct title, our effect will
right now not react to that.
So it will not be re-executed.
Now, luckily for us, we already know how to fix that, right?
So we just have to include this title variable here in the dependency array.
And so then if we give it a save, then you see that it actually changed to the correct title.
Let's just try that again.
So first we get undefined and then we get Inception, which again is because now our effect is basically
listening for this variable to change.
And when it does change, then our effect is executed again.
Now there's just one problem, which is that we actually don't want to see the undefined here in the
beginning.
So we don't want temporarily to be our movie set to undefined, but we can simply fix that by writing
if there is no title.
Then just return.
So try that again.
And yeah, that's fixed now.
Now, also, because we did this here, so we specified the title, we can now move to another movie
and it will then automatically change the title up here, which if we hadn't done this, this actually
wouldn't happen.
So let's just remove it just so I can show you.
And.
Uh, well, now, actually, we never see anything because we have this early return here.
So let's try that again.
Okay.
And now again, as I click another one, we see that the title stays at undefined.
So this component here has Rerendered.
And so the title has changed, but of course our effect did not react to that.
And again, that's because we are missing this critical dependency in the dependency array.
But now with this, it does actually work.
Great.
There's just one final problem, which is that when we go back, then you see that the movie actually
stays here in the title.
So let's do another one then.
Of course it is correct.
But again, if we go back, then the title will stay here.
So it will not go back to just use popcorn as we would probably want.
So it doesn't make any sense that now here we still have the Inception movie while we are no longer
seeing that movie.
So how could we change that?
I mean, nowhere in our code we are actually telling React to go back to the use popcorn title, right?
And right now we actually don't know how to do that yet because for that we will first need to learn
about the concept of cleaning up.
And so let's do that right in the next lecture.