So the third part of an effect is the cleanup function.
And so let's now come back to the timeline that we have looked at before and the holds that we have
left in it.
So remember that after the last effect, run the title of the page in the browser tab was set to interstellar
wars.
Right?
However, once we unmounted the movie details component, we would probably like the title to return
to the original text, which was simply use popcorn.
So just the name of the application.
But how could we do that?
How can we ensure that the page title stays synchronized with the application even after the component
has disappeared?
Well, basically what we need is a way to execute some code as the component unmounts and we can do
exactly that by returning a so-called cleanup function from the effect.
And in this case, that's simply a function that sets the title back to use popcorn.
All right.
But you see that we still have another hole here in the timeline.
And that's because the cleanup function that we return from the effect is actually also executed on
rerenders.
So right before the next effect is executed again.
So let's recap this important new information that we just learned.
So the clean up function is a function that we can return from an effect.
And I say can because the cleanup function is optional so we don't have to return one from the effect.
Now the cleanup function will run on two occasions.
First, it runs before the effect is executed again in order to clean up the results of the previous
side effect.
It also runs right after the component instance has unmounted in order to give us the opportunity to
reset the side effect that we created if that's necessary.
So remember that we have the dependency array in order to run code whenever the component mounts or
rerenders.
And now with the cleanup function, we also have a way to run some code whenever the component unmounts.
And so with this, we have the entire component lifecycle covered.
Now, you might be wondering, when do we actually need a clean up function?
Well, basically, we need a cleanup function whenever the side effect keeps happening after the component
has been re rendered or unmounted.
For example, you might be doing an Http request in your effect.
Now, if the component is re rendered while the first request is still running, a new second request
would be fired off.
Right.
And so this might then create a bug called a race condition and therefore it's a good idea to cancel
the request in a cleanup function whenever the component re renders or unmounts.
And of course there are many other examples.
So when you subscribe to some API service, you should cancel the subscription.
When you start a timer, you should stop the timer in the cleanup function or if you add an event listener,
you should clean up by removing it.
Okay.
And now to finish, let me give you one more important rule about effects, which is that each effect
should only do one thing.
So if you need to create multiple effects in your components, which is completely normal, just use
multiple use effect hooks.
This not only makes each effect much easier to understand, but it also makes effects easier to clean
up using a cleanup function.
And with that being said, let's return to our application.