So with our knowledge about the cleanup function, we can now very easily solve the problem that we
still have with our page title.
So remember that we need a cleanup function whenever the side effect that we introduced in the effect
keeps happening after the component has already been unmounted.
And so that is actually exactly our case here.
So indeed, we no longer have the Inception movie here, but the side effect is still happening.
So the title is still showing that old movie that we had selected before.
And so the cleanup function is, of course, the perfect solution for this case.
So a cleanup function, remember, is simply a function that we return from an effect.
And so let's specify a function here and then.
Return it from the effect function.
Okay.
And here all we want to do is to basically reset the document title to its original form.
So that's use.
Popcorn.
And this is all we have to do.
So let's reload.
Let's select our movie.
Then indeed, we get the title.
But as we go back or title also goes back to use popcorn.
Great.
And so this is actually all the code that we have to write to solve this problem.
But let's just do a quick experiment just so I can show you something.
So let's look to the console here also in this situation.
Clean up effect for movie.
And then the title.
And here we keep getting these random errors, which is because one of these images here cannot be found.
So that's a bit annoying, but let's just ignore that.
So let's reload.
Clear the console here.
Then select one of the movies.
And now as I go back, we already know that this function here will get executed.
And so again, that's because this component here will be unmounted.
And so that's when the cleanup function of the effect will get executed.
So our title will change and let's see what is logged to the console.
So we get cleaned up.
Effect for movie Inception.
Now it might seem obvious that we get the name here, but if we think about it, it actually might seem
a bit strange, right?
Because as we learned in the previous lecture, this clean up function here will actually run after
the component has already unmounted.
And so if that's the case, then how will the function actually remember this title here?
So again, this function here runs only after the component has already disappeared from our component
tree.
And so all the state, including the movie object, has been destroyed.
But still our function here remembers the title.
So how is that?
Well, it's because of a very important concept in JavaScript called a closure.
So basically a closure in JavaScript means that a function will always remember all the variables that
were present at the time and the place that the function was created.
So in the case of our cleanup function here, it was created by the time this effect first was created
here.
And so by that time the title was actually defined as Inception.
So in this case, the movie that we were seeing before.
So it was inception at the time this function was created.
And so therefore we say that this function closed over the title variable and will therefore remember
it in the future.
So in this case, even after the component has already unmounted.
Okay.
So that was just a bit of a theoretical explanation of what happens behind the scenes, but I think
it's pretty important to understand this idea of closures because it is really a crucial part of how
effects work in React.
And therefore, we will actually also come back to this issue a bit later.
But anyway, I also want to show you that the cleanup function runs between renders.
So basically after each render.
So if we click here on some movie and then we click on another one.
Let's say this one here.
Then you see that the cleanup function actually run again for this movie.
And so that happened right after the rerender.
Right.
Let's just clean this to watch that again.
So as I click here, there will be a rerender.
And so again, then the previous effect was cleaned up with the previous movie that we had selected
before.