Next up, we also need to clean up our data fetching because right now we're actually creating way too
many Http requests as we search for movies.
And to show you what I mean by that, let's make our window here a bit bigger.
Let's come to our network tab again.
Let's add some throttling here and then make sure that you hear in the fetch tab only.
Then let's clear all the requests that had been made before.
And then I will just very quickly search for a movie here.
All right.
And so here we can now see all the requests that have been made.
So basically, we see that we made one request for each keystroke.
So it started here, then it or whatever, then in Sep in Sept and all the way until the final word.
Now, the problem with that is that this created all these different requests that were basically happening
at the same time.
And that has two problems.
First of all, having so many requests at the same time will slow each of them down.
And second, this means that we will end up downloading way too much data because we're actually not
even interested in the data for all of these other queries.
But still, they were downloaded here.
Now, in this case, it's very, very little data.
So that's not going to have any impact.
But in another application, this might actually become a problem.
And so let's now learn how we can clean up basically our fetch requests so that as soon as a new request
is fired off, the previous one will stop.
So it will get canceled.
And actually, I forgot to mention the third big problem with having all of these requests happening
at the same time, which is imagine that actually, for example, this request here would take a little
bit longer than the other ones.
So if this request here would be the last one to arrive, let's say this one.
Well, here we then get the response if we click.
But anyway, again, let's imagine that this request for some reason took a lot longer than all the
other ones.
And so then this one would be the last one to arrive.
And so in that case, it would be the movies or the results from this request that would be stored in
our state and it would be rendered in our UI, which is of course not what we want.
We always want exactly the last request of all to be the one that matters, right?
So all these other ones, again, we are not interested in them.
But if one of them takes longer than the rest, then that one will actually become the one that we see
in our UI.
And this is actually a pretty common problem which even has the name of a race condition, because all
these requests here are basically racing with one another, seeing which one arrives first.
And so let's now fix that issue back in our code.
And the way that we will do this is by using a Native browser API, which is the abort controller,
and we will then use that abort controller in or clean up function.
So the first step for using the abort controller is to actually create one.
So let's define a new variable called controller, and then we use new.
Abort controller.
And again, this is actually a browser API, so this has nothing to do with React but with the browser
itself.
So just like the fetch function right here.
Okay.
Then here, in order to connect the abort controller with the fetch function, we pass in a second argument
where we define an object with the signal property.
And so there we pass in controller dot signal.
So it's not really important to understand exactly how this abort controller works.
This is basically just following a recipe.
Okay.
So we have our board controller and we connected it with our fetch.
And so now in the clean up function.
So a function that we return from here.
We can then, actually.
Say controller Dot abort.
All right.
And that's actually it.
So let's see that this works in practice and then we will understand what is happening here.
And we will also do some minor fixes.
So let's make this big again so we can see.
And reload the entire thing.
And immediately you see a small problem here.
But for now, let's ignore that.
And again, search for a movie.
Okay, now here we have a different types.
So we have this fetch and the fetch redirect for some reason, but we are only interested in the fetches
here.
And immediately you see that all these other ones which are not the last one, got cancelled.
Right.
And so we can also see that now we no longer have all these different requests happening at the same
time.
So this one here started basically.
And then immediately as the next one started, this one was finished, so it was cancelled.
This thing keeps popping up.
Makes it hard to explain.
And yeah, Then finally, the last one that we were actually interested in was of course not canceled.
So this one then went all the way until the end.
All right.
But here we can very clearly see that there is basically only one request happening at the time until
it then got canceled by the next one.
So let's just see why this is actually working.
So each time that there is a new keystroke here, the component gets rerendered, right?
And as we already know between each of these rerenders this function here, so the cleanup function
will get called.
And so what that means is that each time that there is a new keystroke, so a new rerender, our controller
will abort the current fetch request.
And so that is exactly what we want, right?
So we want to cancel the current request each time that the new one comes in.
And so that is exactly the point in time in which our cleanup function gets called.
And so again, the cleanup function is a perfect place for doing this kind of work between renders.
Now, the problem with this is that as soon as a request get canceled, JavaScript actually sees that
as an error.
And so that's why we then get the error here.
So basically this fetch request as it is canceled, it will throw an error which will then immediately
go here into our catch block where the error is set.
And so that's why we can also see the errors down here.
So saying that the user aborted a request, which is exactly what we have here.
However, this is not really an error here in our application and so we want to ignore that.
So what we can do in order to do that is to say if error dot name is different from abort error only,
then we actually want to set the error.
And this works because the error that is thrown here.
So this object that we then get access to will have the name property set to abort error.
And then here we use that to our advantage to again, basically ignore these errors that are of this
type.
And so only if they're not, we set the error to the one that we are interested in.
Now to make this work here, actually, we need to also set the error to an empty string after the movies
have been set.
So we basically set the error to an empty string here at the beginning and at the end as well.
Okay.
And so let's try that now.
And we're still doing that throttling.
That's why it took so much time here.
But anyway, let's just again clean this here.
And so now we never got that error, but we still got all our and again.
So we still got all our requests here cancelled.
And so no more race conditions and no more unnecessary data being fetched.
And so if at some point in the future you are going to do your own Http requests in an effect like this,
make sure to always clean up after your fetch requests in case that you have a situation where many
requests can be fired off very rapidly, one after another, which is exactly the situation that we
have here.
So here when we click on one of the movies and the data gets fetched, then usually we will not have
so many requests one after another unless we click like really fast between these movies right here.
But that's usually not going to happen.
And so therefore there is no need to clean up the fetch that we're doing here in this movie.
Details component.