Let's now implement a new small feature which will require us to listen globally to a key press event.
So let's check out what that feature is in our demo.
And so basically, it's very simple when we open up a movie here to see the details instead of clicking
here on this button to go back, we want to now implement the feature that the user can also just click
on the escape key.
So you can see that.
But I'm doing it now.
And so with this, the movie detail was then closed.
And so again, for that, we basically need to globally listen to that key press event.
So let's get to work.
And the way in which we can react to a key press event in the entire app is basically by simply attaching
an event listener to the entire document.
So let's do that here right in the app component.
And so since this is clearly a side effect because we will be directly touching the Dom, we need another
effect.
So just to show you that we are indeed in the app component.
And so let's create that effect right here.
So use effect.
Then our effect function.
And then as always, we start by saying basically that this effect should run on Mt..
And so now all we need to do is to write document, dot add event listener, which remember is simply
a Dom function.
So we are really doing basically now some Dom manipulation.
And so we are stepping really outside of react here, which is the reason why the React team also calls
the use effect hook here an escape hatch.
So basically a way of escaping, having to write all the code using the react way.
Okay.
But anyway, here, let's now listen for the key down.
Event and then as our callback function here.
We just passed in a function which receives the event and now we can simply say if the event dot code,
which is basically the code of the key press.
So if that is equal escape.
Then we will want to call our handle close movie function.
So we already have that functionality.
And so all we have to do is to call that function right here.
And let's also, just for some experiment, log here, something to the console.
So just like this.
And let's reload here.
But let's first actually come back to our network and disable any throttling.
So let's reload.
Then let's open up a movie and then let's see what happens when I hit the escape key.
And indeed, the movie here was closed and we also got our closing logged to the console.
But watch what happens right now as I hit the escape key again.
So you see, we get closing again and actually even twice.
But again, that's simply because in strict mode, these effects here are running twice.
So again, as I keep hitting the escape key, we see here by this log that actually this callback function
here.
So the event listener is still listening for the Keydown event and it will then execute this function
each time that the keypress happens, which is however, not really what we want in this situation because
we actually don't even have a movie opened here.
So basically what we want instead is to only attach this event listener here to the document whenever
we actually have the movie details in our tree.
So whenever that component instance is actually mounted.
So that's easy enough.
We just cut the effect from here.
And so after all, we want it in our movie details component.
All right.
I just started to place it there so that we could understand why we actually need it here.
And now here, of course, this function is called on Close Movie, which again, we had already passed
into this component right here.
Now here you see that actually Eslint is complaining.
And the reason for that is that we must actually include this function here also in our dependency array.
So that doesn't seem to make a lot of sense.
But we will later learn why that is.
So again, when React tells us that we need to include something here in the array, we actually must
do that.
Otherwise there might be some consequences that we do not want.
And so, again, whenever you see some warning here coming from Eslint about a missing dependency,
you must include that in the array.
So otherwise React says that you are lying about your dependencies and that of course we don't want.
But anyway, let's now try to hit the escape key again while the movie details component is not mounted.
And so now we didn't get that console dot log.
So therefore, now this function is of course not being executed.
But as I open up the movie and then I hit the key again, then you see that we get the closing log.
And of course the movie has closed.
Okay, let's do that again.
And notice how now we are getting even more of these logs here.
And let's clean that and do that again.
And a few more times.
And so you see that we get dozens of these logs here saying closing, which don't really seem to make
much sense.
So if we reload the page and then do that again, then we are back to only having these two logs, which
again come because the effect is executed twice.
But now if I close another movie, then all of a sudden we get three locks.
And so it seems like these are basically accumulating, right?
So the reason for that is that actually each time that a new movie details component mounts, a new
event listener is added to the document.
So basically always an additional one to the ones that we already have.
So again, each time that this effect here is executed, it will basically add one more event listener
to the document.
And so if we open up ten movies and then close them all, we will end up with ten of the same event
listeners attached to the document, which of course is not what we want.
And so what this means is that here we also need to clean up our event listeners.
Or in other words, we need to return a function here.
Which will call.
Or ritual execute document dot remove.
Event listener.
So basically as soon as the movie details component Unmounts, the event listener will then again be
removed from the document.
And so then we will avoid having so many event listeners in our Dom which might become a memory problem
in a larger application with like hundreds or thousands of event listeners.
So again, in this small app, of course this wouldn't be a problem, but this is just to teach you.
So to prepare you for the real life later.
Now here the function that we pass in.
So the one that we want to remove must be exactly the same as here in the Add event listener.
And so we cannot simply copy and paste this function right here.
So it must be again the same.
And so let's cut it from here.
And create a brand new function here.
Let's just give it a name of callback.
And then let's use that here.
And here.
Give it a save.
Let's reload here.
Okay.
Hit escape.
And let's try it a couple more times.
And you see that now we only get one closing each time that I hit the escape key.
Or in other words, actually, our event listener is only executed exactly once, which was exactly
the goal of our cleanup function here.
Great.
So this is how we handle key press events in a React application.
So again, we need to basically step out of the React way and back into like classical Dom stuff.
And so for that we need an effect.
So we specified our effect.
We listen for the event and each time that the component unmounts or even each time that it rerenders,
we will then remove the old event listener from the document.
All right.
And this is actually going to be the last lecture of this section.
And so let's clean up the application here a little bit before we leave this section, even though we
will actually keep working on it in the next one.
But still, let's do some stuff here now, which is to, for example, remove all of these redundant
and unnecessary console.logs.
We also have some other clean up here.
Like this.
So this one we don't need.
But maybe let's just comment this one out because this was nice for the explanation of the closure.
Remember?
And then, of course, also when we open up the app, of course, we don't want to display search results
for a predefined movie.
So in this case, for the Inception movie.
So let's remove that from state and simply start with no search term at all.
All right, then.
Here.
We should probably not lock these errors.
Here as console.error, but as a console.log.
And also when the error is an abort error, we don't even need to log anything because again, for us
those are actually not really errors.
And finally, let's now search for a movie here.
So Interstellar, for example.
All right.
So I selected the movie.
And now let's say that I search for something else.
And so in this situation, I think that it would be best to close the current movie here.
So whenever there is a new search, we simply want to close the movie.
And so that's pretty simple.
We just have to, before we fetch the movie, simply call.
Handle close movie.
And so with this.
Let's see.
So we open up this one and then let's search.
Let's see what actually turns up for Jonas.
Something about the Jonas Brothers.
Uh, yeah, but anyway, you saw that as I did a new search.
Then the movie here actually disappeared.
And the same now again.
Okay.
Now as we load the application right now.
So on the initial render of the entire app, we notice that right now we are no longer fetching any
data, right?
So we are only fetching data as a result of searching here for movies in the search bar.
So basically only as a response to this event.
And so therefore we could now actually transform this use effect that we have here into a regular event
handler function.
Because remember, that is actually the preferred way of handling events in React.
And again, this is actually now more of an event handler than anything else.
Right.
So again, if you think about that, then maybe you come to the same conclusion that maybe this shouldn't
be an effect anymore and really an event handler function.
So if you want, you can go ahead and convert that.
But it's also not really necessary because the main point of this section here was to learn about the
use effect hook.
And in many situations we do actually want to start fetching on mount.
And so in those situations, this is still a perfectly valid way of doing that, at least in small applications
like this one.
But anyway, with this, we wrap up the section.
And so now all that's left to do is, as always, a nice coding challenge so that you can practice on
your own.