So let's now learn about the next important tool in our toolbox, which is the use effect hook.
So we already know about the use state hook.
And so now it's time for our second hook, which is again the use effect hook.
Now the idea of the use effect hook is to give us a place where we can safely write side effects like
this one.
So just again, like our data fetching, but the side effects registered with the use effect hook will
only be executed after certain renders, for example, only right after the initial render, which is
exactly what we are looking for in this situation.
Now we will learn all about what this hook actually is, but for now, let's just use it in practice.
So just like with EU state we just write use effect.
And then we also need to make sure that it has been imported automatically here from React.
So just like you state again, this is also a function that is part of react and so therefore that we
need to import.
Now the use effect doesn't return anything, so we don't store the result into any variable, but instead
we pass in a function.
And so this function is then called our effect, and it contains the code that we want to run as a side
effect.
So basically that we want to register as a side effect to be executed at a certain point in time.
So let's paste that here.
But we are actually not done yet because now we need to pass in a second argument, which is the so-called
dependency array.
Now, this dependency array is actually the most confusing part of this hook.
And we will again learn all about this throughout this section.
But for now, what you need to do here is to just pass in this empty array, which means that the effect
that we just specified here will only run on mount.
So it will only run when this app component here renders for the very first time.
And so now here, let's change this back.
To set movies, give it a save.
And yeah, our movies here are now in the user interface.
But even more importantly, let's check if the problem from before has been solved.
And indeed, now we have no more infinite loops here and no more infinite requests to our API.
So the problem that we created in the previous lecture has indeed been fixed.
And so now our effect is only running as the component mounts.
Great.
And so this is basically the very bare bones way in which we do data fetching in simple react applications
like this one, at least if we want to fetch our data as soon as the application loads.
Now, in a larger, more real world application, we may use some external library for data fetching.
But again, in a small application like this one, this is now a great way to fetch some data on mount.
So when our application first loads.
So let's just quickly recap here.
So we used the use effect hook to register an effect.
And so that effect is this function right here, which contains the side effect that we want to register.
And basically register means that we want this code here not to run as the component renders, but actually
after it has been painted onto the screen.
And so that's exactly what use effect does.
So while before the code was executed, while the component was rendering, so while the function was
being executed.
Now this effect will actually be executed after render.
And so that's a lot better.
Then as a second argument, we passed this empty array here into use effect.
And so this means that this effect will only be executed as the component first mounts.
Okay.
And that's actually it.
So this is how we use the use effect hook in practice in a simple situation like this and so next up,
let's now take a bit of a closer look at this new hook.