So we just used the use effect hook for the very first time in order to fetch movie data as the component
mounts.
But what actually is an effect and how is it different from an event handler function?
Well, let's find out in this video.
And just so we're all on the same page, let's start by reviewing what a side effect is.
So basically, in React, a side effect is any interaction between a react component and the world outside
that component.
And we can think of a side effect as some code that actually makes something useful happen.
For example, fetching data from some API.
So what this means is that we actually need side effects all the time when we build React apps.
Now, we already know that side effects should not happen during the component render or in other words,
side effects should not be in render logic.
Instead, we can create side effects in two different places in React, and the first one is inside
event handlers.
And remember that event handlers are simply functions that are triggered whenever the event that they
are listening to happens.
However, simply reacting to events is sometimes not enough for what an application needs.
Instead, in some situations, we need to write some code that will be executed automatically as the
component renders.
And so this is when we can create a so called effect by using the use effect hook.
So by creating an effect, we can basically write code that will run at different moments of a component
instance lifecycle.
So when the component mounts, when it rerenders or even when it unmounts And this is really great because
it opens up a whole new door of possibilities.
Okay.
But let's now get just a bit deeper into how effects work by comparing event handlers to effects created
with the use effect hook.
And let's go back to the example of fetching movie data that we have been using.
So fetching movie data is very clearly a side effect because it's clearly an interaction with the world
outside the component.
Now there are two different possibilities of when we might want to create this side effect.
The first possibility is that we might want to fetch movie data only when a certain event happens.
So in that case we would of course just use an event handler function.
So just like we have been doing up until this point, I mean, we haven't been using event handlers
to fetch data, but we have used them for other stuff.
Now, the other possibility of when to fetch the data would be to do so immediately after the component
mounts, so after it is first rendered.
And so this is exactly what we did in the previous lecture when we first used the use event hook to
specify an effect that was executed right after the component was painted to the screen.
So we can say that these two pieces of code produce the exact same result.
So they both fetch data about a movie, but they do so at different moments in time.
So the event handler executes when an event happens and the effect executes whenever the component first
renders.
At least in this situation, because the exact moment at which the effect is executed actually depends
on its dependency array, which I shortly mentioned in the last video.
So we can basically use this dependency array to tell the effect to also run after a component Rerenders
But I won't go deep into this right now because that's easier to explain with code.
But speaking of the dependency array, this array is just one of three parts that any effect can have.
So besides the dependency array, we have, of course the effect code itself and also each effect can
return a so-called cleanup function, which is a function that will be called before the component Rerenders
or unmounts.
Now thinking about different moments of the component lifecycle.
So mounting Rerendering and Unmounting can be very helpful to understand how effects work.
However, we should actually not think about life cycles, but about synchronization.
So the real reason why effects exist is not to run code at different points of the life cycle, but
to keep a component synchronized with some external system.
So in this example, that would be to keep the component in sync with the movie data that comes from
some external API.
And if that sounds super confusing, keep in mind that this is just a first introduction to effects.
We will come back to all this after having used the use effect.
Took a bit more in practice.
But anyway, to finish our comparison here, as we just learned, we use effects to keep a component
in sync with the external world, while on the other hand, we use event handlers to react to a certain
event that happened in the user interface.
Now, what's very important to note here is that event handlers are always the preferred way of creating
side effects.
So whenever possible, we should not overuse the use effect hook.
So basically everything that can be handled inside event handlers should be handled there.