Let's now convert our effect to an async function instead of the basic promise handling that we're doing
right now.
So many times when we need a lot of code to handle a promise, it's a lot easier and nicer to just have
an async function.
And here I will just assume that you already know what async await is.
So we might think that all we need to do in order to use an async function is to place the async keyword
here and then use await inside of it.
However, we immediately get this warning from Eslint, which tells us that effect callbacks are synchronous
to prevent race conditions.
So basically the effect function that we place into use effect cannot return a promise, which is what
an async function does.
So instead of doing it directly like this, we just create a new function.
Net, then we place the async function in there.
So let's call this one.
Fetch movies.
Okay.
And then let's of course, adapt this function here to using the await keyword.
So const rez equals await and again.
I'm assuming that you already know how all of this works, so that converting to promises to an async
function is nothing new for you at this point.
So data will be the result of converting the response to Json, which is again an asynchronous operation.
And then finally, we can set the movies to data dot search.
So just what we had here.
All right.
But now, of course, nothing is happening because nowhere we are calling this function.
So that's also why this gets this yellow underline here.
So our effect is now this function right here.
Right.
But this function, all it's doing right now is to define yet another function.
So this async fetch movies.
And so then at the end we just call it and then it is back to working.
Now here I just want to extract this here for now into another variable, which I'm going to call query.
And this is just temporary here.
Okay.
And now what I also want to do is to log our movies here.
So the movies that we received from the API to the console just so I can show you something.
So let's first reload to get rid of the errors there.
And now what I want to do here again is to log our movies to the console.
So do you think that I can just do this?
So you think that this is going to work?
Well, let's see.
And let's reload to actually see the true result, which is an empty array.
So why is this happening?
Well, hopefully you learned in the previous section that setting state is a.
So in other words, after the state has been set here in this line of code or actually after we instructed
react to set the state, that doesn't mean that this happens immediately.
So instead, it will happen after this function here has been called.
And so right here in this line of code, we have stale state, which basically means that we still have
the old value as the state was before.
And in this case, before it was just the empty array.
So our initial state.
So here we can basically then use data that search again.
And so as we reload now, then we get here the output.
Now, what I wanted to talk about is why we always have these two outputs.
So basically why we have these two requests here happening.
Well, the reason for that is react's strict mode.
So when strict mode is activated in React 18, our effects will not run only once but actually twice.
So React will call our effects twice, but only in development.
So when our application is in production, this will no longer be happening.
And so this is just so that React can identify if there are any problems with our effects.
So if we come here quickly just to Index.js, and if we remove the strict mode from here.
Well, then we have this problem.
Let's actually remove the code.
Let's save and let's reload.
And then you see that we only get one output here, which means that there was only one Http request.
So the effect was only called once.
Indeed.
But let's put it back, because this is somehow a bit safer.
Okay.
And that's it for this video.
Next up, let's make this data fetching here a bit more complete with a loading state.