Let's now add a very simple loading indicator to our application.
So basically, whenever the movie data here is still being loaded in the background, we want to instead
display some kind of loading indicator right here.
And to show you what I mean, let's come here to the network tab, which is always a good friend when
we're dealing with Http requests.
And then let's throttle our network here to a slow 3G.
And so then I can either show you what I mean.
So all of this will now take a lot of time to load, but here you now see this flash where there is
no content, basically.
So the movie data was loading but hadn't arrived yet.
And so now again, in the meantime, we want to display some loading indicator.
So in order to do that, we need some more state.
So a state variable, which basically tells our UI that the data is still being loaded.
And then as soon as the data has been loaded, we want to display then the data and not that loading
indicator anymore.
But anyway, let's simply create that state variable and usually it is called is loading.
And so then set is loading.
And let's start with false.
Now then let's come here to our effect into our async function.
And so then right before the fetching actually starts, let's set is loading.
Too true.
And so this then will indicate our UI that loading is being happened and that we can then render that
indicator over there and then when all of this is done.
So let's do it right at the very end.
So this one we don't need anymore.
So here, after everything is finished, we can then set the loading state back to False.
And now it's very easy.
So here, inside this box.
We basically want to say that.
If is loading, then we want to display that indicator and I will actually create a new component for
that.
Let's call it loader.
Or else display that movie list.
Okay.
So creating that loader, that's just very simple.
We just return a paragraph with the class of loader.
And then here we can say just loading so many times in web applications, you will get like a rotating
spinner or something like that.
But you immediately saw that it was already working.
So as I save now the code, it will always refetch the data.
But let's try it again here manually.
Let's wait for it.
So now it's still the application that's being loaded.
So we get this white screen in the meantime.
But now it has started fetching the data.
Then it displayed that loader.
So that new component here.
But then as soon as is loading was set to false, it was time to actually display our movie list.
And so with this, this whole behavior is a bit more natural and also a bit more real world because
in all real applications, you always have some indication to the user that some data is being fetched.