So whenever we are doing any data fetching in any web application and dealing with asynchronous data,
we always need to assume that something can go wrong.
And so therefore let's now account for that situation by handling those errors.
So one of the things that can go wrong is your users suddenly losing their Internet connection.
So let's simulate that here again in our network tab and let's make sure that we are first on slow 3G,
then let's reload here.
And then while the movies are loaded, we will click on offline.
So right now.
So you see that Now, the application basically never leaves this state.
And also when we come to our console here, we see that we failed to fetch, which again is because
our user basically now lost their Internet connection.
So when that happens, we want to display some kind of error message here on the screen and not keep
the application in this loading state here forever, because like this, the user will think that the
data might eventually arrive, but of course it will not.
Now, reacting to errors like this is actually not built into the fetch function itself.
And so we have to kind of do that manually.
And so let's try that here in our fetch movies function.
So here on the response object that we receive from Fetch exists one.
Okay.
Property.
And so here we can check for that.
So basically, if the response is not okay, then we want to throw a new error.
And again, this is pretty standard JavaScript code.
So then let's just say something went wrong.
Would fetching movies.
Okay.
And so now if we throw an error here, we need to wrap all of our code into a try.
Catch block.
So try and.
Catch, which again is just a normal JavaScript feature.
This one has nothing to do with React.
Okay, then here let's console dot error.
That error.
Okay.
And then let's come back here.
Well, if we load now, then of course nothing will work.
So let's do that trick again.
Where?
First we set it to slow 3G.
Then let's reload and then let's wait for it.
We set our users back to offline right now.
And so where is it?
Well, it's not actually anywhere here, but.
Well, that's not really important anyway.
So let's actually just log error.message.
So this is the property of the error where this string here will get saved into.
But then what we're actually interested in is to get this message here onto the screen.
So basically displaying it right here instead of loading.
So that means that we need another piece of state.
So basically a piece of state indicating whether we currently have an error or not.
So const error and set error.
And so here, this one is actually not a Boolean, but it's truly the error message.
Okay.
So here, let's then set the error.
To actually that message.
And again, error message is basically this string that we passed into.
The error and error is the error itself as it was passed into this catch block.
And again, that is just basic JavaScript.
All right.
And then let's do some conditional rendering here to basically get the error here onto the screen whenever
there exists one.
No.
Okay.
And let's start by creating a new error component here, or maybe let's call it error message and it
will receive a prop with some message that it will then display on the screen.
So let's return again a paragraph, this time with the class name of error, which as always, I already
included into my CSS file.
Then here, let's maybe add some small emoji here.
Yeah.
Like this one.
So showing there was some kind of problem.
And then here we simply display that message.
So this is a very simple presentational component.
Remember that?
Okay.
Now, here in our conditional rendering, basically what we want to do is that when it's no longer loading,
then we want to display this movie list, but only if there was no error.
So basically here we now would have to nest another ternary inside this ternary, but that makes for
really ugly code.
And so let's do something else instead.
So let's comment out this entire part.
Well, only this one.
So the box, of course we still need.
But then let's do.
Is loading and if there is no error.
Then display this movie's list right here.
Now if there is an error.
Then display the error message component with the error, or I think it's called message.
So with the message prop set.
To error.
And here, of course, it needs to be that the data is not loading and there is no error.
And finally, we also need to account, of course, for the is loading state.
So if it is loading, then just display.
Our loader.
So here the situation is indeed a little bit tricky with all these different states that we have and
with all the conditional rendering.
But well, these are now three mutually exclusive conditions.
So it is either loading or it is not loading and there is no error or there is an error.
So only one of these three here can be true at the same time.
And so that's very important so that we don't display multiple of these components at the same time
by mistake.
So let's give it a save and let's try again.
So back to our 3G.
And then I will set it to offline very soon.
Let's wait for it.
And there it is.
So we get our error message correctly displayed here.
However, there's still some problem because the loading state is still set to true.
And in fact, that's actually correct.
So as soon as the error here is thrown, this rest of the code is no longer evaluated.
And so therefore, it's loading is never set to false.
So our application will keep thinking that the data is still being loaded.
So again, the problem is that after this error is being thrown, then React will basically never see
this piece of code here where the loading state is reset.
So instead of doing that here, let's attach a finally block here.
So this block of code here will basically always be executed at the very end.
Okay.
And as an alternative, we could have kept the code here and also pasted it here, but that would have
created a duplication of code.
So with this, it's going to be a lot better.
Now, I will not try this yet here because actually I want to handle another kind of error, which is
not really an error, but also a situation where we want to display a message, which is the situation
in which we cannot find any movie for the search query.
So let's say the query is like this one here.
Then of course the API will not find anything.
So I had to remove all throttling.
And.
Well, what happens here?
Well, basically the length cannot be read of undefined.
And so the problem here is that the data that comes back from the API now is apparently undefined.
So let's take a look at that.
So just add data here and let's try that again.
And so, indeed, we no longer have the search property here.
So we no longer have data dot search.
And so what's happening then is that data search is being set to undefined and therefore we get this
other error here.
So as I was saying in the very beginning, we always need to handle all these different situations that
can go wrong.
And when we are working with data fetching, there's always a lot of things that can go wrong.
So working with data is a lot of work, but it's also essential in most, if not all, web applications.
But anyway, here we can now use this response to our advantage in order to throw another error in this
situation.
So we can say that data dot response and actually this now needs to be.
Uh, here after we already have the data.
So in this case, if data dot response is equal.
Faults.
And so for some reason the API here responds with a string of faults and not a boolean.
But well, this still works.
So in this case, let's also throw a new error and let's simply say.
Movie not found.
All right.
And beautiful.
Let's just reload.
And then here we get this log.
So that's this console.error coming from here.
And then indeed we get our error message also displayed on the UI.
So this one was maybe a little bit trickier.
So let's just quickly recap.
So what we did was to implement another state variable this time specific for the error so that whenever
some error occurred, we could store the error message in there and then display it in the UI as soon
as an error occurred.
Now, as soon as an error did occur, which is in this situation and in this one we threw a new error
and then we caught that error inside the catch block of this try catch.
And so this is a standard way of catching errors in JavaScript.
And so in this situation, we then set the error state to the message of the error that we specified
here.
Then finally, we used, of course, that state variable in order to render something on the screen
conditionally.
And so that was right here.
So this part here is maybe a bit confusing.
And so make sure that after this video you just analyze exactly what's happening here and that, in
fact, these three conditions here are mutually exclusive.
So only one of them will ever be true.
Okay.
And I think that for now, this is enough for error handling in this application.
So that's always a very, very important part that many people overlook.
But it is, of course, essential to deal with this kind of situations.