So I've mentioned the use effect dependency array a few times already, but we don't know yet what it
actually does and how it works.
So let's change that in this lecture.
So as we saw at the beginning of this section, by default, an effect will run after each and every
render.
However, that's almost never what we want.
But the good news is that we can change this default behavior by passing a dependency array into the
use effect took as a second argument.
But why does use effect actually need an array of dependencies?
You might ask?
Well, the reason is that without this array, React doesn't know when to actually run the effect.
But if we do specify the effect dependencies by passing in the dependency array, the effect will be
executed each time that one of the dependencies changes.
And we will come back to why this is so amazing in the next slide.
But for now, this is all you need to know.
Now, what exactly are those dependencies?
Well, effect dependencies are state variables and props that are used inside the effect.
And the rule is that each and every one of those state variables and props must be included in the dependency
array.
But let's take a look at an example to understand what I'm talking about.
And the code here is really not important.
What matters is that the effect uses the title prop and the user rating state.
We can clearly see at the top of the code that title is indeed a prop and that user rating is indeed
a piece of state.
Therefore, both of them must be included in the dependency array.
So the effect function depends on these variables to do its work and therefore we need to tell react
about them.
Otherwise, if the title or the user rating changes react will not know about this change and therefore
it won't be able to re-execute the effect code.
And this will then lead to a bug called stale closure.
And we will talk about what a stale closure is and also about some more rules for the dependency array
in a later, more advanced section.
But for now, let's actually understand why the dependency array is so important for the use effect
hook.
So I like to think of the use effect hook as an event listener that is listening for one or more dependencies
to change.
And when one of the dependencies does change, use effect will simply execute the effect again.
So a bit like a regular event listener, but for effects.
But let's go back to our previous example where we had the title and user rating dependencies in the
array.
So whenever the title or the user rating changes react will execute the effect again.
So it will run the code one more time, which will in turn update the document title.
So the website title that we see in a browser tab so essentially effects react to updates to state and
props that are used inside the effect because again, those are the effects dependencies.
So in a way effects are reactive, just like React reacts to state updates by Rerendering the UI and
this is extremely useful and powerful as we will see throughout the rest of the course.
But all this only works if we correctly specify the dependency array.
Okay.
But now let's remember how I said in the very first lecture about effects that effects are used to keep
a component synchronized with some external system.
So some system that lives outside of our react based code.
And if we think about it, that's exactly what is happening here.
So the state and props of our component are now in fact synchronized with an external system, which
is in this case the title of the document.
Now updating the title in some other way will of course not magically update the title or user rating.
So the synchronization only works in one way, but that's not really the point.
The same actually happens with state updates and we still say that the UI is in sync with state.
So the point is that use effect truly is a synchronization mechanism.
So a mechanism to synchronize effects with the state of the application and you will discover this each
time that you're going to use an effect.
And so let's go explore this a little bit further.
So as we just learned, whenever a dependency changes, the effect is executed again.
But now let's remember that dependencies are always state or props.
And what happens to a component each time that its state or props are updated?
Well, that's right.
The component will rerender.
This means that effects and the lifecycle of a component instance are deeply interconnected.
That's why when the use effect hook was first introduced, many people thought that it was a lifecycle
hook rather than a hook for synchronizing the component with a side effect.
Now, the conclusion and the big takeaway from this is that we can use the dependency array in order
to run effects whenever the component renders or rerenders.
So in a way, the use effect hook is actually about synchronization and about the component lifecycle.
Okay.
And so with this knowledge, let's look at the three different types of dependency arrays that we can
specify and also how they affect both synchronization and life cycle.
So when we have multiple dependencies, like in this first example, variables X, Y, and Z, it means
that the effect synchronizes with X, Y, and Z.
Now, in terms of the life cycle, it means that the effect will run on the initial render and also
on each rerender triggered by updating one of the dependencies X, Y, or Z.
So again, just to make this crystal clear, the effect will be executed each time the component instance
is being re rendered by an update to x, y, or Z.
But if some other piece of state or prop is updated, then this particular effect will not be executed.
Now, if we have an empty dependency array, that means that the effect synchronizes with no state or
props and therefore it will only run on mount.
In other words, if an effect has no dependencies, it doesn't use any values that are relevant for
rendering the component.
And so therefore it's safe to be executed only once.
Finally, if we have no array at all, we already know that the effect will run on every render, which
is usually a really bad idea and not what we want.
Now, if the effect runs on every render, that basically means that the effect synchronizes with everything.
So essentially every state and every prop in a component will be dependencies in this case.
And now to finish, let's look at when exactly effects are executed during the render and commit process.
Now, I mentioned in the first lecture on effects that effects are executed after render.
And while that's not wrong, it's also not the full story.
So let's look at a timeline of events that happen as components render and rerender.
And I found this extremely useful when I first learned about the use effect hook myself.
And so I think that you will benefit from this as well.
So as we already know, the whole process starts with mounting the component instance, in this case,
an instance of movie details.
After that, the result of rendering is committed to the Dom.
And finally the Dom changes are painted onto the screen by the browser.
So this is just what we learned in the previous section.
But where do effects come into play here?
Well effects are actually only executed after the browser has painted the component instance on the
screen.
So not immediately after render as you might have thought initially.
That's why we say that effects run asynchronously after the render has already been painted to the screen.
And the reasons why effect work this way is that effects may contain long running processes such as
fetching data.
So in a situation like that, if React would execute the effect before the browser paints a new screen,
it would block this entire process and users would see an old version of the component for way too long.
And of course that would be very undesirable.
Now, one important consequence of the fact that effects do not run during render is that if an effect
sets state, then a second additional render will be required to display the UI correctly.
And so this is one of the reasons why you shouldn't overuse effects.
Okay.
But moving on now, let's say that the title was initially set to Interstellar, but then it changes
to interstellar wars.
And since this title is a prop, it means that the component will rerender and the Dom changes will
be committed and painted to the screen again.
Now, since title is part of the dependency array of this effect, the effect will be executed again
at this point.
So just as we learned in the last slide and this whole process can of course be repeated over and over
again until this movie details instance finally unmounts and disappears from the screen.
Now you might notice that there is actually a hole between the commit and browser paint, right?
And the reason is that in React, there's actually another type of effect called a layout effect.
So the only difference between a regular effect and a layout effect is that the layout effect runs before
the browser actually paints the new screen.
But we almost never need this.
And so the React team actually discourages the use of this use layout effect hook.
I simply mention this here so that you know that this also exists.
And actually there are even two more holes in this timeline.
But we will talk about these mystery steps by the end of the section.
So stay tuned for that.