Welcome to the last and optional section of the intermediate React part of the course.
This one is all about class based react.
So once upon a time we used to write React components in quite a different way.
Instead of using functions and hooks, we used classes and so called lifecycle methods.
Now you will most likely never have to write a class component in your work or personal projects, but
you will encounter them in older code bases and you might even need to convert class components to function
components at some point.
That's why I've decided to include a section on this legacy way of writing React code.
Now, if you're concerned that this different syntax will confuse you, please just skip this section
for now and come back to it later.
Or only if you ever need to learn about these class components at your job.
But if you're curious about this historical part of React, then let's move right on.