Let's finish this section with the three most important life cycle methods which are component did mount.
Component did update and component will unmount.
And we are going to use these lifecycle methods to implement two more features into our application.
So first of all, we want to search for weather as we type.
So, for example, as I keep typing, it will then search basically for different locations until I
arrive at something that I want.
So notice that we don't have the search weather button here anymore, but instead, each time that I
type, a new search will be fired off.
So that's one of the features.
And the other one is as I reload the page now, then you see that we get the exact same location that
we had before.
And so that's because we store this location here in local storage each time that we type a new location
in here.
So let's now use lifecycle methods to implement these two features.
So lifecycle methods are essentially special methods that all react components get access to and which
we can use to run side effects at different points of the component lifecycle.
And the most important points of the lifecycle are mounting rerendering and unmounting of the component.
So we already talked about these before when we first talked about the Useeffect Hook, right?
Now, the lifecycle methods are not exactly the same thing as the use effect hook in function components,
but they are the closest similar thing that we have in class components.
And so let's now start with the component did mount method.
So let's just specify that one here.
So component.
Did mount.
And so this is really just another method.
And as the name of the method says, this one is called immediately after rendering.
So basically after the Dom has been created, just like a useeffect took with the empty dependency array.
And so this is the ideal place to perform some initial side effects as the component loads.
So what we can do here as the component renders and first mounts, is to call our fetch weather method.
Okay.
And so what this will do is that as soon as the app is loaded, it will immediately start fetching for
the weather.
And indeed, that's exactly what happened here.
Now, this only works because we have Lisbon here as a predefined location string.
But this is just to demonstrate how this life cycle method here works.
So again, this is not exactly the same as the use effect hook, but the closest thing that we can imagine
this being is a use effect with the empty dependency array.
So only running on mount, but not on Rerenders.
Okay.
But speaking of Rerenders, of course we also have a lifecycle method for that event.
And so that one is called component did.
Update.
All right.
Now, what's special about this method is that React actually gives it access to the previous state
and the previous props.
So the first argument is the previous props.
And it's the second one is the previous state.
And so this is then a bit similar to the use effect hook with some variable here in the dependency array.
For example, we can now use these previous state here to check if the location has changed.
And so that's then similar to having a use effect with location in the dependency array.
The difference is that this method right here is not called on mount.
So really only on rerender.
While this use effect would of course also be called on mount.
So on the initial render.
So as I was saying, we can now compare the current state with the previous state.
So this dot state dot location.
If it's different.
So if it has changed across renders.
Then we can do something.
And of course, we can also not do this comparison and not even do anything with this previous state
or the previous props.
But in this case we actually need them because now what we want to do is to again fetch the weather
in case that the new location is different from the previous one.
And so this will then basically enable us to search for the weather as we type.
So you see it's already working.
So it's doing exactly the same thing as before in our demo app.
Now, one downside that you can immediately see is that our fetching logic here is now spread across
these two lifecycle methods.
So we're fetching the weather on mount and also on rerender.
And so then we need to call this function here in two places.
Now that's not a big deal, of course, in this situation, but in real world applications, this used
to be really a big problem.
So we used to have logic that belongs together, spread out over these different methods.
So that then makes the code a lot harder to understand.
And so use effect actually solved some of these problems again, because this one here.
So this effect like this would run both on mount and on rerender.
But anyway, we can now remove this button here as we now no longer need it.
All right.
What we can also remove to make this a bit more real is, of course, this initial location.
But this will now give us a problem because right now on the component mount, this will still attempt
to fetch the weather, even though right now we have no location.
And so actually, in this particular case, it doesn't make any sense to even fetch the weather as the
component mounts.
So I will now remove this from here.
But it was still important to understand initially how this lifecycle method here works and we will
actually need it again here in a minute.
But now let's just reload here.
And so then we don't get that error anymore.
But we still get now this error.
And first, that's because this one here doesn't exist.
But let's try that again.
And so here now, the problem is that there was no location found.
So this only starts searching for something if we have at least two characters in our string.
So let's quickly fix that by coming here into this function.
And we can just say if this dot, state, dot, location, dot length is less than two, then just return.
So then just don't do anything.
So now, Yeah, now that's fixed.
And again, as we keep typing, it will then show us the weather for those different locations.
Okay, great.
And now what we want to do is that feature where it will remember our location in local storage.
So how are we going to do that?
Well, basically, each time that we type a new character here, we want to store the location into
local storage.
And so then once again, the component did update lifecycle method is the perfect place for doing that.
So besides fetching the weather, we also want local storage dot set item.
Let's call this one location.
And then what we want to store there is this dot state dot location.
And since this is already a string, we don't even need to convert it to a string.
And so now as we keep typing, let's check out our.
Application tap here.
With a bit more space.
And then indeed, here we have Pharaoh in the local storage right now.
And so all we have to do now.
Because right now, of course, we don't get that value yet.
And so what we have to do now is to read that value from local storage as the component mounts.
And so the perfect place for that is again or component did mount lifecycle method.
So here we will want to set our state based on that data that's coming from local storage.
So this dot set state.
And then remember, it always needs to be an object here.
So with the location property.
And then simply local storage dot get item.
From the key of location.
Now, when we run this app for the first time, there won't be no local storage yet, at least not with
this key.
And so let's then set a default of an empty string.
Okay.
And there it is.
So let's reload here and then that's working great.
So let's just analyze what happens here.
So as the component is mounted, it will then read this value here from local storage.
Right here.
So in this lifecycle method.
So this then sets the state which will in turn rerender the component.
And so then after that rerender, the component did update method will get called.
And so that's where we then fetch the weather because of course the new location will be different than
the previous one.
But if we copy this, for example, and then just paste the same thing here, then the new state is
the same as the current one.
And so then nothing happened here.
Great.
So this is how we work with lifecycle methods in a very simple way.
So just again, some simple examples, but that's all we need right here.
And now to finish, let's just take one more minute to talk about another lifecycle method, which is
the component will unmount method.
So this one is a bit less important, but let's just mention it here as well.
Now this component.
So the app component will actually never unmount.
So it doesn't make sense to use it here.
So let's do it here in the weather because of course, this component will sometimes not exist.
So when there is no string here, then there is also no weather component.
So we can just then use component will unmount.
And so doing this is very similar to returning a cleanup function from a effect function.
The difference is that this one really only runs after the component unmounts.
So after it disappears and is destroyed, not between renders.
So again, this lifecycle method is mostly used to clean up after some effects, which in this case
we don't really have.
And so there's not really any meaningful thing that we can do here.
So let's just log something to the console just to show you.
So weather will.
Unmount or is unmounting?
It doesn't really matter.
No.
Right.
So again, between renders, this is not running, so it's not doing anything.
But then.
Well, nothing happens, actually.
So our weather didn't even disappear.
But that's just because we probably have some problem here.
So let's come back here to the function where we fetch this data.
And so here what we want to do instead is to not only return, but also just set the state to empty
weather again, basically doing return this dot set state.
And then the weather should basically be reset to an empty object.
So let's try that again.
Okay.
And then now we saw that the component disappeared.
And so then the component will unmount method was called and therefore we got this log here in our console.
And so this again would be ideal to clean up after some side effects that we created.
So not really the case here, but now you know that this method exists and that it's one of the three
most important ones, I would say.
Now if we write again here component, you see that there are many other lifecycle methods, but these
are not that important.
And so therefore we will not talk about that here in this basically crash course of class components.
So remember that the goal of this section was not for you to really learn how to write these class based
components on your own, but more to understand how they work and what they look like.
In case you ever come across some of them in your work in case that company still maintains some old
codebase.
So that's perfectly possible thing to happen.
And so I thought it was a good idea to include this section here so that you can be prepared for that
possible future.
And now if you feel like it, you could actually convert this entire application back to function components.
So I think that would be a really, really great exercise for you to practice everything that we have
learned up until this point, including understanding even better how these class components work.
So in case you do that, I would really like to see your implementation.
So make sure that you paste something like a link to a GitHub repo in the course Q&amp;A after this lecture.
And so yeah, really looking forward to seeing that.
And then once you're done with that or even if you don't want to do it, I hope to see you soon in the
next section, which will be the beginning of part three of this course.
So this is where we will finally enter the advanced React part of this course.