So let's now create our very first class component.
And to do so, we are finally going to create a brand new app.
So open up your terminal or command prompt.
And then npx create.
React app.
Version five.
And then the name of this app is going to be classy.
Weather like this.
So we are going to create a weather app basically.
And since it's based on React classes, it is called class weather.
And in the time while this is installing, let me just quickly show you the app.
So here it is.
And so we can very simply search for a location here.
Let's say London, and it will then load the weather for today and for the next six days.
So basically for the current week and that's it.
So it's a very simple application, but it's fetching this weather data here from an API, of course.
And here we can also, of course, search for any location that we want.
So let's say I'm in Lisbon and so, well, it is going to rain tomorrow apparently, and therefore also
where I live, I assume.
But anyway, let's now wait for this to install our application and then once that's finished, let's
meet back here.
Okay.
Looks like that finished.
And so, as always, let's grab our starter files from the class.
Whether.
So these two.
And then where is my folder?
Oh, apparently I installed it in the wrong folder.
So let's come here to the root folder.
And there it is.
So let's put that right here.
And try again.
So I'll just rename it again.
And then inside our source, let's paste these two files.
And also, as always, let's get rid of all the junk files here.
So, yeah, I think those are the ones.
So all we need are the Index.js, the app or new CSS and the starter dot JS, which is coming from our
starter files.
All right.
And with this, we are ready to open up our project folder in vs code once again.
Okay.
And so let's just open up our app.js and index.js to clean up that file.
And that should be it.
And also clean up this file.
So let's delete everything here and get started with our very first class component.
So basically back in the day before 2019 in React, we would write components not using functions but
using JavaScript classes.
So the class keyword, then the name of the component, and then this class would actually be a child
class of react.component.
So extends and then react Dot.
Component.
And so therefore we would have to also import react in every component file.
So import react from.
React.
No K.
And then we should also export this component.
Let's do that down here.
Export default d counter.
No.
Okay.
And so this is how we would set up a brand new component using classes.
So again, using ES6 classes, so modern JavaScript classes which extend the parent class of React component.
And so this parent class gives us a couple of methods and one of them is the render method.
So every single react component that is written with classes needs to include the render method.
So this render method is basically equivalent to the function body of a function component.
So every single class component needs to have a render method which returns some JS.
So let's just do that here.
And of course works in the exact same way as in function components.
Now what we're going to do here is a very simple date counter.
Again, so similar to what we did, I think, in one of the challenges before.
So let's just.
Write a minus and a plus button.
And in the middle, we just are going to have some span with the current number.
So let's start at zero.
All right.
And so this is actually enough as a bare bones component.
And so let's try it out now.
By coming to our terminal.
And then as always, npm start.
So let's wait for it.
And there it is.
Well, that doesn't look really nice.
Let's make this, like, really big so we can actually see something.
Also, as always, let's bring up our developer tools.
And.
Okay.
So next up, let's actually add some state to our component, which works in a very different way than
in function components, because here we cannot use the use state took.
So hooks are only for class components, but not of course, for class components.
That's the huge difference between the two actually.
And so in a class component, if we want to add state to a component, we first need to call the constructor
method.
So this one is part of all ES6 classes.
And then this one receives props and it calls the parent constructor as well by using the super method
or the super function.
And it does so by passing in the props again.
So this is a lot of boilerplate that we have to write when we want to use class components.
And so this is why basically all react.
Developers now prefer functional components.
So again, this is a lot of work and super annoying to having to write all this boilerplate that really
doesn't do anything.
I mean, at least not anything super useful.
Okay.
And so now to initialize state, we do that also right here in the constructor method.
So that's because this method here is called each time a new object is instantiated from this class.
And so that's just how ES6 classes work, which I hope you're familiar with.
But if not, that's also not a big deal at all.
But anyway, here we are now defining basically a state property on the current object.
So the current component will get the state that we define here.
So that has to be an object.
And then for each state variable that we want, we need to create one property in this object.
So we want to count to start at one.
And so this is yet another huge difference between functional and class components.
So in class components, again, we only have one huge state object and not multiple state variables
like we do with the use state hook.
But anyway, let's use actually a different value here so that now we can access that here in our render
method.
So instead of the zero, let's actually access now this state and the way we have to do this is again
a little bit annoying.
So we have to write this dot state.
Dot count.
So the this keyword here will, in this case, simply point to the current component instance.
And so then from there we read the state and from there the count.
And so in class components, you will see this kind of thing all the time.
It's always going to be this dot state dot something or this dot props dot something.
But anyway, let's now save this.
And we see that indeed our value here got updated to five.
So it's reading our value from the state now.
And so next, what we need to do is to then of course, attach some event handlers to these buttons
here to then actually update the state.
So let's do that in the next lecture.