Let's now learn how we can work with event handlers and how we update state in class components.
So just like before, basically here, we now want to use the onClick property in order to add an event
handler to this button.
But now where do we actually write that event handler?
Well, remember how I said that this render method here is basically equivalent to the function body
of a functional component or a function component.
So I use these two terms interchangeably.
So they're basically the same.
But anyway, since this is equivalent to basically the function body of the functional component, we
might think that this is where we now define our event handlers.
So just like we do in functional components, right?
However, that's not what we do in class components.
So in class components, this render method should be as clean as possible, so it should contain as
little render logic as possible.
And so instead our handler functions are defined as class methods.
So let's define handle decrement.
Decrement like this.
And so with this, we have a brand new class method.
And so here now we update the state.
But before we do that, let me actually show you something that we need to do first.
So let me log the this keyword because the this keyword is necessary all the time.
So we will actually also need it here.
Okay, but now let's then connect this onClick prop with this handler function.
And the way we do that is, again, using the this keyword and then handle decrement.
And so again, the this keyword basically points to the current component instance, which will inherit
this method here from the class definition.
Now.
Right?
Let's give it a save.
And then let's click this button.
And so you see that we get undefined, or in other words, that the this keyword inside this handler
here is undefined.
However, we need the this keyword to point to the current component because that's how we will update
the state.
So we will update the state by doing this dot set state.
And then here something.
So we are going to need the this keyword, but again, it is currently undefined and the reason for
that is simply the way in which JavaScript works.
So when React calls our event handler here, it first actually behind the scenes creates a copy of this
function.
And so then the function call is just a normal function call, which is not bound to any object.
And so because of that, this function then loses the binding to the current this keyword.
But that's all not really important.
The only thing that matters to know is that all event handlers that are called here inside the JS will
lose their binding to the this keyword.
And so we need to fix that by coming here again to our constructor method.
And then we basically need to override the method.
So writing this dot handle decrement is equal.
To this dot decrement.
And then we use the bind method to manually bind the this keyword to this function here.
And so by doing this, we basically give this method here access to the current component instance again.
All right.
And so if you ever come across some older react code base, you will see this kind of thing everywhere.
So this manually binding the this keyword to our event handler functions.
And so now if we click this button, you see that we actually get access to this object so we can see
even the state, the props that it received and some other stuff.
But that's not really why we're here.
So we are here to update the state.
And so, as I mentioned earlier, we do this by calling the set state method on the this keyword.
And the way this set state method works is very similar to the state setter functions that we get back
from a use state hook call.
So basically we can update state in two different ways.
We can just pass in the new state here or we can update the state based on the current state.
So let's actually do the second one.
So by providing a callback function here, which gets access to the entire current state object.
So let's call it current state.
And then let's actually explicitly return the new state object here, just so we know that this is what
we need to do.
So we need to return a new object where the count property is then updated.
So we can get the current count from state dot count and then we just add one.
Okay.
And that's it.
And well, that's actually the opposite direction.
So we want to subtract one.
But in any case, that's working great.
So we just made our first class component dynamic and are already updating some state.
So we're doing great progress.
Now, let me just tell you the other way.
So let's.
Remove this.
And so here we could also have passed in simply a value.
So setting the count, for example, to ten whenever we click here.
So you see that works as well.
But of course, here we want to set state based on the current state.
All right.
And by the way, notice how all the concepts behind react that we have been talking about before still
apply to class components.
So things like updating the state will rerender the UI and all things like that.
So those fundamentals haven't changed.
The only thing that's changing is that we write the component in a completely different way.
But anyway, let's now just duplicate this code here to create or handle increment.
Uh, event handler.
And then here, all we need to do is to just change this to plus one and then here.
Also attach an event handler function.
So the one that we just created.
So handle increment.
And just like before, of course we do not call the function, but we simply let react, call it as
soon as we click on the button.
And so we got some error.
Well, why is that?
Ah, of course.
So I just told you before that the this keyword will lose its meaning basically.
So inside handle increment, it will no longer point to the current component instance.
And so that's why we fixed that this binding right here.
But we forgot to do the same thing for handle increment.
So let's fix that.
Give it a save.
And so now it should work.
Yes.
So never forget to do this because you see that the consequence is that your app will not work.
Okay.
And so now let's instead of just displaying the number here, display the date.
So just like we did before in that date calculator.
And so this kind of very simple render logic is actually allowed here in the render method.
So we just shouldn't define functions here like we do in our render logic in functional components.
But some simple logic like this is allowed.
So we define our date.
Let's just pass in a string here so that JavaScript can parse the date object out of it.
So let's say we are in 2027 and then we want to set the date on that.
To date dot get date.
And this is similar again to what we already did before.
So we're just transforming that to a class based component.
Right.
So here you basically want to add the current state to this state.
So that's this dot state dot count, which again is a lot of work where in functional components we
would simply call that count, right?
And so let's.
Just place that here.
So date and then to date string.
And let's place this here into some brackets.
And that looks a bit too big now.
Okay.
And you see that it is working.
Indeed.
Okay.
And so with this, we finish this short introduction to class components and are now ready to build
the classy weather application.
But before we go do that, let's just quickly learn all the differences between class components and
function components in the next video.