Now, before we really dive into class components, it's a good idea to get familiar with all the main
differences between function components and class components.
So as we already know, function components are the current way of creating components in React as they
were introduced into React in 2019 with React version 16.8.
Class components, on the other hand, have been around for a long time, so since version 0.13 back
in 2015.
Now, technically, React has always had function components, but without hooks.
So before 16.8 function components were very limited and not really useful because they couldn't even
have their own state.
Now, in order to create a function component, we just use any type of JavaScript function, no matter
if a function declaration or an arrow function with class components.
As the name says, we have to create an ES6 class that extends the provided React.component parent class.
So just like we did in the previous two lectures.
So when we're using class components, we're actually using object oriented programming principles like
having to use the disk keyword to read incoming props and to define local component state, which can
become a bit annoying over time with function components.
On the other hand, these things are much easier.
So to read props, all we have to do is to use the received props object and to define local state.
We can use the use state hook.
But probably the biggest difference between these two types of components is how they handle side effects
and the component lifecycle.
So in class components, we actually have special methods that were defined by React in order to run
code at different points of the lifecycle.
And so these are called lifecycle methods and we will look at the most important ones throughout this
section.
Now with function components, we now care a lot more about synchronization rather than the component
lifecycle.
And we do so by using the use effect hook.
I mean, we know that this synchronization with use effect still kind of translates into the component
lifecycle, but the focus is more on synchronizing the component with a side effect.
And actually, I think it's safe to say that hooks in general are the big and the main difference between
function and class components.
Hooks just introduced a completely new way of thinking and of writing React applications.
So the way that hooks were introduced, React development really changed forever.
And if you ask me, it actually changed for a lot better.
But anyway, some smaller differences are in event handlers and in the way in which we return the JSX
from our components.
So in function components, we simply handle events with functions that we define inside the component
function body.
While in class components, we have to create a new class method for every single event handler.
Now, as for the JS in function components, we return our JS from the function while in class components.
We need to return JS from a special render method, which is yet another React specific thing that you
need to remember when you work with class components.
So in general function components with hooks have a lot of advantages over class components.
They are easier to build because they require a lot less react specific boilerplate code and they produce
much cleaner code.
And the main reason for this cleaner code is that the user hook combines all code related to the lifecycle
in one single place, while in class components.
That code is usually spread across multiple lifecycle methods, which can become quite confusing in
large components.
Now, one of the big reasons why Hooks were introduced in the first place is that they make it much
easier to share stateful logic simply by creating custom hooks.
And finally, in function components, we can get rid of the annoying and error prone dis keyword,
which was especially hard to grasp for many beginners.
The only advantage I would say that class components have is the fact that some people find it easier
to understand the component lifecycle because of lifecycle methods with explicit names such as component
did mount or component will unmount.
Okay.
And with this pretty detailed comparison, I think we're now ready to dive deep into how class components
work in practice.