Okay, so let's start working on the classy weather application.
And let's start by duplicating this file here.
And then let's call.
This one here, the counter, so that we can keep the code that we wrote previously.
And so now let's delete everything from here and start from scratch.
So we start by importing react.
From React.
And then again we use a JavaScript class.
We call it app and it need to extend react.
Dot component so that we can inherit all the things that we need from React.
Here inside this class, for example, the render method to return some JS.
So let's actually start writing that JS for our classy weather application.
So starting with a div of the app class name.
And as always, you can check out the CSS file that is part of this section.
And let's start with an H one with the name of the app.
So classy weather.
Then let's create a div with an input field.
And so this field will basically be for the location for which we want to search the weather.
So this will be of the type of text.
And let's also add a placeholder.
Search for.
Location.
No.
Okay.
And now all we need to do is to export that component.
And there we go.
We just need to make this a lot smaller so that it actually fits our screen.
And so now here we can search for any city.
So just like here in this demo application.
Now here in this app, we for now also want a button.
Sew a button to search for the weather.
So get weather like this.
Okay.
And next up, let's make this input field here a controlled element.
So an element where React controls and owns the state.
And so this idea of controlled elements is exactly the same as before in function components.
So many of the things that we learned previously still apply to class components.
And so this means that we now need to give this component state and remember that we do that by calling
the constructor method, which is a method that is available on all JavaScript classes.
So this is not coming from React, but this one is called with props so that we can then call the parent
component.
So that is react component by using here the super keyword.
And again, we do that with perhaps.
Okay, so this is really like a recipe that you need to follow and it's always the same.
And so that's why we say that these class components have a lot more boilerplate code.
So it's all of this stuff that doesn't really do much, but which we still have to do in order to make
this work.
But anyway, let's now define state again by using this dot state and then setting it to an object.
And this one will have the location property.
And let's start with a default location.
So, for example, Lisbon.
And so now, just like always, we use this state as a value, but now that state lives in this dot
state.
Dot location.
So as we save this, we see that immediately our state got added to our input field.
Nice.
Now all we have to do is to then listen for the change event and update the state as the user types.
And so again, we get the current event and then here we set the state.
So in class components, we do this by using this dot set state and then we pass in the new object.
Or at least the properties that have changed.
So location will be equal to e dot target dot value.
And so if we reload this now.
And that's working just fine.
And we can see that also here in the dev tools.
So you see that just like before, we can see the entire state down here.
The only difference is that now it doesn't say hooks and it doesn't have here the numbers for the hooks,
of course, as well.
But besides that, yeah, everything works the same.
Now notice that here in this event handler function, we didn't have to manually bind the disk keyword
like we did before.
We only have to do that when we define the event handler as an outside method, which is exactly what
we will do next.
So basically, as an event handler for the event of clicking here on this button.
So let's do that.
And let's call it fetch.
Whether.
And for now, we will only just log something here to the console like loading data.
And then let's also again log the disk keyword here.
So just so we see again the problem that we have.
So let's attach that here.
And so again, that is this dot and then whatever name of the method.
So let's see.
And well, here we have the wrong prop name.
Let's just reload that.
And now as we click here, we get loading data and we also get again that our this keyword is undefined.
And that's going to be a problem because we will need the this keyword here to later set some state.
And so just like we did in our counter, we need to now explicitly bind the this keyword to this method.
So we say this dot weather is equal to this dot fetch weather and then we explicitly bind the this keyword
to this method.
So basically giving it access to the current component instance so that then we can set the state on
there.
So give it a save.
Try that again.
And now indeed we get our current component instance here.
So it has our state and everything.
And if we change that here, then of course it won't change here.
But if we do that again.
Then.
Yeah.
Now we have the new updated state right there.
Okay.
And with this, we are now ready to actually fetch the weather data in the next video.