So now it's time to fetch the weather data according to the user's input location.
And to do that, I actually already prepared much of the code.
So that's right here in starter Dot JS.
So let's copy all of this.
And close that and then just paste it in here.
So before our actual component.
So here we have basically a function that will get these weather icons here.
So the icons that we have right here.
So they will come from this function here.
Then we also have this function that converts a country code to an emoji just to make this look a little
bit nicer.
And then we have this function here for formatting a day so that one will be responsible to showing
the weekday here like this.
But what we're interested in now is this get weather location and in fact, all that we need is to grab
this code here.
So just this try catch.
And cut it from here.
And then this function itself, we actually don't need it.
So just grab that code there, then get rid of this temporary code and paste that here.
Now, immediately we see that we have a problem because we are using the await keyword.
And so this needs to be an async function.
But that's a.
But that's luckily for us, very easy.
So we can simply make these methods here.
Async methods like this.
No.
Right.
So that's looking better.
But we still have a problem here, which is that we are using this location here.
So trying to reference a variable that doesn't exist.
So instead here what we want is this dot state dot location.
Okay.
Now it looks like we have no more errors.
And so let's just quickly go through what this code here does.
So we have this API here at Open Metrocom so we can check that out and check out the documentation if
you want.
But it's basically just a free weather API.
So if you want you can check out the documentation here, but that's not necessary here right now to
use this API, we first need to basically geocode our location here into a latitude longitude, a country
and so on.
So first we do a fetch request to this endpoint right here with our location string, which will then
return basically all the information about that location.
So then here we are for now simply logging that to the console.
So the name of the location that came back and then converting the country to an emoji flag.
So just as I showed you before, and then once we have that information, we plug that here into this
URL endpoint.
So the latitude, longitude and timezone are things that this endpoint here needs.
And so that's why first we need to convert our location to basically this information.
And so then we get the data here.
And again for now, just log it to the console and in case there is any error, then that simply gets
logged also to the console.
So let's just reload.
Let's click here.
And so you see that it's actually working.
So let's see what we have here.
So first we have the geo data.
And so then in the results, we have basically different possible results where we then take the first
one.
So here we take data dot results and the first one, and from there we get all this information that
we need.
Okay.
Then we display the name that came back together with the emoji.
And finally, we have the weather data.
So that's weather data dot daily.
And so here we have all the information that we will need to then later display the weather.
Okay.
Now, one thing that I want to start by doing here is to create an is loading state.
So just like we have been doing before, we want to indicate the user that we are currently loading.
And so let's add a new piece of state.
And as I said previously here, we now do not create multiple state variables, but instead we add them
all to the same object.
And so here, let's say.
Is loading and we start at faults.
And then here in the beginning of this try block we simply do this dot set state.
And so now here comes a very important part.
So in this object that we pass to set state, we only need to specify the actual properties that we
want to change.
So here we just need to write isloading set to false and that will then not overwrite the location.
So it will really only update this isloading property.
And this is important to mention because with the use state hook, if we updated the state that is an
object.
We could not do this.
We would first have to destructure the current state.
So like this dot state for example, and then we would mutate this one property.
So basically we would have to return the entire object.
But here again, that's not necessary.
So just mutating this one property.
And of course, it needs to be true.
And then let's copy it and at the end set it to false.
So let's add a finally block here, which will run no matter if the code here threw an error or not.
And then down here in our render output.
Let's do some conditional rendering.
So this dot state dot is loading and maybe you start seeing that it is quite annoying to always type
that this dot state.
But anyway, that's why we no longer use these components in practice.
No.
Okay.
But so here we just render a paragraph with this predefined class name.
And so let's try that again.
And beautiful.
Now we just forgot to actually change it back to false and not leave it at true.
Yeah, that looks a lot better.
Okay.
And now next up, we also want to get this city here and, of course, the weather onto the user interface,
which means that we need two new pieces of state.
And by the way, we need to get also this new location into the UI, even though we already have it
here, because sometimes it's actually different.
So, for example, if I search for London.
So if I just type Lun, then our API will automatically assume that it is London.
So here we then want to display that the weather is indeed coming from London, not just from London.
Okay.
So let's, uh.
Come.
Where is that?
Uh, yeah, right here.
So let's call this one the display.
Location and it starts as an empty string and then also the weather.
And let's initialize this one as an empty object because it will later also become an object.
All right.
And so then here, instead of logging this stuff to the console.
Well, this one we actually only want to log we don't want this one in state, but we want this display
name.
And so let's now do this dot set state.
And then of course, this needs to be an object.
And then display location and the same thing for the weather.
So here.
This.setstate.
An object.
And then whether.
Just like this.
No.
Okay.
So let's reload here.
Let's come to our components.
So we have all the initial state right there.
Then let's get the weather and nice so we get our actual weather or display location and really all
the data that we need to nicely display and render our data here in the UI.
And so that's going to be the topic of our next lecture.