Next up, let's actually render the received weather data.
And for that, let's create a brand new component.
And I will actually do that again here in the same file.
So let's call this one here.
Whether.
And so it again extends.
React dot component.
And as usually we start out with the render method, which again is called each time that the component
is rendered.
And then from here, let's just return a div and then for now, let's just.
Right.
An H2.
Whether.
All right.
And so now, of course, we need to include this component here in our X, So let's do that and let's
do so conditionally.
So only when there actually is some weather data, then we want to display the weather component.
So let's say this dot state dot weather.
But this is not enough actually, because by default, this is also an object, Right?
And so we actually need to read some property from this.
So to see if it exists.
So let's for now comment this out and run our code again.
So that.
And we are not logging it to the console anymore, but we can still take a look at it here in our dev
tools.
So let's then say here if this dot state dot weather dot.
Whether code exists.
So this array here, this can only exist if the whether does exist.
And so if that's the case, then let's render the whether component.
And as a prop, let's actually pass in the weather that we want to render.
And then also the location.
And here, of course, it's not whether this is how we would do it in normal functional components,
but here we need to do this dot state dot.
So of course I'm actually no longer used to writing code like this, so this is a bit of a change for
me as well.
So we're passing in weather and location, and so then we can receive these here as props.
But more about that later.
For now, let's see if our component actually gets rendered as soon as the data arrives.
And yeah, so in our component tree now we also have the weather.
Okay.
And so now let's take those props.
And in class components, there's actually no easy way of destructuring all the received props.
So we can only do that in each method separately.
But first of all, let's actually see how we receive props in a component like this.
And so let's log to the console, this dot props.
And so if we click here now, then we should get.
Yeah, here it is.
So here is the props object which contains the weather and the location.
And actually here we want the display location.
Just like this.
And now let's actually take all this data here out of the weather.
So let's destructure the props, which again, we have to do it manually inside of each method here.
So we cannot do that centrally like we do in function components.
Let's look.
Props, dot weather.
And so now let's take out all these things there.
So temperature underscore two.
M.
Max.
And let's also rename these.
So this is basically just the maximum temperature.
Okay, let's copy that.
We also have the min.
Which you will just call Min.
And here we are getting this error because of course, this is this dot props.
Not just props.
Let's take also the time and let's call this dates, and then let's also take the weather code.
And this one I will call codes.
So codes because it is multiple codes, not just one.
So these here are basically four arrays.
And so in order to render those, we need to, of course, loop over the arrays and then for each of
them, render one of these components right there.
So that's going to be another component.
No.
Okay.
And before we do that, let's also quickly.
Now include the location here in this H2.
And then let's finally do what I just said, which is to loop over these arrays.
So let's create this list here with.
The prop name or with the class name, actually, of whether.
And then we will just loop over one of these arrays, as always.
So in this case, since all of these four are actually arrays and we will need to pass the data for
each of them into the new component, it doesn't really matter over which one we loop, so let's just
choose the dates.
And then here we will create a day component.
And for now, I will not pass anything in.
And so instead I will just create that component here first.
So class day.
Extends.
React dot component.
And then I'll render method.
And then in their return one list item which will now just says de.
And so let's check that.
Here.
Let's get rid of that highlighting.
And let's wait for it.
And there we go.
So we have one day component for each of the days.
And so now let's pass in all the data that we need.
So basically we need the current maximum temperature, the minimum the date and the weather code for
each particular day.
So let's start with the date, which is just the current date.
Then the max temperature.
And so now let's come to the max array and then take the element at the current position that we are
looping over this date's array.
So here we also need to receive the current index and so then use that index here.
Now the same thing with the minimum temperature.
So min at.
I as well.
And finally, also for the code.
So codes dot add I.
And finally react also needs the key, as always.
And so here we can actually use the date itself, which is going to be a unique string.
So if we reload that now, well, actually, there's no need to test this because we're not yet doing
anything with that data here.
But so let's now do that and let's again start by destructuring our props.
So date.
Max Min.
Code is equals to this dot props.
And now it's time to actually use that data to render the weather.
So let's create a paragraph here first with the date and then here the minimum and the maximum temperatures.
So let's use the HTML entity for degrees.
Then a dash.
So another entity and then the max temperature.
Okay, so that's not the final version, but it should already show us something.
Nice.
So that's already the current weather, even though that's not really easy to understand yet.
So it needs some formatting.
For example here, this one should actually get the day class.
And also we want the weather code now.
And for that we will create a span and you will see why that is in a minute.
So let's just try this again so we can see what changes we need to do next.
And so here we are.
So this is our temperature here, which we should probably round.
So like this, it's a bit confusing.
Then we want to format these dates and we want to transform these strange looking weather codes here
into something meaningful.
And so that's where we have all those functions for that we included in the beginning.
But first, let's round these values here.
So let's round this one down with math dot floor.
In this one we can round it up with math dot ceil.
But let's not save this yet.
And so let's continue now with the code and the date.
So for that we have the get weather icon function, which just takes in the code.
So a code like this.
It will then return the corresponding emoji and we have the format day function.
So let's now use both of them.
So.
Here we use format de and here we use.
Get weather.
Aiken.
All right, So let's try again.
And it always takes some time.
But this time it was actually fast.
So that's looking nice already.
Let's just make the second one here bold, which I think I have.
In the demo.
And then closing it, of course, right after here.
And then what also have in the original demo application is that for the first weather here, that is
basically today I want to display actually today here.
And so now we need to pass in another prop here into the day component which tells us whether this is
actually the current day or not.
So let's say is today.
And then if it is today, it simply means that the index is equal to zero.
So basically that it's the very first day component that will be rendered.
And so then here we can say is today.
And of course, then first we need to also destructure that.
So if it is today, then here the output should just be today and otherwise format the date.
And this should be it.
So let's see.
And there it is.
Let's do London now.
And there, of course, it rains a lot more.
And so we have the exact same weather as we have here.
And our app now looks exactly the same.
Great.
So we did a lot of things here in this lecture.
Let's just quickly recap, even though it wasn't really complicated stuff.
So we just created this weather component and included it here in case that there is some weather data.
So basically in case that this property here exists on the weather.
So we pass in weather and location and then here we destructure at least the weather right inside the
render method.
And if we had more methods that also needed access to these props, then we would have to destructure
them again in there.
Now, also notice that this component here and also the day component, they both don't have the constructor
method.
Right?
And so the reason for that is that when we don't need to initialize state and we don't need to explicitly
bind the this keyword to some event handler methods, then we actually don't even need to implement
the constructor in the component in question.
And so that's why these two actually don't have it.
But anyway, here then we do pretty standard stuff, so we just loop over the dates array so that we
can render one day component for each of the dates.
So then we pass in the relevant date max and min temperatures weather code and letting it know whether
the current component is today or not.
And then here we simply display all that.
So these two here are basically just presentational components.
They don't own any state and they just display our weather data, which was exactly the goal that we
had for this lecture.