Let's now remove some of the boilerplate code that we have been writing using the modern JavaScript
class fields feature.
But before we do that, let's quickly duplicate our file again and.
Rename this one to version one, so then you can keep both versions of doing things.
So, yeah, let's come back here to our app component and now use the class fields feature.
So in JavaScript with class fields, we can basically declare properties directly on a component instance,
right in the class definition.
So outside of any method.
So basically what we can do is taking this and pasting it right here.
And so with this, we can then completely remove this thing from here.
And notice that here we do not need any this keyword because this will basically simply be placed on
the component instance.
And since the this keyword is also the component instance, well then that's really not needed anymore.
So we just basically take everything that we want to declare on a class instance and place that here
outside.
So again, that's a JavaScript feature, not a React feature.
And so if we now save this and then run our code again here, then you see that it still works.
So it's doing the exact same thing.
So that's already a huge win, but we can do even better because we can also define methods as class
fields as well.
So instead of writing a method in the traditional way, we can instead do this.
So let's comment out this part.
And so now we can do.
Fetch weather like this and then we can simply assign a function value to this variable.
And the great thing about this is that we can now use an arrow function here.
And the great advantage of that is that arrow functions do not lose their binding to the disk keyword.
So arrow functions don't have their own disk keyword and instead they get access to the surrounding
one and therefore we then no longer will have to do this.
So what.
As I type async and then again an error function.
And I'm missing just the curly braces here.
But that should be enough.
And so now I can delete this.
So let's try that.
And yeah, it still works exactly the same.
And so now we no longer need this.
So Eslint even tells us that this is now a useless constructor.
So with this, we got rid of all the boilerplate code that we had.
And the biggest win by far is this one here so that we no longer need to manually bind the this keyword
to our event handler methods.
So now these methods are basically defined as a normal variable.
And so then using the async function, that problem that we had with the this keyword simply disappears.
Now, this function here is really huge.
But unfortunately for us with class components, there is no easy way of extracting it into, well,
somewhere else basically.
So we can not just remove this function from here like we could do with custom hooks in function components.
So if we have a lot of long methods like this, then our components can get really annoyingly long.
But again, there is not really a way around this.
But I still wanted to mention this here just so you could see another great advantage of functional
components.