Let me now show you a quick example of child to parent communication, which is a very important thing
in React development.
And it works basically exactly the same in class based react.
So what I want to do now is to quickly extract this input right here into its own component.
So let's actually grab all of this here.
And then let's create a new class here.
So a new component just called input.
Which extends react dot component.
And then the render method.
From which we simply return what we just cut there and then let's come back here and simply include
that.
Input.
All right.
But of course, then we get some errors because this input here depends on some state and on updating
state, which is not living anymore in this current component.
So the location state, of course, needs to stay in the app component because we need it here in this
other method.
So here in this fetch weather event handler.
So we need to do what we always do, which is to pass in.
These things as props.
So this data of location and so that's at this dot state dot location.
And then here we receive that as props.
So now it's no longer this dot state dot location, but this dot props, dot, location.
And so if I give it a safe now, then we are back to working here.
However, the state will of course still not update because the state again still lives in that other
component.
So in the app component.
And so this is where child to parent communication comes into play again.
So remember that that basically means that a child component needs to update the state in a parent component.
And the way we do that is to simply pass down the state updating function into the child component.
So basically we need now this and pass it as a prop.
So let's grab that and actually let's create a brand new event handler function here.
And we will do it just like this other one.
So just like we did in the previous lecture as a class field.
So let's call this one set.
Location, and then this one needs to receive the event.
And actually it's just copy paste at this point.
So let's remove that.
And so with this, we created ourselves the event handler.
And so now all we have to do is to pass that in also here.
So let's call that prop maybe on.
Change.
Location.
And then the set location function.
So actually this dot set location.
So we have so many disks here, it's getting a bit confusing indeed.
So on change location, let's just copy that.
And so.
Now again this dot props dot on change location.
And so now we are back to being able to change the input here.
But now we are doing it using child to parent communication.
So this technique is just as important in class based react as in function, component based, react.
So the whole thinking in react part is actually exactly the same in class and in function components.