Let's now take a break from building our project and build a small, reusable and flexible star rating
component.
So what we want to build is a component like this one.
So it displays multiple stars and then as we hover over them, it displays the currently selected rating
here on the right side.
So as you see, as we hover over the stars, it always shows the currently selected number of stars.
And if we click here, then that number stays fixed.
And if we then click again because this movie is definitely a ten, then of course we can also change
that rating.
Now.
Okay, Now we will develop this component here in complete isolation.
So outside of this current application so that we could reuse it anywhere we wanted and also make it
really flexible by allowing for different props.
For example, here we can rate between 0 and 10 right now, but we will make it so that the user of
the component can choose what number of stars they want to display.
And that's just one of the things that we will do.
But anyway, let's now come here to our project.
And then let's create a brand new component file here.
So star rating.
And then export.
Default.
Function and then the name of the component.
So star rating.
And for now, we won't accept any props here.
We will leave that for later.
And now let's just.
Return something here.
And now what I want to do is to actually come to the Index.js file and then no longer import the app
here for now, and also not the CSS file, because again, this component should be completely reusable
and so it shouldn't depend on any external CSS files.
So instead what I want to do now is to import that star rating.
And you see that vs code automatically wrote our import statement here.
And if for some reason your VS code didn't help you with this autocomplete, then just make sure to
type exactly this.
Then finally, we also need to remove this one here temporarily and instead include our star rating
here.
And I'm doing it like this just so that we don't have to create a brand new project just for building
this one component.
So for now, we will just use this project that we already have instead of creating a new Create React
app.
But anyway, let's give it a save now.
And now.
Here.
You see that?
Hello?
That's coming from here.
So from the star rating.
So let's close the app and the sidebar and then let's get started.
So starting with the JS here.
So just with the structure, we see that we have basically two main elements.
So we have one container for all these stars and we have then like this message here.
So the current rating on the right side.
So inside our div, let's place another div for those stars and then one paragraph for that message.
So for now, let me just place a number here and here for the stars.
We want to dynamically generate these star elements.
So instead of writing them by hand, one by one, because that's the only way in which we could sometimes
have five stars in other situations, ten stars or really any other number.
So let's use the technique that we used before in the far away app.
So entering JavaScript mode and then we can write array dot from.
And here we can then specify an object with the length property.
And let's set it here to five initially.
And so this then creates an empty array with five elements that we can then immediately loop over by
passing in a function.
So like a map function here as the second argument.
So in this function we are not interested in the elements themselves.
So let's just use a placeholder variable.
But we are interested here in the number.
All right.
And now here we can just render anything.
Let's just do a span element for now.
But later, we will place the stars in here.
So let's just write s for Star.
And then here the number.
And actually this should be s plus one because I, of course, is zero based here.
Okay.
And this should already be something.
And indeed, we see star one, two, three, four and five, which of course, again are just placeholders
for now.
Here we have some error, which probably yeah, it's because of that key prop.
So let's add that key here.
Well, actually, we don't because this is just temporary anyway.
Okay, so now let's define some styles here.
And remember how I said initially that we cannot depend on any external CSS file or CSS classes and
therefore we need to define all our styles inline.
So let's do that starting here with the parent element.
And so here we now need to specify an object.
And why not actually do that here as a separate object outside?
So let's write.
The container style.
Then let's set the display property to flex.
So to place the two elements side by side.
Then align.
Items.
Let's set that one to center which will align the items vertically.
And then let's also specify a gap of 16 pixels.
Okay.
And now here we can just specify that.
Give it a save and it looks already a bit better.
And now we can do even better, which is to take this entire object, which will never change.
And it doesn't depend on anything that is here in the component, and we can place it completely outside
of the component.
And by doing so, this object here will not have to be regenerated by JavaScript each time that this
component here rerenders, because otherwise each time that the component does rerender, this function
will get called again.
And so then this object would also get regenerated again.
And so that's not necessary.
And so we can just place it outside here.
Now.
Next, let's also create some styles for the other container.
So this container here with the stars.
So let's say star.
Container style.
So let's also do display flex.
And then give it a gap here of just four pixels for now.
All right.
And finally, just some styling here for the text.
So text style, let's say line height.
Yeah, I was trying to write some actual CSS.
But in remember, we need to write our property names.
Camel case.
So not line dash height, but line height like this.
And let's also specify a margin of zero.
And here, let's actually say one.
So this probably won't change a lot yet, but it's going to be important later.
So style.
Okay.
And now to finish, let's do what I said right in the very beginning, which is to basically allow the
user of this component to set the maximum amount of stars so the maximum rating.
So coming back here, let's say that as the user of this component, I wanted to pass in the Max rating,
for example, as five and then maybe I wanted to use this component at some other place in my application.
But here I wanted ten stars.
But now as we reload, of course, both of these components will only have five stars because we hardcoded
that value here in our rating.
So what we need to do is to now accept that prop here.
Max rating and then use that right here.
And so this is why we had to use this trick here instead of manually writing the number of stars.
So instead of writing one element here per star.
And so if I save this now, you see that indeed we get now ten stars here.
Great.
But now what if someone used this component without specifying the Max rating property?
So since we're building a highly reusable component, we need to account for all these situations because
we will never know who is actually going to use this component and what props they will specify.
So we need to account that this might happen.
So in this case, we have a problem because then.
Well, we have exactly no stars.
So what we need to do is to set a default value for the rating.
So how do we do that?
Well, we can actually leverage the power of Destructuring in JavaScript because whenever we destructure
an object, we can actually set a default value as we do so.
And so.
So here we are actually destructuring the props object.
And so if Max rating doesn't exist, we can set a default simply by writing this.
And so if we save this now, then we are back to having our five stars by default.
And so this is a very common way of setting default props in React applications.
We will do this all the time as we go through the course.