To finish this component.
Let's now add type checking to the component's props using prop types.
So with prop types, we can basically specify the type of value that we expect the consumer of the component
to pass in for each of the props.
For example, we can define that this Max rating here really must be a number and nothing else.
And this is what we call type checking.
So again, checking each type of the prop and specifying what type they need to have.
Now, if you really care about this, you should actually just use TypeScript instead of JavaScript.
Now I will show you how to use React's built in prop types because it actually does make a lot of sense
for this reusable component.
But I will not do this in the rest of the course for all the components that we're going to build because
that just takes too much time.
And also developers these days don't really do this anymore.
Again, if this is really important for your app, you can just use TypeScript instead of JavaScript,
which is what many teams and many developers started doing again instead of using prop types.
But anyway, let's now actually use prop types and for that we import the prop types.
Object.
From the prop types package.
So there is no need to install this proptypes package here in this case because create React app already
comes with this package pre-installed, but we do need to import it here.
So just as we did here because it is actually a separate package from React itself.
Now.
Okay.
And now in order to do the type checking, let's use our component.
So that star rating.
And then on this component, we specify the prop types property.
And here it's important that we write it with a lower case.
So proptypes.
And then here we then assign those prop types an object.
So again, we imported prop types here with the capital P, but the property name here is with this
lowercase P.
Okay.
And now here, for each of the props, we can specify the type.
So let's say max rating.
And so that's exactly the name of the prop that we have here.
And then now we actually use that prop types object that we imported in the very beginning.
And so now all we need to do is to use one of the validators that is inside this object.
So here we can simply say prop types.
Dot number.
And that's it.
So let's say that here we import this star rating and instead of specifying a number, we specify a
string.
And so then here we get this problem or this warning here, which says invalid prop of max rating.
And that's because it has the type of string instead of the expected number.
And it is these warnings right here that will then allow other developers to catch bugs like this,
because, I mean, no one would specify this here on purpose, but by mistake, we might end up here
with a string.
So, for example, also this could happen.
So we could specify the five here but as a string and then we would still get the same problem.
Now the code does actually work with this here somehow.
So JavaScript is somehow able to coerce the types into a number.
But again, here we get this warning because we really should specify this not as a string but as a
number.
And so then of course this disappears.
Now we can also chain the is required property here, which just as the name says, will then make this
prop required.
So somewhere here we probably have one without.
Yeah.
So this one doesn't have the max rating.
And then immediately we get this warning down here.
All right.
But in our case, we actually have some default values for all of our props already defined.
And so it doesn't make sense then to mark any of them as required.
So by default, you shouldn't use this one.
So instead just use default values for all or most of your props.
But anyway, now let's keep going and let's make this really complete.
So the default rating should also be a number.
Then the color should be a string.
And so we basically have one of these validators here for all the types that we can imagine.
So this one is also a number.
Then we have the messages.
And so here we have prop types, dot array.
Let's see what else we have.
So we also have the class name, which is.
A string.
So here I wrote the wrong one.
So always use the uppercase prop types.
And now finally the on.
Set rating prop.
So prop types and this one is a func which stands for function.
Okay.
And besides these two, we also have a bull which stands for a Boolean.
So if it's a true or false value and we also have object.
So in this case, we have none of these.
And so this one is just a function.
Okay.
And that's actually all that we have to do.
And as you see here, adding prop types is also a nice way of documenting our components because this
type definition right here makes it really obvious what kind of data we are expecting.
But as I said in the very beginning, I will not start using this in all components from now on.
So this was mostly just to show you that you can use this yourself in case that you have some component
like this, which you want to make highly reusable across multiple applications or even just inside
one application.
And if at the same time you don't want to switch to TypeScript.
But in any case, with this, we finished our reusable component and we also reached the end of this
section.
All we have left to do is one final coding challenge to practice what we just learned here in this section.