So let's now split one huge components into many small ones using the framework that we just learned
about.
Now, as always to start, we need to get our starter files here from this folder.
So let's grab.
These two.
And then let's move back to our project folder.
And as always, I'm renaming it and then let's paste the new files right in here into the source folder.
And then we need to replace these and just get rid of some of this garbage that we have here.
All right.
So as always, we just end up with Index.js.
Index.css and App.js.
Then we just grab all this.
And open it in vs code.
As always.
Close down this one.
And.
Yeah, then we need to clean up this file here.
And so this is always a little bit of tedious work, but we just have to do it.
And actually that's already done.
You can take a look here at the CSS if you'd like, because there's actually a lot of it to make this
application here work.
So to style that application.
But what matters most to us is of course this app dot JS.
So here we have this array of objects that I talked about in the previous lecture.
Here.
Then we have another array of objects, which is for this watch list.
And then here we have that huge component that I was talking about.
So it has all this JS inside.
So basically all of this, the entire application is now inside of one component.
To prove that to you, let's actually start this application here because this one here is of course
still the demo.
So let's open up our integrated terminal.
That's slightly too big and then npm start.
So that should then open up a new tab in here.
And there it is.
So make this even smaller.
And yeah, so there is the app.
And as I was saying in the first lecture, it does work here in terms of collapsing these two lists,
also writing something in here.
So all of that is working and it's all working within this one huge component.
And so I thought that it was a nice exercise to basically pretend that we're working on some team and
that one of our team members created this huge component and now it's our task to take it and split
it up into small components that make it easy to work with and well, which isn't this huge mess.
So let's use the framework that we learned about in the previous lecture to do that.
So let's take a look at our JS here.
And if you want, you can, of course, pause the video and do that on your own because there is a lot
to unpack here.
So we have this nav bar here.
So this entire thing here is this nav element.
And then we have this main part, which is all of this.
Then inside the nave, we have this box here for this left side, which contains this list.
And then we have another box on the right side which contains all of this, but we will take care of
that later.
So for now, let's basically split up all of this here into the nav bar and into this main part.
So I think to start, that's the best logical separation of the content, which is remember the first
criteria that we talked about.
So those were logical separation of content, second reusability, third responsibilities and complexity,
and fourth, the personal coding style.
So this nav bar here and the main content here, they really don't belong together.
And so that's a good idea then to create a component for each of them.
So I'm cutting this code here and I will actually now create these components here on top.
Otherwise, I have to scroll too much.
So let's write function nav bar.
And then return simply this.
Give it a safe.
And now it's complaining here.
So we now need to also move this date here into this other component.
So this one here is depending on query and set query.
And so therefore, we need to move that state right there.
And so actually having all the state here was another great indicator that this component here had way
too many responsibilities.
So we have five pieces of state and then these three derived states.
So that's way too much.
So let's just cut this here.
Paste that here and here.
We also need the movies.
But for now, just replace this here with an X.
Okay, so now the nav bar is gone because, of course, we haven't yet included it here.
And so.
Let's do that.
And now our app looks just like before.
So now let's then grab all this other code.
All of this.
Cut it and put it into yet another component.
And this one, let's actually call it main.
And as we save it, it will now complain that it needs all of these states here.
So for now, let's just grab everything and paste that here.
All right.
And then well, we just have to include, of course, that Maine right here.
And then after doing that, the app should look just like before.
Well, for some reason it isn't.
But let's see that in a minute.
For now, I will just take this component here actually back to the top.
So just here.
Now let's open up our console.
Maybe we have some errors here that we're not catching.
But.
Well, actually, no.
Ah, but I think I know.
And the reason is that here we are not returning.
So we were not returning any.
JS.
And so then of course we couldn't have any JS here in the UI.
Great.
So let's keep going and let's look again at our nav bar.
So our nav bar is now a lot simpler than before, but it's still doing a lot of different things here
I would say.
So we are displaying a logo.
We have this input field and we have the number of results here.
Now, in a way, all of this does actually belong together because well together they form this nav
bar.
So we could definitely argue that this is okay like this.
But on the other hand, it still takes some work to actually figure out what this component here is
doing and maybe we even might want to reuse some parts of it.
So, for example, this search bar, which is basically this, we might want to reuse it all over the
place in the application, at least if the app grew a bit bigger in the future.
And so let's at least grab this part here and extract it into its own component.
So I'm cutting that.
And then let's create a function.
Simply called search, then return that.
And of course, we will then need this state.
And we will want to include that here.
Give it a save.
And then it looks exactly like before.
Okay.
But now something happened here that I personally really don't like, which is to have one piece of
JSX which mixes like this native HTML elements with our custom components.
So we have this div, we have this P, but then in the middle we have like our own search.
So that I think looks really ugly and I really don't like that.
I think it's quite confusing.
And so let's actually also extract the logo and the Num results.
And so then we make this component here really nice and clean and end up with these three components
here where each of them has its own responsibility.
So let's create the logo.
So we will end up here with a few small and reusable components if we'd like.
So we have our logo and then let's say num results.
Function.
Num results.
No.
Right.
This doesn't look quite correct.
And yeah, now all we have to do is to include them here.
And then numb results and this looks a lot nicer.
So as soon as we look at our navbar component, we can immediately see, oh, it contains a logo, a
search and the numb results.
And from there, if we were interested, we could then really drill down into each of these components
if we needed to.
And of course, if we wanted, we could even keep going.
So we could now create like one component here for the icon and one for the title, so to say.
But that would then be that situation in which we would end up with like hundreds of mini components,
which really isn't worth it.
So this is more than enough.
This logo is doing just one thing, so it has one responsibility already, which is basically to display
this logo, which is all this.
So there's absolutely no need to break it down even further.
So this is perfect.
Like this.
So the nav bar is now finished and we are ready to break up.
The main component, of course, a lot more as well.
So looking at our first criterion, which is the logical separation of content, we clearly have no
clear separation right now.
So we have one component that has all of this.
And so the first visual division that I would make here is to create one component for this box and
one for the right one here.
And so let's do just that.
Take this box.
Then let's move down here and create.
The list box.
All right.
And I'm calling it the list box.
And now we can see.
So again, I'm calling this component here, the list box, because in there is where we will have this
list of movies here.
So let's now grab the state that is missing here.
So set open one and the movies.
So.
Cutting that from here and placing it here.
All right.
Now, of course, when you build your own apps in the future, then you will not build one huge component
like this.
This is just an exercise so that we can apply what we learned before.
But again, never built such a huge component like this because there's really no need to then have
all the work of splitting that huge component up like we are doing right now.
But I think that yeah, for learning this is fun and absolutely no problem.
So let's grab this other box as well and place it into the watched box.
So function watched.
Box.
All right.
Let's grab all the state that we need here.
And let's also already include both the boxes here.
So that's the list box and the watched box.
So basically exactly the code that we had here before now split up into these two components.
Placing the state there and it's not appearing.
But that's because, once again, I'll forgot to return here.
Nice.
So let's keep going, because I still think that this is way too big.
So just looking at this code, it looks quite confusing.
You cannot immediately understand what this component here is doing.
It has like this button here which does something, and then we have all of this code down here.
And so now what I want to do is to extract this code here into its own list component, which will then
have only one responsibility, which is to simply display, well, the list of movies.
So let's grab this.
Cut it from here.
And place it right here.
So movie list.
And keep.
Forgetting to return.
And then here we also need that movies state.
And yeah, here.
Then all we need to do is to include that movie list.
Nice.
And this is still working.
Yes.
And so we're doing a great job here.
So this component is now a lot easier to understand here, if you ask me.
So we have one button, and then if that button is open, we show the movie list.
Nice.
So getting better and better.
And I just want to mention that in the real world, we would probably have one file for each of these
components.
So something I said already many times ago or many times before, but I still wanted to just mention
that here.
So we now have this movie list component right here.
And for many people, this would now be enough.
But if it comes down to my personal coding style or my personal preference, I would actually like to
still extract this list element here into its own movie.
And we have actually done that many times before already in this application where we had one component
for the list which would then simply loop over some array and then display one component for each element.
And so now I will do exactly the same here.
So again, this is now a bit more of my personal preference, but I think that it's actually quite a
sensible thing to do because then here we have a the mapping over the array here, isolated in this
one component and have then one component which is really only about the movie and nothing else.
And again, I keep forgetting to return here.
And yeah, let's then use that movie here.
And what will happen is that we will pass the current movie.
So this one here that's coming from the map as a prop into that component.
We will also need this key no longer here, but now here.
And finally accept that prop.
Right here.
We give it a save?
We have no error.
And so let's keep going.
So I think we are quite finished here with this left part.
And so let's go over here.
Now, here we can already see that it's a bit more complex because here we have not only the list,
but also like this summary of the list, but let's see what we actually have there.
So it's inside this watched box.
And of course, we can also start seeing our components tree right here, which is always nice.
So I always like to do that actually.
And so it's coming together here quite nicely.
Maybe it doesn't even have to be this big.
Then we can see a bit better.
And so, yeah, this is exactly what we have been building.
And now all we have to do is to also break up this watched box a bit better.
So let's take care of that.
And first up, I will do that division that I just mentioned earlier.
So we have this list here and also this summary.
So let's grab that summary here.
And so that's basically this div with the class name of summary.
So I'm cutting that and then let's just create.
Function.
Watched summary.
And then returning this.
So now this code here actually depends on a few things.
So all of these variables.
So let's see what they are.
So that's these variables right here, plus the West.
Now, we could pass all of these three here individually or actually the four of them.
So what plus these three here?
So we could pass them in.
Into the.
Watched box component that we just created.
But actually, if we take a look at them, all of them simply depend on the watched state.
And so what we're going to do is to grab this and pass this watched list.
So that array right here as a prop.
Okay.
Moving there.
Pasting that here.
Oh, and of course, we need to accept that Prop ten here.
And now React is happy again.
So again, what we did is that these three pieces here are derived state and they are derived from this
watched array right here.
And so we simply passed the watched array into this component and then, yeah, just moved these three
here.
Of course, also into this component.
And so we did that instead of leaving this here in the parent component and passing all of them one
by one.
But this code here clearly belongs in this component.
So it's clearly part of the responsibility of what summary to calculate its own statistics.
And if all it needs to do that is this watched array, well then we are happy to provide it with exactly
that array.
But moving on, let's now create another list which is here for this watched.
So this watched movies list.
So cut that as well.
So let's call this one here, the watch list.
And of course, we could have also called it the watched movie list.
And let's actually do that.
So remember how I said that we should not be afraid of long component names?
And so I think that this is a bit better, actually.
Now here we will need that watched array.
So that piece of state that we have up here.
Right.
But let's first give it a save and then see that error.
And.
Well, nothing really happened here.
Uh.
Well, first of all, we have a bug here and it's a big one, which is that we are here, including
the same component inside itself.
So we are including Watchbox inside Watchbox.
So this was by mistake.
Probably you have noticed this as I was typing.
So here of course it needs to be the watched summary which is the component that we were talking about
before.
But still nothing is happening.
So let's try to reload here.
But now we have like this infinite loop.
Maybe we have some errors.
But yeah, I think the best thing to do is to actually quit the application altogether and then just
try to restart.
So let's wait for it.
And.
Yeah.
Let's close the old one.
And now we get that error that we had before.
So before I fix that.
Or actually, let's pass it in already here.
But still wanted to say that it's really, really important that you do not call the component inside
of itself.
So again, I was calling watched box in here.
And so the problem was that this then created an infinite loop of the component calling itself.
And so that's why when I was reloading the application react here wasn't really reacting.
So the application wasn't really able to then render itself.
And again, because of that infinite loop, so never do what I just did here by mistake.
But anyway, we now past the watched array here into this watched movies list.
And so here we just need to receive that.
Give it a save and then we are back to normal.
Let's quickly get our console back.
And, uh, yeah, So this is the list that we have.
And now just one more component where just like before, I will extract the list item into its own component.
So grabbing all of this.
Let's create the watched movie.
Here.
We already know that we need to accept the movie.
And here remember, it's very important that we place the prop name into these curly braces because
we are in fact, just destructuring the props object.
Right?
And so then here all we have to do is to write.
What movie pass in the.
Movie prop.
And yeah, we also need this key right here.
And with this we should be done.
And we are indeed.
So the app works and looks just like before.
But we now divided this application into its logical components.
So components that have a logical separation of the content that might be reusable and that have the
right number of responsibilities and of complexity.