Now that we have created a few different components, let's quickly talk about different component categories
that naturally emerge in most React code bases.
So most of your components will naturally fall into one of three categories stateless or presentational
components.
Stateful components or structural components.
And I say naturally, because we shouldn't force our components into one of these categories.
Now these are all still normal react components in our code.
So just like the ones that we have been writing, but we can categorize them in this way when we think
about components.
There are also other categories that could be used, but I think that these make the most sense.
So starting with stateless or presentational components, as the name says, these don't have any state.
Usually they are components that receive some props and then they simply present that data or even some
other content and therefore the name presentational.
Many times these are quite small components such as the logo num results and movie components in our
current app.
Next.
Stateful components are simply components that do have state.
Now, just because these components have state, that doesn't mean that they can't be highly reusable.
For example, the search component that we built does have state and we could reuse this input as many
times as we wanted throughout the app.
Now, finally, you can think of structural components as pages, layouts or screens of the application,
which are oftentimes the result of composing many smaller components together.
And more about composition later in this section.
So these structural components can be large and non reusable components, but they don't have to.
Structural components are sometimes quite small too.
What matters is that they are responsible for providing some sort of structure to applications such
as pages or layouts.
Therefore, these components might not be present in really small apps, but you will definitely have
a few structural components as your app grows bigger and bigger.