Welcome back.
In the following section, we'll start looking at a core skill that every React developer needs to develop
right from the beginning.
And that core skill is to think in react.
Now, thinking in React encompasses many different aspects, but in this section we'll focus on state
management.
So you will learn when and where to create state variables, when and how to derive state, and also
how to communicate between child and parent components by lifting state up.
And all these new skills will be needed as we keep building our faraway application.
So get ready for some more foundational react knowledge.
And so let's dive right in.