Let's now take everything that we learned throughout this section in order to make the accordion that
we started building earlier a bit better and a bit more real world.
And here it is.
So just like before, when I click on one of the items, then it will open.
But when I click on another one, then only this one stays open and all the other ones are closed.
So basically what this means is that now each of the items no longer controls whether there are open
or not.
Instead, it is now the accordion.
Who knows which of the items are opened and then only that item basically is allowed to be open.
So, for example, if item number three is the one that's currently opened, then number one, two and
23 need to be closed.
So again, all of these items here need to know which is the currently open item.
And so that means that we now need to move our state from the item onto here, the accordion.
Now, I still have the code here from the part one of the exercise and to let me now fork this so I
can basically leave the other part unchanged.
But you can totally also work on top of version one.
So then you only have that one.
So let's now remove this piece of state, because again, now each item no longer controls whether it
is open or not.
And then we get a bunch of errors.
But that's not a problem for now at least.
So here, let's now create that piece of state I was talking about which will be current open.
And so here we will store the number of the item that is currently open.
Set is open.
Use state and we will start with Null.
So then none of them will be open in the beginning.
So again, this open state variable will basically hold the number.
So this number right here of the item that is currently open.
And so then we pass that open into the accordion item and then from there it can calculate whether it
is currently open or not.
So let's do that.
Let's pass.
Open in.
So we use a prop called open to pass that in.
And then we also need to pass this setter function in so that then down here in the item, we can set
the current item to the one that has been clicked.
And here let's use the convention we used before, which is to start with the on prefix.
So let's say on open.
Set is open.
And now here, let's then receive those props.
So cut open and on.
Open.
Here.
Let's for now just comment this out to get rid of this error right there.
And then here, as I was saying, we can basically calculate whether this item is currently opened or
not.
So we can say again is open.
So bringing back the variable name from before.
And then if the number.
So if the number of this item is equal to the currently open one.
So in that case is open will be true, and then it will be well displayed as open.
So let's change this here from null to one.
And so that works.
So remember that this one add one.
And so this is zero one and two.
So if I set to.
Then that one is open.
And then.
What?
Zero.
The first one is open.
Great.
So we created a state variable.
We used it in the UI this time by passing it into the item and then using it to compute whether the
item is currently the open one or if it's not.
All right, let's set this back to Null because, of course, now we want to update the state by clicking
on each of these.
So that's right here.
So let's get rid of all that and then let's.
I use our on open function.
And here it's very simple.
All we want to do is to pass in the number.
So, for example, if we are here in item number one, then when we click on open, we'll run with number
one.
And remember that on open is basically set is open, which should be called set current open.
All right.
So we run it with number one.
And so then the state cur open becomes one.
And then what happens down here again is that one is equal to one.
And so then that item will become open and all the other ones will stay closed.
For example, this one here, item zero.
Well, item zero is different than one.
So is open is false.
And that works beautifully.
Great.
And I know this can be pretty confusing because we're passing state up and down, but this is basically
just the idea of lifting up state.
So before we had the state right here in each item, but then suddenly all of them need to know about
the current state.
And so therefore, we can say that we lifted state up to the closest parent.
All right.
So after this exercise is done, please take some time to analyze the data flow here in great detail.
I'm just moving a bit faster here because we already learned about all of this.
And this is just an exercise.
Okay, Now, next up, what I want to do is to use our knowledge about the children prop.
So instead of passing the text in here like this, it's actually a lot nicer to define the text basically
as content.
So let's pass that text in here.
So l dot text.
And let's close this.
And indeed, now the text is temporarily gone.
So we no longer need this prop here, but we need the children prop, which I'd like to add either to
the end or to the beginning of this list.
And then here, that's no longer text but children.
Yeah, that works great.
And with this, we are a lot more flexible when it comes to the kind of content that should be displayed
in each of the items.
So let's add one manually here.
And so that's where that 23 comes from in the demo that I showed you earlier.
So outside this loop, let's now create just one, one test, one here, test one.
And this should actually be a string, I guess.
The number, let's say 22.
Here.
Let's again repeat the title.
And as for the content, let's just come here and copy this.
You can write it by hand if you want, or you can just write really whatever you want.
So just wrapping this here in a.
This one in a Ul.
And each of these here simply one lie.
So just I mean, this is not really necessary.
This is just to show you.
Okay.
And so if we click here now, you see that we are able to pass in this entire JSX as the content.
And so that's again thanks to the children prop.
So here of course we only have text, but yeah, here we have this entire piece of HTML basically.
And of course our entire functionality here of the accordion still works just like before, so we can
only have one of them open at the same time.
Now there's just one small thing missing, which is that when we click here on an opened one, it doesn't
close, right?
So probably you can see that for yourself.
And so what we need to do now is to basically set the state to null whenever it is opened already.
So when we click here and it is already open.
Then.
The new state.
So the new current open should become null and only otherwise it should be the number.
And so that will fix it.
Indeed.
Great.
So that exercise is finished as well.
And I hope you found it useful.
And now, as I said before, please take some time to analyze the code and the data flow right here
in this component.
And then once you're done, you are ready for the mandatory coding challenge in this section.