Welcome to the very first coding challenge of this course, where you will now for the first time practice
all the skills that you have already learned in this course on your own.
So the goal of this challenge is to build a developer profile card just like this one.
So we have like an avatar image here.
Then the name of the developer, a short bio, and finally a list of skills.
Now to actually build this project, you have two options.
First, you can simply create a new Create React app on your own computer and then build the project
there, just like we have been doing in this section.
Or second, you can use the CodeSandbox app that we used for the very first app that we built in the
course.
So this is basically an online editor, which makes it very easy to quickly try out some new small projects.
And so this is what I'm actually going to use to build this challenge.
Now, in case you want to do the same, I advise you to create a new account here and then once you're
done, you can simply create a new react app here.
So just click up here to create and then react.
And again, maybe by the time you're watching this, CodeSandbox looks completely different.
But just find the button somewhere to create a new React app.
Or alternatively, as I showed you also before, you can simply do React dot new and this will then
also scaffold a new React app and actually it does use under the hood also create React app.
It's a bit different here in terms of the file structure.
But yeah, it also allows us to very quickly build a small React app.
Now before you actually start coding, I have a few pieces of advice for you because this probably seems
a bit daunting.
So building all of this here from scratch as a complete beginner might be a bit difficult.
So let me give you a few hints.
So here I already have basically the app component.
And so let's together look at the structure here.
So in this app we return a div with the class name of Cart.
And by the way, you can get all of these styles right here from this file which is available at this
URL.
So at this starter for this challenge, which of course I will attach to the lecture on Udemy as always.
So make sure to check out that link and from there you can then get this CSS.
But anyway, going back here, what I want you to do is to create this div, which is the entire cart.
So basically the container for all this with this black border.
And then in there we have an avatar component, which will be for the image.
And then we have this div for the data.
Then in the data we have the intro, which is for this heading here and for this bio.
And then we have here a list of skills.
So a component called skill list.
And in the skill list you should have one skill component for each web development skill that you have.
And in order to customize each of these skills, you will use props.
So just as we learned previously.
So going back here, for example, I created one skill for each of these six web dev skills that I have,
and so into each of them I passed the skill itself, then the emoji here, and then also the background
color.
And this background color is probably the most challenging part here.
So maybe don't worry too much about that part.
What matters to me here is that you pass in the emoji and the skill name itself.
And so basically with that you can already customize the skill component pretty nicely.
Now as for the image, you can actually upload the image so your avatar image or any other image that
you wish right here into code Sandbox.
So you can just open this public folder and then drag and drop an image right into this.
So this will then upload the image right into the sandbox and you can then reference that image just
like we have been doing in our app throughout this section.
Okay.
And I think these instructions should get you going and in case you need some more, then you can just
start watching my solution.
That is of course no problem at all.
It's really, really no problem if you're not able to do all of this on your own, on your first try.
So if you need to watch my solution, that's 100% fine.
Now make sure also to read here through this styles.css, because this will then give you the hints
for which class names you should use.
For example, for the Avatar image, this is the class that you need here for the skills list and so
on.
So please go ahead, pause the video now and then.
Do as much as you can.
And once you're done with that, I will meet you back here with my solution.
And probably I should leave this one here up on the screen so you can see what you actually need to
build.
So good luck with that and see you in a minute.
Okay.
So how did you do?
Well, let's try to tackle this one together.
So I'm creating here a brand new React app.
So the one that I actually created before with React New.
And then let's get rid of this file here as we will once again do it all inside Index.js.
Okay, so let's create.
The app component right here.
And actually just to make it a bit quicker, I will already.
Uh, copy and the code that I already had before.
So this way we're speeding up the video a little bit.
So just like this.
And I will also, of course, get these starter styles.
Okay.
And so now let's just create these additional components.
So function avatar.
Then the intro.
And finally, also the.
Skill list and the skill itself.
So again, we're going to have one skill component for each of our web development skills.
And now let's start with the easiest one.
So the avatar is basically just an image with a source.
Let's leave this one empty for now and let's add the alt tag with my name.
Okay.
And now let's grab the image and drag and drop it here.
So I have it in my downloads folder.
So this will quickly upload the file and then I can just write here in the source.
Jonas Dot J.
Pack.
So if I save this now, then let's see if something happens.
Well.
We have some errors here, so let's just reload this internal browser.
Let's just fix it.
And there we go.
So this is way too large.
And that's simply because I forgot the appropriate class name here.
So that's just class name.
Avatar.
Yeah.
Beautiful.
So that's already our first part right there.
It's just closed down.
Yeah, just like that.
So next up, we have the intro.
Which is just some div here.
And then.
One primary heading.
And then here with a paragraph for the bio.
And here I will just grab it from here.
And of course you are hopefully going to write your own one.
Give it a safe.
So that's the next part.
And now here comes the hardest part, which is the skill list.
So before we tackle the skill list, let's actually build the skill itself.
So return.
It's a div with the class name of skill and hopefully you got this one simply by looking at the CSS
file.
Let's close it.
And for now, let's just write something in here.
And also just some emoji.
Okay.
And then.
Let's hear also create a div.
And if I'm going a bit too fast for you, it's simply because I don't want this video to take forever.
Okay.
And I will also explain the important parts, of course, after the code is written.
But anyway, we see that we already included or very first skill right here.
However, if I now copy and paste this, then we have the same problem as we had before with our pizzas,
which is that they are all the same.
And so now we need to again reach for props in order to customize these skills.
So into the skills component.
Let's pass in a prop called skill.
And I will call it react.
And then let's also pass in an emoji.
So this one, for example.
Okay.
And now here, just like before we receive the props object.
So as an argument or as a parameter to this skill's component function.
And so here we can now use exactly that.
So let's maybe actually create one span.
So one element for the skill itself and then one for the emoji.
So here all we have to do is to now write props.
So props again is that object that react will automatically pass into the component when we define some
props on it.
And so now we have on props, props, skill and prop dot emoji, because these are the two props that
we passed in right here.
So again, think of a prop as a communication channel between this skill list component, which is calling
so, which is including this skill component and the child component.
So the component itself.
So these two can now basically communicate by passing in some data.
But anyway, let's now use this prop.
So props dot skill.
And then let's use.
Another span here.
For props.
Dot emoji.
And let's see what happens.
So we have the skill.
But here.
Of course, that cannot work.
And there we go.
Beautiful.
So let's keep going.
So let's say skill.
HTML.
Plus.
And the emoji, let's say, is the same.
So also some strong skills right there.
And so now, indeed, we got two different components here.
So two skill components with different data.
And now let's add just another skill.
What do we have here?
So we have, uh, let's say svelte then with this baby emoji because, well, I'm not very good at svelte.
I just tried it out once for a few hours.
So I can say that I'm good with svelte.
All right.
Here, we actually need to add the class name of skill list, I believe.
Yeah.
This then places them nicely side by side.
And let's actually just add one more.
Just so they wrap onto the next line.
Let's say JavaScript here.
All right.
So we are already almost done here.
So the only thing that is missing and which I told you is not really mandatory because it is quite confusing,
is the background color here?
So how do we do the background color?
Well, first of all, I will pass in a string with the name of the color.
So let's call that prop color.
And then for react, the color that I want.
While I'm not really sure, let's just use blue.
So it could, of course, also do some hexadecimal value right here.
So Will just leave that there for now.
So HTML, CSS.
Let's do orange red for this one.
Then here.
Yellow.
And while svelte is also kind of orange.
So let's do that.
Okay, so we passed in a color.
Now it's time to use it here.
So what we want to do is to add it here as a background color.
So basically we want to add an individual style to each of these skill components.
And do you remember how we can do that?
Well, we can just use the style property or actually the style prop as we now know it is called.
So each of these is called a prop even here.
So like even this class name in JSX and also this style is called a prop.
So we enter JavaScript mode and then we create an object with the property of.
Background color.
And then here all we do is to use that prop that we passed in.
So that's props, Dot.
Color.
Give it a safe and beautiful.
So that worked.
So maybe you also got this.
And if you did, then really congratulations.
This year was the trickiest part.
But my main concern here was actually to get you writing these components here on your own and have
all of them return some JSX and then of course, apply your new knowledge about props.
So having these two components here basically communicate with one another.
So this is really, really important that you understood what is happening here.
Just make this a little bit prettier here.
Let's do it.
Actually, this one orange and this other one orange.
Red.
And even though these colors are not perfect, there are at least a bit better than they were before.
All right.
So hopefully you found this challenge useful and hopefully it helped you really to understand this concept
of props here even better.
And again, if for some reason you weren't able to do all of this on your own, then please, really,
really don't worry.
There's plenty of time to learn all of this stuff throughout the course and I'm 100% that by the end
of it, or even after a few sections already, you will start to get really good at React.
But now let's keep going and keep learning about some more fundamental react principles and techniques.