So let's check out how we can do the same thing with the ternary operator.
So instead of the end operator here, let's now use the ternary operator to do conditional rendering.
And again, in case you are not familiar with this ternary operator, please go check out the previous
section with the review of JavaScript needed for React.
So the ternary operator has three parts and the first part is a condition.
And if this condition is true, then the result of the operation will be this second part of the operator,
which right now is all of this, right?
But then the ternary operator also needs a third part, which is basically like the else branch.
And so if we want to reproduce the same thing we had before here, we can just write null.
So give it a save.
And you see, we get exactly the same result as before.
So again, the ternary operator has three parts.
So first, a condition.
And if this is true, then this first branch here will become the result of the operation.
So of using the operator.
But if it's false, then this last part here.
So this third part will become the result.
And so that's what is rendered then in this case.
Let's check that out.
And indeed, that's what happens.
Now, the advantage of using the ternary operator is that then we can display some alternative.
So let's write some more.
JS Here.
And let's say we're still working on our menu.
Please come.
Like later.
For example.
So then we get this.
So this is in some situations a bit nicer than simply displaying nothing.
But let's go back.
And here we go.
So you might be wondering why we cannot simply use an if else statement right here.
Well, the reason is, once again, because of what we learned in the lecture on the rules of JS, which
is that inside this JavaScript mode we cannot write any JavaScript.
What we need to do here is to write something that actually produces a value and an if else statement
does not produce a value.
So let's just experiment something fictional.
So let's say we wrote if.
Num pizzas greater than zero.
Then this.
So let's try that.
But yeah, that's not really going to happen.
And we even get this big error here and it simply says unexpected token.
Well, that's that's all it says.
And yeah, the reason here is that doing this does not produce a value.
And so it's the same as just having this in the end.
Now, right?
So the ternary operator, when used like this, is really nice and I do greatly prefer it over just
the end operator that we were using.
And so let's go back down here and also replace it in this situation here.
So.
Let's replace that here.
And then also, let's print an alternative here.
So another piece of.
We're happy to welcome you between.
Let's just grab this from here.
So here we have the open our.
Okay.
Let's change it again to 20.
And.
Yeah.
Nice.
So the ternary operator is a really important tool in your React toolbox.
And once again, we are just using JavaScript here.
There's nothing react specific that you need to learn or to memorize in order to do conditional rendering.
It's all already part of the JavaScript language.
You just need to know that this is how you use it.
So basically inside these curly braces to enter JavaScript mode and then, well then you just use the
operator just like you would do in vanilla JavaScript.