Let's now learn what a React fragment is and when exactly we might need one.
So let's actually come here to the final version of the application so that I can show you that we are
actually still missing something.
And that's this sentence right here.
So there is a paragraph of text right here that I'm just going to copy now and you can maybe pause the
video and type it, or you can just type something shorter.
So let's for now place that paragraph here.
Give it a save.
And.
Yeah.
Then it looks exactly the same.
But now what if we have no pizzas at all?
So in this case, well, then we actually don't want to show this.
So this sentence right here, we only want this one.
So the one that's coming here from our conditional rendering.
So let's put that back.
And what that means is that we only want to render this paragraph here in this situation.
So let's grab that paragraph and place that here.
Because again, we want to render this paragraph and this ul.
In this case.
But immediately react starts yelling at us.
So JSX expressions must have one parent element.
And so this is exactly what we learned in the rules of JSX lecture.
So a piece of JSX, no matter where it is defined, can only have in fact, one root element.
And this has happened to us before and the way we always solved this was by simply wrapping everything
in a div or some other component.
So let's try that.
You don't have to do this and this is just to show you that this will then actually mess up our formatting
here.
So this is actually not really what we want.
We do not want to render one element which contains these two, but we really want to render these two
elements here.
So these two elements in separate without it having one element as a parent of these two.
Right.
And so this is the case in which we need a react fragment.
So a react fragment basically lets us group some elements without leaving any trace in the HTML tree.
So in the Dom, so it looks like here we need a react fragment and that's very easy.
All we have to do is to basically delete everything here.
Just like this.
And so this is now a fragment.
So let's save.
And then we are back to what we had before.
So now let's then inspect the Dom tree.
As I was saying, just to show you that actually this didn't create any new element at all.
So here we have the header and see, we still have that footer class there.
Of course.
Let's get rid of that.
All right.
So we have our container, then we have the menu, then we have the H2.
So this one.
And then.
Exactly, we have the paragraph and the Ul, but in a separate.
So not wrapped in anything.
So this is completely invisible here and it's exactly what we were looking for and that's it.
That's all a react fragment is and it's all that it does.
Now, sometimes we need to add a key to a react fragment.
So, for example, when we are using it to render a list and so then we need to actually write it in
a slightly different way.
So first, let's make sure that we have react imported and we do.
So it's right here.
And so we can write, react.
Dot fragment.
And then down here, we need to close that react dot fragment.
And so then the result is exactly the same.
But if we need it, then here we could add a key.
Of just anything.
All right, Now, we don't need a key, so we can just go for the short version, which is, of course,
a lot nicer.
All right, let's try maybe something else.
Let's say that here we actually didn't want this container.
So maybe we just needed all our elements right here directly in the root.
So basically, what we wanted in this case is the app component to return three components.
So these three elements made out of these three components.
And so then that would be very simple.
Now, in our case, it's of course going to mess up the formatting because then we are missing the container
class.
But just as an example, this is what it would look like in the end.
So we would have our route with immediately these three as direct children.
But let's put everything back.
And yeah, I think that's all that you need to know about React Fragments.
It's a very simple concept which basically allows us to have more than just one element inside a piece
of JSX.