Okay, so let's begin by rendering the list of friends.
And to start, let's again come here to our starter files.
And then inside the Eden split folder, let's get App.js and Index.css.
So both of them copy them.
And I will just as always change the name here.
And then inside the source, let's paste them.
And so here we need to replace both of them because they already existed.
And then let's delete all the junk files.
So all of these so that we end up only with App.js.
Index.css and Index.js.
And so now let's get started by opening up this folder in vs code.
So index.js.
Here we need to, as always, clean up a little bit.
And then also remove these files that no longer exist.
Yeah.
And that's it.
So we have our index dot CSS file, which is always please feel free to explore it.
But our main work is going to happen in App.js.
And in fact, let's start by creating the app component, which is as always or main parent component.
And here this one we need to export.
Default because this is the component that index.js imports.
Okay, so let's just return some div here.
Hello.
But give it a safe.
And then let's open up the integrated terminal so that we can start up this app.
Just make sure that you are in the correct folder here and then just type NPM start, which should then
open a new tab over here.
So let's wait for that.
And indeed, here it is.
And yeah, we got our hello, which is nicely centered and that is because of the CSS that I provided
and which is as always, automatically included right here already.
So Index.js is importing our index dot CSS.
So that's why these styles are now automatically applied.
Now, back here in our code, we see that we have this initial friends array, which as always is simply
an array of objects.
And in this case of some friends where each of them has an ID, a name, an image, which is coming
from this URL here, and then the balance that we saw before.
And more about what these numbers here mean in a minute.
But for now, let's then start building that list of friends component.
And here let's again build all the components right into just one file so that we don't have to jump
around all the time.
So, friends.
List.
And then here, let's return a list which for now will only contain list.
And so now we will then include this component right here in the app.
So friends list and no props.
And here we will now place this into this div with a class name of app which has been provided in the
CSS file.
And then also this should be inside a sidebar.
So another div class name.
Sidebar.
Okay.
As always, it's a good idea to have the terminal open.
And for now, all I'm doing here is to inspect the layout, basically.
So here is that div with the app which you can see is a grid container.
And then we have the sidebar and in there we have the Ul, which you can also see is automatically a
flex container.
So all this layout stuff, of course, I already did it in advance so that we can focus exclusively
on React.
But when you build your own applications in the future, then of course you will have to do all of that
as well.
But since this is not a CS course, well, I already wrote it beforehand so that this is a lot faster.
But anyway, let's now here actually render these friends that are in this array right here.
So let's for now create a.
Variable called friends.
Which we will simply set to the initial friends and later on we will then change this here.
But for now, this is the array that we want to render.
So.
Let's say friends dot map.
And by now you should be pretty familiar with this syntax.
So each of the objects is a friend.
And then for now, let's just render a list element and then simply here.
With friend dot name.
And indeed, immediately we get Clark, Sarah and Anthony.
So those are our three friends.
At least the ones that we want to share a meal with here in this example.
Now, we could of course, write the JS right here inside this loop, but since we will have a lot of
code for each of the friends, we should actually move that into a separate component.
And so let's do that.
And simply call it for rent.
Well, not like this.
And so this friend should then probably receive the current friend object.
Right?
And so therefore, we accept that here as a prop.
Okay.
And now basically we can move that here.
And then here what we want to render is that friend.
And into that friend we pass the friend prop with the value of friend.
Close it down.
And then we should also, of course, specify the key prop.
So this unique value that each of the elements in a list needs to have.
And so for that we actually have friend.
Dot ID.
And so as we reload, it looks exactly the same as before.
But we have each friend inside its own component.
And so then we start seeing here our component tree.
So here we still have the error from before.
But now it's gone.
So we already have a small component tree with app friends list.
And then in there each friend with their unique key.
But now let's keep moving here and let's actually build this list item here, so to make it a bit more
complete.
So first we have the image of the friend, which is at.
Friend dot image.
And then we should also not forget the alt tag.
So here, let's just use the name of the friend.
Okay, then we're using an H three element for the name of the friend.
And so that's looking already close to the demo right here.
The only thing that's missing is this button and then this text here.
Let me actually just reload this so that you can see that we have basically these three colors here.
So whenever you owe your friend, then the text will be red.
If they owe you, it will be green.
And if you are even, then there is no styling applied.
So let's implement that here.
And so let's see what these numbers here actually mean.
So here we have this balance property, and if that's a negative value, that means that you owe your
friend.
So in this case, you owe Clark seven.
But if the balance between the two friends is positive like here, then that means that the friend owes
you.
And so let's now use that knowledge here to do this conditional styling and also this conditional text,
because they are, in fact different.
So let's do friend.
Dot balance.
So if that is negative.
Then let's render a paragraph with the class name of red.
Saying you.
Oh, and then the name of the friend.
Dot name.
But then.
Friend dot balance.
And then zero, which I don't really know how to type.
On the keyboard that I'm using.
And so let's just copy it from here.
Or of course you can also use the dollar sign like this, so that doesn't really matter.
But what matters is that now we have this text here.
Here.
We just want to remove that negative sign.
So let's actually do.
Math dot apps, which stands for Absolute, and that's a bit nicer.
Okay.
And now let's copy this three times.
And so here I decided to basically use three times the end operator for conditional rendering instead
of a nested ternary.
So we could also have done this condition right here with a ternary operator.
And then in the else branch we could have another ternary operator for these two cases here.
So friends balance greater than zero or equal zero.
But since these three cases are mutually exclusive, it's easier to simply have three times this end.
And so then only one of these will apply.
But anyway, here it is, green.
And here we have no class at all.
So no special styling.
And here, let's say you and.
Your friend.
Or even.
Okay.
And now here we need to also change the text to your friend.
Owes you €20.
And so that's, in fact, exactly what we have here.
Now all we are missing is the button here on the right side.
And that's easy enough.
Just button with the class.
Name of button.
And then.
Select.
And there we go.
That's our list of friends.