Welcome to the next section.
In this one, we will keep exploring fundamental react topics and finally make our components do something
so we will make components interactive now.
So to do that, we will start learning how to handle events in React and how to update the user interface
using the extremely important concept of state.
We'll also start building our next project where we're going to focus on state and on building forms
in the React way using controlled elements.
By the end of the section, we'll summarize everything we have learned about props and state, both
in theory and in practice by building a really nice small flashcards application.
So once again, a super essential and foundational section for you.
And so let's move on right away by.