So to finish up this part, I want to once again do a quick comparison of the React code that we just
wrote with an equivalent vanilla JavaScript implementation of the same app.
And this vanilla JavaScript implementation I actually gave you at the beginning of this section.
So we placed it right in the public folder.
So let's now open that up and open it here on the side.
Okay.
So again, the vanilla JavaScript implementation is inside an HTML file where here we have first the
HTML and then separated the JavaScript.
So this might look familiar as it is quite similar, of course, to this.
The only thing we don't have here is the button to open and close the component.
So I didn't include that part.
But anyway here then starts or script.
So we have the same messages.
And then here we have to manually select all of these Dom elements based on the classes that we gave
them.
Then next we have this let variable here with the step, which we will then update down here in these
eventhandler functions.
So here we took the elements that we selected manually and used add event listener on them.
We have a similar logic inside of these event handlers to basically update the step variable.
So when we go back, the step goes minus one and when we go forward, the step goes plus one.
So this is a bit similar to what we have here.
So these event handlers.
But the big difference is that here all we have to do is to just update the state and so then React
will keep the UI in sync.
Where here we first update the state variable and then we have to call this function which does the
Dom manipulation.
So here inside of the update values function, we need to now manually update the Dom and keep it in
sync with the step state because of course, as soon as we click these buttons here, if all we did
was to update this value, then nothing would happen in the UI.
So after doing that, we need to then call this function here.
Or of course we could also just have all of this code here.
But since we need the same code here, I just placed it into this function.
So then here we manually update the text content of the message.
While here in the JSX, it is simply declared right in the markup.
So here we have imperative code that tells JavaScript step by step what it needs to do.
So update the text content, then set the class list, set this class list and set this class list.
So set the class to active in case that the step is currently active while here.
That's all just declared in the JSX.
We don't tell react to do anything.
We just write that here.
The step should be equal to the current step and that here the active class should be inside the class
name if the step is greater equal one.
What we don't need the imperative dummy stipulation that we have here.
So we talked about this now many times.
And so I think that this is enough set at this point.
But of course, it would be a good idea for you to keep comparing.
Now these two implementations, there's just one small thing that I want to do here, which is going
back to the previous lecture where I told you that each component has and manages its own state.
So what I want to do now is to prove that to you in code.
So let's actually take all of this code and place it into a new component, which we will call step.
Or actually let's call this component here step, then we don't have to do so much copy pasting.
Then let's remove this and actually call it steps.
All right.
And now here we do our app again.
So export default.
A function.
App and then this app.
Will basically include two steps.
So let's say here we have a div and then we want to have.
The steps to time.
Now, just a few more changes we need to do.
So now, since we have two components on the same page, let's actually return a div here so that the
button and then these steps are all in the same place.
And then just one quick change in the CSS, please.
So down here in the close, let's just remove this line of code.
All right, let's close that.
Put it here on the side.
And then as you reload, you will see that now we have two steps on the page.
So we successfully reused our steps component.
So this is now no longer the app.
Again, it is steps and we can nicely see that here.
And react dev tools.
So now we have a bit of a bigger component tree.
So we have app and then it has two child components.
So but what I wanted to show you is that as we change the state in this one, for example, the state
here will stay the same.
And so even though both of them are steps component, the state in each of them is completely isolated.
So of course, I can also close this one and this one stays open.
And we can obviously also see that down here in the dev tools.
With a bit more space even.
Yeah.
So the first steps here, the state is three and it is visible.
So that's this true here while the second one, the state is one and it is not visible.
Okay.
So that was just a small and quick demonstration.
And so now that we have used state a couple of times here, it's time for you to practice state on your
own in the upcoming coding challenge.