So in this section we will start to learn about events and states by building a very simple components
where we can navigate through a few steps.
And so let's now, in this lecture, start by building out the static part of that component.
Now, in order to build that component, we will actually create a brand new project using Create React
App.
So if you're on Windows, go ahead and open up your command prompt.
And if you're on a mac, then just open your terminal and remember that in the terminal you are always
in a folder so you can see what folder that is here in your command prompt.
And then from there, just navigate to the folder where you want to create your new projects.
And for me that is again the desktop.
So remember that you can see all the folders that you can navigate to from here.
So I am here in this home folder basically, and so I can navigate to any one of these.
And so that's what I'm going to do with CD.
And just by the way again on windows that's the I instead of.
But anyway, I will now navigate to the desktop.
And so now here let's create our new project.
So that's Npx, create Dash, React app.
And now here remember to log in the version number five just so we are all building the same thing here.
So using the same versions.
And then I will simply name this project here.
Steps.
So then hit, enter and then create React app is doing its thing.
And in the meantime, let's actually check out the component that we are going to build.
So that's this one right here.
So it's basically this component where we have these three steps.
And as I said in the beginning, we can basically navigate through them by clicking here on these buttons.
So when we click next, we go to step number two.
And so then we get applied to jobs.
So first we had learn, react, then apply to jobs and then invest all your new income.
So we can click this buttons here.
So we have some interactivity here and we can then also close and open up this component again.
All right.
So again, in this lecture, we will start by building out the static part of this component.
So just the component basically without any interactivity.
So just writing the JS.
But anyway, Create React app has now finished.
I will just quickly again rename the folder here and then let's drag and drop it here onto VS code.
And as always, you can also open it right here.
Okay, so let's clean up our starter files a little bit.
And in fact, I will delete almost everything here.
So we will just leave App.js and Index.js.
So all of them can go to the trash.
And now let's open up Index.js.
Now, this time we will actually not write all of this year again by hand, because now you already
know how that works.
And so we can basically keep the code here that create React app, put there for us.
We just need to get rid of this part and also of this import.
Now, we also got rid of the Index.css file.
So this import right now doesn't work, but I do actually have a CSS file in the starter files.
So let's open up the files that we downloaded in the beginning.
Then here in the Steps starter files, we have these two.
So let's copy them.
And then in steps, let's place them here in the source.
And then let's also just move this vanilla dot HTML into the public.
So we're going to check out later what that is.
Okay, then going back here, notice how we are importing this app from this file App.js.
And so that's this one.
But here, let's clean everything and let's once again start from scratch by creating a new component.
And as always, that component will be the app component.
So function app.
And so you see that usually we use a component called app as the root component of our application.
So basically as the component that is the parent component of all the other components.
Let's just return something here.
Hello, React.
And finally, all we have to do is to export this function from here.
So export.
Default so that now index.js can import it here and render it into the Dom.
So just again, like we wrote before by hand, but now we will just leave the code here.
Of course, we don't always have to do everything manually.
Now let's come here to our integrated vs code terminal.
So just by clicking here and as you see, this is already automatically in our project folder, or at
least it should be.
So now there's no need to navigate anywhere.
All we need to do to start the project is to run npm start.
So this will then automatically open up a new browser tab.
And yeah, here it is.
So this is the content of our app Dot JS.
All right.
Just giving ourselves a bit more space here.
And so you notice that the file name here, App.js, is exactly the name of the component.
And so this is going to be a pattern that we will see throughout the course.
But anyway, let's now together write the JS here so that we end up with something like this.
Again, just without the interactivity.
So we actually start with a div that has the class name of steps.
And if you're interested in the CSS, then of course make sure to check out the CSS file that we just
included.
And now this div here has three child elements.
So it has a div.
With the class of numbers.
And so here we will have these numbers.
One, two, three.
And now to make this a bit faster, I would just duplicate the code here, which, as I explained to
you before, we can simply do with this command here.
So copy line down.
I think I actually personalized this command right here.
So for you it is probably another one, but you should see which one it is right here.
And if you want, you can also personalize all your shortcuts right here.
Okay.
But anyway, let's now move on to the next one.
And here we actually want a paragraph.
So a paragraph with the class.
Name of message.
Let's just use a placeholder for now.
And then finally a div again.
For the buttons.
So here we then will have one button element.
Let's see.
Yeah, this first one says previous.
And then another one which says.
Next.
So here basically we have the numbers, then the message and the buttons.
And so what we have here is already looking pretty close to that.
Now, the buttons here are not purple like in the demo, and that's because we will later have another
button which should not have that background color.
And so let's add those stylings here directly to the two buttons.
And so with this, we can then also practice again how we add styles to some individual elements.
So remember that we do that by passing in basically the style prop into this element.
So then we enter JavaScript mode, and then here we can define our object of styles.
So background color.
And here the color is 7950F2.
And also the text color.
Let's set it to white, which is F and it needs to be a string.
Of course, since again, this is just a JavaScript object.
Now, in case you're wondering why these colors are so nicely highlighted, that simply because I have
this extension called color highlight.
So a very popular one with 5 million installs.
And so if you want to replicate the way this looks.
Then you can just also install it.
But here, let's just copy all of this.
To make it faster.
Next.
And yeah, that's looking pretty close.
All we are missing now is the highlight here of the current step.
So here we are in step number one and therefore it's now highlighted with this purple color.
And for that we have yet another class name.
So class of.
Active.
Okay.
Now, finally, let's also add the message here.
And those messages are actually in the CSS file that I provided for you.
So I placed this JavaScript object here as a comment.
And so let's paste that out here outside of the component.
So this data doesn't depend on anything that is inside the component.
And so it should be located outside because otherwise each time that this function here is executed,
this data.
So this array will be created again.
But we will learn all about that a bit later, of course.
So when objects are created and when these functions are executed and so on.
So right now we are only learning really how we use these react features, but not yet how they work
behind the scenes.
So the mechanics of React are still a bit hidden to us.
We are only just learning how we use the different features.
Right.
So now we need this message here, basically.
So the first element of the array right here, but we're not going to just copy it, right?
So we want to read it dynamically.
And so let's here inside this component define a variable which will tell us which step we are currently
in.
So let's do const step and let's just set it to one.
And by the way, it is this step here that we will want to update later as we click on these buttons.
But for now, we are just building here the static part, so we are just manually setting it to one.
So then let's right step and then the number of the step.
And then let's read the value out of the array.
So that's messages at position step.
And we need the minus one here because of course, the array is zero based.
All right.
Ah, beautiful.
So if we now manually change it here to two, then that will then change the message here.
But what didn't change is that this step number two was not marked as active.
So basically, we need to now set the styles here on these elements conditionally.
So if we just add the class name active to all of them, then they would always be active.
But that's not what we want.
So we need to basically determine the string here based on a condition.
So just like we learned in the previous section.
So let's enter JavaScript mode so that we can write a template literal.
And so here we will then produce either active or nothing.
So let's enter the JavaScript mode basically of the template literal, and then let's just ask if the
step is greater or equal one and if so.
Then the result of the operation should be the string of active.
And if not.
Well, then, just nothing.
So you see that this one here already became purple.
And so that's, of course, because two is greater than one.
All right.
But let's add this.
To all of them.
But then here, of course, we need to adapt.
And yeah, nice.
That's working.
So if we had number three, then all three of them would become active.
All right.
And let's just quickly check this out.
So you see now this one has the class of active and these ones still have the class attribute because
we specified it here, but then there is no string to it.
So that's basically just this empty string that we return in these two cases.
Great.
So that's the static part of the application.
But of course we want to now navigate here by clicking on these buttons.
So not changing manually here, this step variable, right?
And so that means that it's now time to learn how we can handle the click events on these buttons.
And so that's what the next lecture is going to be all about.