From my experience, it's not super hard to understand how state works in React, but it can actually
be quite tricky to understand how exactly to use it in practice in different situations.
But the thing is that this is the number one skill that you need to have as a react developer, and
that's why I decided to create this extra exercise that we're going to build together now to give you
more situations and more opportunities to practice.
So let's go.
And here is the exercise that we're going to build, and it's actually a small project.
Even so, this is a flash card project where a flash card is basically a question on one side.
And then when you click it, you get the answer on the other side.
So imagine that you can like rotate each of these cards here, which is what many people use to study.
So if I click here now again, then it will basically turn the card around again.
If I click here, then it opens this one.
And while this is open and I click on another one, then you see that one closes and this one opens.
All right.
So this is going to be a small, fun exercise, which maybe looks very complex to you right now.
But actually all we need is one piece of state to control all of this.
Now, I added a starter file to the link of this lecture.
So that's this code sandbox here.
And so here we already have an array with all the questions.
And once again, that's an array of objects.
All right.
And so what we're going to build is this flashcards right here.
So all you have to do is to fork now this CodeSandbox, or you can just also copy paste this entire
code into your own code editor on your computer.
So that's your choice.
But what I will do is to now fork this, which will basically create a copy in my own code sandbox.
All right.
And so let's get started at the first part is to actually render out these different flash cards.
Like this.
So basically only the front part, which contains all the questions.
So you'll see that each one has an ID, a question and an answer.
But of course, by default, only the questions are visible.
So we already know how to render lists, right?
We just entered JavaScript mode.
Then we take our questions array and map over it.
So each of them is a question.
And then here we can render some JS x.
Now, many times what we do here is to create an extra component.
So just like we did in the Faraway Travel List app that we're currently building, but we don't have
to.
So we can also just return some JS X here.
And so that's what we're going to do now.
So just another div.
And then in there a paragraph with the question.
So that's question.
Dot question, actually.
Then let's close that and close the div as well.
And there we have it.
Now, what's missing here is the class name.
Of.
Flashcards.
So as you see, I already created some CSS, so if you copied the code into your own computer, then
make sure to also copy the contents of this style.
Dot CSS.
Okay, now we see that here we have some problems which are related to the key.
Exactly.
So each one needs a unique key, and so.
Well, we can just put that here.
So key.
And then let's use question ID, because these are unique values.
And as you know, each element that we render here inside the map, so as a list needs a unique key.
So if I reload now, then these errors will be gone.
Okay.
So we have now our static parts all built out.
Now what we need to do is something to happen whenever we click on one of these components here or actually
each of these elements.
So how are we going to do this?
Well, as I said initially, all we need is actually one piece of state, and that piece of state will
keep track of which question ID is currently the active question.
And if that sounds confusing, then let's just write the code.
So.
Let's call this the selected ID and then set selected ID.
Use state.
And then here we will want to start with Null, because by default, we want none of the questions to
be open in the beginning.
So to be selected in the beginning.
And so that's what Null is for.
So Null is basically just nothing, right?
So now here we need to import.
A use.
State from React.
All right.
And now let's remember the three steps of using state, which I like to always come back to, because
I think this makes it a bit more helpful to understand how we should approach this.
So the first step is to define the state variable, which we already did.
Second is to then use that state variable, and third is to update it.
So as for the second point, let's now do that.
So let's use this selected ID here for something.
But well, this time this is a bit tricky, right?
Like what do we actually need this selected ID for?
Well, let's maybe make it easier by instead of using null here using one of these.
So one of the actual IDs.
So 9103.
So if this is the state.
So let's imagine that we just clicked on this one here.
So how to give components memory.
Let's say that we just clicked here and so that this is then the state.
So how do we want to use this state?
Well, basically here, instead of displaying the question, we want to display the answer.
So we can do that.
We can say question.id equals the selected ID, and if it is display.
Question, dot answer.
And if not.
Well, then of course, the question that question.
And so now here we actually this time got the answer.
So that's the use state hook.
And so that's already working.
So let's do the same thing for the styling, because here actually this gets like with this red background.
And so we can use a class that I created for that and add it here to this div.
So let's do something similar then.
So class name.
Enter a JavaScript mode and then we do the same thing.
So if the current question ID is equal to the selected ID.
Then here the class name should be.
Selected.
And if not, then nothing.
And there we go.
So beautiful.
Just make sure that you actually understand what is going on here.
So as we loop over this array here, each of these elements is one of these divs, right?
And in each of these divs we have access to the current question object, and then each of them has
one ID.
And so what we can then do is to compare that ID with the selected ID, so the one that we have currently
selected and if that is the same then well, it's just what we have written here.
So if it is the selected question, so if the selected ID is equal to the one that is in the object,
then simply display the answer.
And otherwise in all other cases, well then the display the question itself.
So not the answer.
All right.
And now let's set it back to null.
And now all we have to do is to set the state.
So that's the third step.
So when do we want to update the state?
It's whenever we click here.
So in one of these divs and so that's where we place the onClick handler.
So as you see, it doesn't even have to be a button or anything like that.
Okay.
And now what we are going to do is to create a function here.
So just to make our code a bit easier to understand.
So let's call it Handleclick.
So for now, just the name of the function.
So here we need to now then pass in that function, right?
However, that is not really enough because well, here we will now call set selected ID, but as the
name says, we now actually need the ID of the question.
That should become the selected question, right?
And so what this means is that this function needs to receive that ID so that we can then set it here.
So now we need to call this handleclick function with that ID.
So simple enough question ID, but don't make the mistake of thinking that this is finished and actually
react already gave us an error.
So remember that here we need to pass in an actual function and not a function call like we have here.
So this is calling Handleclick immediately.
That's not what we want.
We want to pass in a function so that react can then call the function as soon as the event happens.
Okay.
And that should already be enough, at least for now.
So that worked great.
And as I click on another one, then of course, this one becomes the active one.
And let's check out the React Dev tools, because CodeSandbox actually also has the React tools integrated.
So when we come here to the app or actually flashcards, notice that the state is now 9103 which is
exactly this ID When we click here it becomes.
Well, that should have updated, but apparently it doesn't work that great, so.
Yeah, well, maybe.
Never mind.
Let's just close this down again.
What matters is that it is working, at least kind of.
Because watch what happens when I click here again.
So nothing happens, of course, because.
Well, because here we are simply passing in that ID and then we are setting that ID as the selected
ID.
So just as expected, but as we see here, as we click again, it actually closes the card again.
So this functionality we already have of changing between cards, but when we click on it that we don't
have yet.
So let's do that.
And that's not too hard.
Basically, what we want to do here is to set this ID based on a condition.
So we want to say if the question ID is different from the currently selected one.
Then.
The result here should be the ID, And if not.
Well, then set it back to null.
Now, here, there's some problem.
Yeah, I have one equal.
Too much.
All right.
So, again, if the question ID is different from the already selected ID, then set the ID, And so
that's exactly this behavior.
Right.
But if not so basically, if the question ID is already equal to the selected ID, then set it back
to null and so with null, then none of them will be active.
And yeah, that works.
And I think it makes sense as well, right?
So this usage of state tier was quite a bit different from what we had before.
And so that's why I decided again to include this exercise here by the end of this section.
So please make sure to study exactly what is happening here.
And then after that, I think you are ready for the final coding challenge of this section.