Let's wrap up this section by continuing to work on the date counter challenge that we started earlier.
So in this part two of the challenge, we will upgrade the date counter that we built before so we can
still click here on these buttons to move forward in the date.
But now we can also directly go to a date by defining a count here.
So for example, a thousand days from now is well, this one here or 10,000 or 100,000.
And you can keep going.
As you wish.
So let's put it back to one.
And so that is the upgrade here for the counter.
And the step is also different.
So instead of these buttons that we had before, so similar to these ones, we now have this slider.
And so now if we click here, we move up these seven here.
But the seven was now defined using this nice slider.
And this slider is actually just another type of input element.
But I will show you that here in a minute.
Finally, what we also have is that we can reset.
So when we click reset, it goes back to zero here and back to one in this step.
And this button is only visible when one of these two changes.
So let's go back and let's do that.
So here I still have the code from the previous challenge, and what I'm going to do now is to fork
this.
So this will basically create a copy out of that other one.
And so now I can keep writing the code here without changing the initial one.
So what I wanted to quickly show you here is that slider.
So we can use the input.
So as I said, this is now an input and the type is of range and then we set a minimum value.
You can set that to zero and a max value to ten.
Let's see.
And there we go.
So now this is, of course, an uncontrolled element now.
So right now, React is not in charge of controlling this value.
And so what you need to do, as you can imagine, is now make this input element a controlled element.
And then also this one right here.
So with this, you will practice what we just learned a little bit earlier.
Right.
And in case you have any doubt, you can just go back to that lecture and check out the code that you
wrote there.
So let me just show you here the result.
So you know what you have to build.
So good luck with this challenge.
And I see you back here in a few minutes once you are ready.
All right.
Let's now quickly supercharge basically our counter component.
So most of the things are actually not going to change here.
So we already have the step state.
All we have to do is to connect it now.
So with this input element.
So the value of this element should be, of course, controlled by that step state.
And then we need the onchange handler just like before.
So we get the current event and then we set the step based on that event.
So event.target dot value, and then we can get rid here of this button.
And let's see.
Yeah, that works already.
And indeed.
Well, that doesn't really work, does it?
So it is adding the ten as a string.
So we have a bug in our code.
So the problem, as you can see, is that this value here is taken as a string.
So that's actually the problem that we had before and that we detected using the React dev tools.
And in fact, the dev tools are also available here.
So we could see the same thing here.
So the state is ten.
So ten is a string.
So we just do what we did before, which is to convert this value to a number before we then place it
into the state.
So let's reload that here.
Take some time.
And let's set it to something.
And that's working now.
And you see here that we have.
Well, that's not correct, really.
For some reason.
But what matters is that here it's actually working.
So maybe the integration here in Code Sandbox is not as good.
But yeah, never mind.
What matters is that this part is working already.
And now all we have to do is to create an input element here as well.
So that should also not be so hard.
So we no longer need this span, but instead we will use an input.
Of the type.
Text.
The value here is count and then on change.
Basically, we want almost the same thing as before.
So we get the current event and then set count.
And then this time we're not going to forget the conversion part.
So we convert to a number.
E dot target dot value.
And now all we need to do is to close down this element.
Give it a safe.
And yeah, this all looks correct to me.
Let's see.
Well, something's happening here.
Let's close down the React tools.
Maybe.
Yeah.
Anyway, let's just reload here, just to be sure.
So this works.
And now if we input a value here.
Yeah.
Nice.
So that's really, really nice.
So with this, we have a bit more control over the component and we can calculate dates from now, which
is quite helpful.
But yeah, let's just review quickly what we did here.
So these two input elements are now controlled elements for the same reason that we already saw before.
So we have a piece of state and we then connect that piece of state.
For example, here, the step with the input element.
So we force this input field to take the value of the step piece of state.
But that alone is of course not enough, because with that we would not be able to then change here
the value.
And so we then need to handle the event of actually trying to change so of sliding here basically.
So each time we slide, the change event is fired off.
And so then each time that happens, we want to set the step with the current value of the element.
So that's e dot target dot value.
Nice.
And finally, the only thing that's missing is that reset.
So that button right here.
So let's then create a button down here.
Let's create another div where we place that button into.
So reset.
Close that.
And close the div.
So we want something to happen on the click.
So we use the on click prop.
And now here, let's actually do this as a separate function because here we will need to set two pieces
of state.
So let's call this handle reset.
Now that does, of course, not exist.
So we get this complaint.
So let's fix that handle.
Reset.
And so what's going to happen here?
Well, all we have to do is to set these two back to their initial state using their setter functions.
So set count will go back to zero and the step will go back to one.
So.
Yeah, that works.
The only thing that's different between the demo that I showed you is that we should not display this
reset button when there's actually nothing to reset.
So basically what we want to do is to conditionally render this part here.
So let's wrap it into a JavaScript block and then we can say if count is equal to zero.
Or if step.
Is.
Different than one.
So count different from zero or step different from one.
So zero is the default for count and one is the default for step.
And so if one of these defaults is different, then we want to conditionally render this part.
So for that we can again use the end operator.
Or maybe just why not let's this time use the ternary operator.
So in this case, maybe we should just put a parenthesis around this.
So just to make sure that this is one condition that gets evaluated first.
So in this case, render this and else render nothing.
All right.
So as soon as we change this, we get the button or as soon as we change this the same.
Beautiful.
So that's exactly what we wanted to build.
And so we are finished with the challenge and we are finished with the section.
And so let's waste no time and let's keep working on the far away list right in the next lecture of
the next section.