Welcome to probably the most challenging section in this course, but also one of the most exciting
ones and most rewarding ones.
So up until this point, we have only focused on how React concepts and features work in practice.
But now it's time to understand how things actually work internally, inside, react behind the scenes.
So just like my other courses, this course also includes a really deep dive, which most students absolutely
love, because this information you're about to learn will not only make you a much better and more
confident react developer, but it will also allow you to ace the most common React interview questions
with all the confidence that you need in order to nail that job and would go as far as saying that this
knowledge will actually put you right in the top 5% of all react developers.
Now, again, this section is quite intense and it should probably be in the advanced part of the course.
But since there is so much important stuff that we need to talk about before moving on, I decided to
place it right here.
If at some point it becomes a bit too much or if you become bored, please watch at least the final
lecture of the section where I'm briefly going to summarize everything we covered.
So that video really is a must watch.
But anyway, without further ado, let's dive right in and uncover how React works.