So as I was just saying, let's now go back to our Eaton split up to fix one problem that we have left
in that application.
So let's come to our desktop and then grab the project folder and open it in vs code.
Okay.
And so now we have to vs code windows open and we will also start to react apps at the same time.
So let's just write npm start.
Hit, enter and then it will ask you to use another port instead.
And so that's simply because you're already running one app here in this other port.
And of course each one can only have one app running.
So just hit enter or y as you reached this step and then you will see your application pop up right
here.
Let's get a bit more space and then let me show you the problem that we actually left here.
So let's say that we typed some values in here and then we moved to another friend.
So here we have exactly the same problem as before.
So as we select another friend, the only thing that changes is really the props that is being passed
here into this component.
So let's check out the name of that component.
So I don't remember it.
So yeah, it's this form split Bill.
So this one receives the selected friend object.
But as you see here, as we change, nothing changes in the Dom tree.
And so across these rerenders, exactly the same component is rendered in exactly the same position
of the tree.
So just like before.
And so therefore the state is not reset across renders.
But also just like before, this is not the behavior that we would expect in this application, right?
So if suddenly we move from one friend to the other one, we would certainly expect that the bill value
here should be reset.
So how can we do that?
Well, let's see where we are using this form split Bill.
So that should be somewhere here in the app, probably.
So, yeah, here it is.
And so now we basically need to make each component instance here unique so that each time that it is
rendered with a new friend, React will see this as a completely new component instance.
And as you already know, the way we do that is by providing a key that will actually change across
the rerenders.
So here we can use the selected friend.id, I guess.
So let's just see if they actually have an ID.
And yeah, they have.
So we could also use the name here.
Really.
So those are also different.
But the idea is really a unique identifier.
So let's see.
So we are at Sarah.
And so therefore, let's see down here.
So here we see that the key now is nine three, three, whatever.
And so let's move to another friend.
And there we go.
So we fixed our problem because now the component instance has another key.
And so therefore, it is a completely unique instance right now.
Great.
And that's actually it.
So that's all we have to do here.
So let's close this one and let's also close this.
So we are finished.
We are back in our project that we were working on before.
And so, yeah, there's nothing left to do.
And so let's move on right to the next lecture.