All right.
And now to finish off this section, let's talk about something entirely different.
So this lecture is not really about how React works behind the scenes, but more about what React actually
is, which is a library.
So for future react developers like you, it's important to understand what it means that React itself
is a library and not a framework.
And so let's now learn about the differences as well as the React ecosystem.
And to understand the difference between a framework and a library.
Let's start with an analogy.
So imagine that you want to make your own sushi for the first time, just like I did recently for the
first time as well.
So you have two choices about how you want to do it.
The first option is to just buy one of those all in one sushi kits, which will come with all the ingredients
that you need.
And so then you don't have to buy anything separately.
All you have to do is to assemble these ingredients into your sushi.
However, there is also a downside to this because now you're stuck with the ingredients that are included
in the kit that you bought.
So if you find out that you don't like one of these ingredients, then you still have to use it anyway.
Now, instead of getting an all in one kit, you also have the option to buying all the ingredients
separately.
And so this will give you complete freedom to choose only the best ingredients and the ones that you
like the most.
On the other hand, all this freedom can give you decision fatigue, because now for each ingredient,
you need to research which brand is the best option.
And then you also have to go by each of the products separately.
And even worse, if one of your selected brands changes or is no longer sold, then you need to start
the whole process over.
Okay.
But probably at this point you're wondering why is he going on and on about sushi?
Well, the reason is that this analogy actually translates beautifully into the difference between building
a web application, using a framework or using a library.
So we could actually just replace the images here and call it a day.
So we could describe Angular Vue or Svelte, for example, as the all in one kit and react as buying
separate ingredients and the pros and cons of building a web app with each of these approaches are basically
exactly the same as in making sushi at home.
Okay, But actually, let's now replace these terms with their actual definitions and actually learn
what's the difference between a framework and a library.
So in the world of JavaScript, a framework is basically a complete structure that includes everything
that you need in order to build a complete large scale application.
We can say that frameworks like Angular are batteries included because they include stuff like routing,
styling, Http requests for management and more all out of the box.
Now the downside of this is that you're stuck with the frameworks, tools and conventions even if you
don't like or agree with them.
However, that's actually not always bad.
And so this is not a real downside for some developers.
Now on the other hand, we have JavaScript libraries which are basically pieces of code that developers
share for other developers to use.
And the prime example here is of course React, which is what we call a view library view, because
all React does is to draw components onto a user interface, so onto a so called view.
Now if you want to build a large scale single page application, you will need to include many external
third party libraries for things like routing, styling, Http requests and so on.
So all these functionalities are not part of React itself, unlike what happens with Angular and other
frameworks.
And so this is how this notion that React is a library ties into the analogy of buying separate ingredients
to make sushi.
Because to build a React app, we have to choose all these separate libraries.
Now, don't get me wrong here, we can actually build React apps with just React itself.
So without using any libraries, but that only makes sense for small apps or while we are still learning
react.
Now, being able to choose multiple libraries in order to build your application offers you incredible
freedom because you can choose exactly the ones that you like the most.
And also every app will have different requirements.
And so each app will require a different combination of libraries.
And so including all of them in a framework might not even be necessary.
However, on the other hand, the implication of this is that as a react developer, you need to be
able to find and.
Download all the right libraries for your specific application.
And of course, on top of that, you then need to learn how to use these libraries and even stay up
to date with them over time.
But don't worry, it's actually not as bad as it may sound.
So if you follow this course until the end, you will have a very good understanding of the most important
libraries that we usually include into most React projects.
Which leads me actually to the next point, which is React's huge third party library ecosystem.
So React's huge popularity has led to a really, really large ecosystem of libraries that we can include
in our React projects for different needs, like routing for single page applications, making Http
requests, managing remote server state, managing global application, state styling, managing forms,
animations and transitions, and even entire UI component libraries.
Now I will not go over all of them here one by one because that just takes too much time and you can
also just research them if you need.
So instead I will show you which ones I consider the most important libraries.
And so these are the ones that we will use later in the course.
So things like React Router, React, Query Redux, styled components or tailwind.
Now, many react.
Developers actually do feel overwhelmed by having to take so many decisions and choosing between so
many third party libraries.
And so this fact, among some other reasons, has led to the development of multiple opinionated React
frameworks such as Next.js Remix or Gatsby.
So next.js or remix are react frameworks because they are actually built on top of react.
So they basically extend React functionality and they are opinionated because other developers basically
included their own opinions into how to handle stuff like routing state management or styling into these
frameworks.
So we're in a traditional React app.
We have to make decisions about what libraries to include in an app built with a React framework.
Some of these important decisions have already been taken away from you, the developer, and so this
makes project development much easier and much faster, and it can also lead to a better overall developer
experience.
Now different frameworks specialize in different aspects, but all of them offload much of the setup
work from you.
Also, all of them offer many other advantages besides just being opinionated, such as server side
rendering or static site generation.
In fact, we can even describe many of these frameworks as full stack React frameworks because they
include so many features that we can actually build full stack apps with them all while using React
as the base layer.
But anyway, this is just a brief overview of React frameworks.
We will learn a lot more about this in the last part of the course where we will actually build a very
large project using Next.js.
Now this will not be included in the course at launch time, but I will include it at a later point.
But at this point I just wanted to let you know that these frameworks exist because of course we can
only learn about them once we really master React itself and also its most important third party libraries.