So after using a ref to select a Dom element in the previous lecture, let's now focus on the other
use case of refs, which is to simply give us a variable that is persisted across renders without triggering
a rerender.
So let's just search for some movie here.
For example, this amazing classic Back to the Future.
And so now let's say that behind the scenes of this application, we want to count how many times the
user selects a different rating.
So, for example, let's say first I rate this three, then seven and then nine.
So this means that it took me a long time to decide between the right rating of this movie.
And so let's say that in our application we somehow wanted to register that.
Now, I said behind the scenes, because we actually don't want this data to show up on the screen.
So basically we don't want like a counter anywhere here in the app, which tells us how many times the
user has clicked here.
So again, it should happen behind the scenes.
And so this time what we need is a variable that is persisted between renders, but that does not cause
a rerender when it is updated.
And so a ref is a perfect use case for this.
So let's then come here to the movie details component and let's create ourselves a new href.
And I like to do that right here after the States.
So let's call this one here, Count ref.
And then again use ref.
And then just like with use state here, we pass in the initial value of that variable.
And so in the beginning the count is of course at zero.
All right.
And so now the idea is that each time the user gives a new rating.
So by clicking here on one of the stars, this count ref ref should get updated so that then when the
user actually adds the movie to the list, we can.
Then add that here to the new watched movie object so that we can then finally store that value somewhere
so that count that we're going to create here.
But first, let's now take care of actually updating the ref.
And the way we do that is, again, using a use effect, because remember that we are not allowed to
mutate the ref in render logic.
So instead we need to use a use effect.
Okay.
And when do we want to update the ref?
Well each time that the user rates the movie again.
And so that's each time that this piece of state here updates.
Okay.
And so now all we want to do is to take our count ref and then manually mutate the current property
so we can say that count ref dot current should be equal count ref dot current plus one.
Okay.
And actually, this updating here should only happen when there already is a rating because the effect
will also run on mount.
And so then it will already add plus one here even without the user having rated.
Let's just say if there is a user rating, which in the beginning is not, because it will still be
this empty string.
Okay.
So again here we imperatively basically updated this variable.
So with a ref we don't have a setter function, but instead we simply mutate the current property which
is in the ref.
So that's why we say that the ref is basically like a box that can hold any value.
So we could, for example, also, instead of just storing the count here, store all the different
ratings that the user has given in an array.
So that would also be perfectly possible.
But anyway, let's then now come here to the function where the new movie is actually added to the watch
list.
And here let's then create a new property.
Count rating.
Decisions.
And so this should then be equal to the.
Count.
A ref dot current.
Property.
Now.
Right.
And that's it.
So this should now already be working.
So let's test it out here.
Let's just make sure to reload.
No.
Right.
So let's count how many times we click here.
So let's say first we think the movie is a seven.
Then maybe, maybe it's a nine.
But then we think even better.
And then we come to the conclusion that it's actually an eight.
So we decided three times here.
And so let's now add this to the list.
Now, in order to check out if this actually worked, let's come here to our app.
So where we have our state so that in there we can then see.
If the value was correctly set, because of course we are not rendering that new value anywhere here.
So here it is.
And indeed, count rating decisions was set to three, which are exactly the three times that we clicked
on a different rating.
Nice.
So let's just recap what we did here and why this works.
So we created this ref here where we want to store the amount of clicks that happen on a rating before
the movie is added.
But we don't want to render that information onto the user interface.
Or in other words, we do not want to create a rerender.
And so that's why a ref is perfect for this.
So then each time the user rating was updated, the component was re rendered.
And so then after that rerender, this effect was executed, which means that after the rating had been
updated, then our ref would be updated as well.
So we would update the current property to simply adding one so we can actually make this a bit simpler.
So just like this.
Or even.
Could even do this.
So this works just in the exact same way.
And so then we just used the count ref dot current property.
Later down here, whenever we create a new object to be added to our list.
Now, of course, if we tried to do the same thing with a regular variable, then that wouldn't work.
So let's try that also.
Let's say count.
So just count equals zero.
And then.
So let's just do the same thing here.
So if user rating, then.
Count.
Plus.
And then here we also need to add count, which for a ref we do not.
And then let's just add that count here.
So then we will see that this doesn't work.
So let's reload.
Let's empty this entire thing.
Okay, so clicking one, two, three, four times.
Now add to the list.
And then again we come here to the state.
So once again, really, really helpful to have these dev tools.
And then we see that we have four count rating decisions, but the count here is only at one.
And so this one is basically just the last click that happened.
So the lat variable, which is just a simple variable, is of course reset after every rerender.
So it's always going back to zero.
And so then when the last click happened, that zero was here, increased to one, and then that count
was added to the object.
So in conclusion, this normal variable is not persisted across renders and it doesn't trigger a rerender.
On the other extreme, we have state which does both of these things.
So it triggers a rerender and it is persisted.
And then in the middle we have a ref which is indeed persisted across renders, but it does not trigger
a rerender when updated.
And so that's why we normally don't use a ref in the JS output.
All right.
So this was really just to drive home the message how refs are different from both states and also from
normal variables.
Okay.
Now we still have some problem.
We still have to count.
Ah, here it is.
So forgot to delete this one.
Okay.
And later on we will even see some other more real world use cases of refs.
For example, storing the ID of a timer to stop it.
But for now, I hope that this use case of a ref also made sense to you.
And we don't use refs all the time, but it's still good to know how they work and to keep them in the
back of your mind.