Welcome back.
So the last part of this section is all about custom hooks.
And so let's start by understanding what custom hooks are and when to create one.
Now custom hooks are all about reusability.
And in React, we have basically two types of things that we can reuse a piece of UI or a piece of logic.
That's it.
That's all the things that we can reuse.
Now, if we want to reuse a piece of UI, we already know that we use a component.
On the other hand, if you want to reuse logic in React, you first need to ask the question Does the
logic that I want to reuse have any hooks?
If not, all you need is a regular function which can live either inside or outside of your component.
However, if the logic does contain any react hook, you cannot just extract the logic into a regular
function.
Instead, what you need to create is a custom hook.
So basically, custom hooks allow us to reuse stateful logic among multiple components and actually
not only stateful logic, but really any logic that contains one or more react hooks.
So we can say that custom hooks allow us to reuse non-visual logic, which is a more generic term.
Now, just like regular functions or components or effects, one hook should only have one purpose,
so it should only do one specific, well-defined thing.
So the idea is not to simply put all the hooks of a component into a custom hook and call it a day.
No, the idea is to make custom hooks reusable and portable so that you can even use them in completely
different projects.
And actually, now that we have had hooks for so many years in React, developers have started to share
their custom hooks with the world.
And so there are now lots of custom hook libraries that you can download from NPM and use in your projects.
Now, since custom hooks are made out of regular React hooks, the rules of hooks that we learned about
before still apply to them as well.
Okay, But now let's look at an actual custom hook so that we can learn just a bit more about them.
So first, a custom hook is really just a JavaScript function so it can receive and return any data
that is relevant to this custom hook.
In fact, it's very common to return an object or an array from a custom hook.
And notice how this is different from components which are also just regular JavaScript functions,
but which can only receive props and always have to return some JSX.
Now, the difference between regular functions and custom hooks is that custom hooks need to use one
or more react hooks.
So this custom hook here, for example, uses to use state and one use effect hook to abstract a simple
fetch functionality into this custom hook.
And finally, in order for us and react to recognize this function as an actual hook, the function
name needs to start with the word use.
So just like all the built in react hooks.
So in this example that's use fetch and this is really not optional, so you need to give the function
a name starting with use.
Otherwise it's going to be just a regular function in the eyes of React.
All right.
And that's all the theory that you need to know about custom hooks.
And so let's now go build ourselves some custom hooks for the rest of this section.