And as our first custom hook, let's start with a hook called Use Movies.
So there are basically two strategies to decide if we want to create a new custom hook.
So the first one is that we want to reuse some part of our non-visual logic.
So just as we learned in the previous lecture.
And the second factor might be that we simply want to extract a huge part of our component out into
some custom hook.
And so that's actually what we will do in this lecture.
So we will take this use effect here, which fetches our movie data and we will extract it into a hook
called Use Movies.
And so then we get rid of all of this code here in our component.
And of course, if we wanted, we could then later reuse this hook in some other project.
Okay, so in this lecture I will show you how we can extract all the stateful logic that belongs together
into a nice and well packaged custom hook.
So let's do that.
And actually, for that, I will create a brand new file.
Here in our source and I will then call it use movies.
Dot JS.
Okay.
And from here, we will export a function.
Which is going to be our custom hook called.
Exactly.
Use movies.
Okay.
And notice that here I'm not doing an export default, but a named export.
And so that's kind of a strategy that I like to use.
So using default exports for components like this one here and using named exports for custom hooks.
Now, that's not really mandatory, but that's just the way I like to do it.
So you could, of course, also do a default export here.
Okay.
And so let's start by extracting this use effect here.
So this huge thing.
And then we will notice that we will need a lot more stuff than just this.
Here in this function.
Okay, So give it a save.
And immediately we see that we are missing all of these state variables.
So in this case, the state setter functions.
And so that's because fetching the movies requires a lot more than just this effect.
So notice how we actually also need multiple state variables.
So the movies is loading and error.
All of them are necessary to make the functionality of fetching movies work.
And so let's also extract them from here and paste them where they are unnecessary.
No.
Okay.
And then we just have some problems with importing.
So import use state and use effect.
From React.
Okay, so that's looking already better.
But we still have some missing information right here.
So we're missing the key and we're missing the query.
So to fix that, we can simply accept the query here, for example, as a parameter to our function.
And so now remember that this really is a function, this is not a component.
And so here we don't accept props, but really we accept arguments like this.
So even though our custom hook is not yet going to work, let's already call it.
So use.
Movies.
And so then again vs code will automatically import this for us.
So now you have this line of code here which again, imports the custom hook that we just created.
And notice how it's using here, the curly braces, meaning that this is a named export and the named
import.
But anyway, now here we are calling our new custom hook.
And so let's pass the query in.
Now.
Right now, we're not saving anything to a variable here just yet because for now, our custom hook
is not returning anything.
And so let's actually change that.
So what exactly should we actually return from this custom hook?
Well, basically, we want to return everything that we need here in the app.
So basically all the variables that somewhere in our JS are necessary.
And so that's basically exactly the three pieces of state that we just removed from here.
So it's the movies, the error and the is loading state because again, we will need these somewhere
here in our JS.
So we have movies we have is loading and we have error.
And so again, we of course now need access to this variables right here as well.
And so that's basically what we will want this custom hook to return.
And so let's return them from here.
So I think that's the correct place.
Yeah.
So right after the use effect, we will return and we will place them all into one object.
So it could be an array as well.
But it's very common to just return an object, especially when we have so many different things like
movies is loading and error.
All right.
Now, here we actually have a problem now with this handle close movie.
So let's comment this out for now.
And now there's only one thing that we are missing here, which is this key.
And so let's grab this.
So copying it and then pasting that here as well.
So we could also have passed this in as an argument into the function.
But I think that the key itself really should be part of this file here because it is tightly coupled
also to the movie URL.
So if we pass in the key, then we should probably also pass in the URL, but that we don't want.
So we want to make this as reusable as possible.
Okay.
And so now all we have to do is to then.
Here.
Basically get the data that is returned and destructure them here into their own variables again.
So that's movies is loading and.
Error.
And so that's actually it.
So again, here we are returning these three pieces of information.
So these state variables that we are going to need outside of this custom hook.
And so basically then this returns an object which we then immediately destructure right here.
And so then as far as the app component here is concerned, having this is exactly the same as having
all the code that we had here in the component before.
And so if we give this a save and try this now, then you see that it's working just like before.
The only difference right now is that when we select a movie here and then we search for another one.
Let's say test.
Then this one here is not closed.
And so that's because we are no longer calling handle closed movie.
So what should we do about it?
Well, we can just leave it as it is right now.
So in order to make this really reusable or we could also accept a callback function that the user of
this custom hook can pass in if they want, and then we can call that at the very beginning.
And so this is a way of customizing this custom hook a little bit more.
So we can think of these arguments here again, a bit like the public API of this custom hook.
So just like we can think of props as the custom API of a component.
So a custom hook like this can also be created by someone and then consumed by someone else.
And so that's the whole point of creating reusable pieces of stateful logic.
Okay.
And so.
Well, let's remove that from here.
And just to make this a bit more clear, we can call this at the very beginning of our effect.
So we can say callback and then we only want to call it if it actually exists.
And so we can basically do optional chaining on calling a function as well.
So that's just like this or actually the other way around.
So like this.
And so now this function will only be called if it actually exists.
So without this optional chaining part here, we would first have to check if it does exist and then
we would call it.
So if we now try this again, since we didn't pass in any callback yet, this will then work without
problems.
So you see no problems there.
But now we can actually pass in that callback, which is handle close movie and we can use this function
here before it is actually defined.
Because remember that in JavaScript function declarations like this are hoisted.
And so that's one of the big reasons why I don't like to do this, what many people do these days.
So writing an arrow function like this.
So if I did this, then I couldn't do it like this.
I would first have to create a function.
But like this, that's not necessary.
And so one of the reasons why I always prefer function declarations.
Okay, let's try this again.
So let's open some movie.
And beautiful.
So now the currently open movie is immediately closed as the search query here, it changes.
Great.
So with this, we really cleaned up our app component here.
So we only have like this small effect here left, but we will actually also take care of that in the
future.
And now let's just quickly recap what we did here.
So basically, we took all the logic that belongs together to search for movies and simply placed it
here into this custom hook.
And notice that we used for hooks to achieve that result.
So one use effect and three use states.
And that's important because remember, a custom hook actually needs to use at least one react hook.
Otherwise, it's just a regular function.
Right.
So we took all the logic that belongs together, packed it here into this one function, and then returned
everything that is necessary for the app to keep working in exactly the same way as before.
Now here we just need to probably also add the callback to the dependency array.
But then you see we have this like infinite.
A reload here of error.
Now, fixing this is too difficult for us at this point.
So I actually didn't think of this because I hadn't even prepared this lecture here before.
So let's actually go back, remove that from the dependency array.
But since we should really not lie about our dependencies in the array, let's then remove the entire
ability to do this.
So I will just comment this out.
Take away the callback.
And here as well.
So then the custom hook will not work exactly the way as it did before.
But that's not a big deal here.
So we are just learning.
So we just wanted to learn how we can extract this non-visual logic into a custom hook like we just
did.
And to practice this a little bit more, we will do a few more in the next few lectures.