In this lecture, we're going to create a new custom hook called Use Local Storage State, which basically
will behave exactly like the use state hook, but where the state actually gets stored in local storage.
And so with that hook, we will then be able to replace this code right here.
So this state, which gets the initial value from use state or from local storage actually, plus this
part right here, which is responsible for storing the state in local storage.
Okay, so right in our source folder, let's create a new file for use local.
Storage state.
Okay, so export and then again use local.
Now, some people would probably just call this use local storage.
But I want to make it really clear that the idea of this hook is to work in the exact same way as the
use state hook.
So of course, here we're missing the function keyword.
But now let's come back here.
And in order for us to know how we should design our hook, let's first call it.
So as I mentioned, I want this hook to work basically the same way as the use state hook.
And so it should also return an array of the state.
So let's call it watched again.
And of a setter function.
So set watched.
And then.
Well use local storage state and again, make sure that it is correctly imported.
And then we want to pass in the initial state, which remember for the watched array was simply this
empty array.
Right.
And so let's now comment out this.
And actually before I will copy it and then comment it out.
All right.
So let's then come back here to our hook.
And so first of all, we can specify the parameter.
So the parameter here is basically the initial.
State.
Okay.
And now I will paste in what we just had there before, which is this state.
So let's import use state here.
Also import use state from React.
And now here I want to give these variables here some more generic names because remember that the idea
of this hook here is to easily reuse it in other projects.
So let's just call this value here and then.
Set value.
All right.
Now.
Right now, we simply have a custom hook which sets some state and reads the state from local storage.
But that's not super helpful yet because of course we also need to update the state in local storage.
So we also need to get.
This use effect right here.
So let's cut that from here.
And let's actually delete all of this as well.
And then let's paste this here and of course we will have to rename then these things.
So this is now no longer watched, but.
Just our generic value, right?
And then here we need to also import use effect.
Now, there's still one big problem here, which is that we have this key here hardcoded.
So of course, again, this needs to be reusable and generic and so therefore we need to allow the user
to pass in the name of the key.
So this is not 100% similar to use state any more, but this is really necessary.
Otherwise this cannot work.
All right.
Then here we also need to pass in the key.
Because our effect here depends on that variable.
Okay.
And now to return.
We simply return an array which has the value.
And set value.
And so then it works exactly like the use state hook.
So here we already destructured that result.
So that array again into the state variable and into the state setter.
Now, here we just need to pass in that key.
So that's what.
And as I save this actually immediately or watch list is back, which means that this custom hook is
fully working already.
But let's just go back and do some fixes here, because in the very beginning, if we had no local state
at all yet.
So let's simulate that.
Here in the application tab.
So let's remove this.
And so now this doesn't really exist.
And so then we should get some problem.
So here in the console now, of course, we have these problems because now our watch list is basically
null.
And so then our app somewhere is trying to call the map method on that.
And so we need to fix this and we do this by actually using now the initial state, which up until this
point we actually have used nowhere.
So we passed it in, but we haven't used it anywhere.
So what we need to do now is to check if this stored value here actually exists, because right now
it doesn't.
So we can easily check that.
So this will then be this null that we can see here.
So there it is.
And so we need to say here, basically, if there is a stored value, then return this and otherwise
then return the initial state, which in this case is going to be that empty array.
So let's get rid of this.
Let's reload.
And so then as we come back here to the application, we will see that indeed now we have an empty array.
So that's our initial state that was stored into local storage because of this use effect, Right.
So remember that whatever this function here returns will be the initial state value of this use state
hook.
And so then at the very beginning, value becomes this empty array.
And then as this effect here is executed after the rerender, that value is already that empty array.
And so that's what is then stored here into our local storage.
Okay.
So that's again it.
So what we did again was to take all the code that belonged together and placed it into yet another
hook.
And in this case, we made it so that this hook looks as close as possible to the use state hook.
So we also pass in some initial state and then we get back a state variable and a state variable and
the updater function as always.
But thanks to our special custom hook, now these work a bit different.
So this piece of state here can be read from local storage as the component first mounts.
While the setter function will not only update the state itself, but it will also update the local
storage.
And so we coded all this functionality right here in this reusable custom hook.
Let's just test this one more time.
So being sure that it works.
Yeah, but here it appears.
And as we reload, then there it is.
So great just to make sure that you understood what happened here.
And if you want, it might even be a good exercise to put all the code back and then do it all again
on your own.
But anyway, if you don't feel like doing that, then let's just move on to the next lecture where we
will create just one more custom hook.