To finish this section, let's now create another custom hook called Use Key, which will abstract the
functionality of attaching and removing an event handler for a key press.
So here in the movie Details component, we have that functionality that if we open a movie and then
hit the escape key on our keyboard, then it will close the movie.
And so we implemented that using a use effect hook.
So this one right here.
And so since this is using a react hook, we can abstract this into its own custom hook because actually
we do something very similar to focus here on the search bar.
So again, when I'm here and I hit the enter key, then that will automatically focus this.
And so that is using basically some similar functionality.
And so it's a good idea to abstract this functionality into a custom hook and then reuse that in both
these places.
So let's copy this code here.
So just copy and then let's create another file for another custom hook.
So this one is called use key Dot JS.
And by the way, I forgot to mention earlier that they actually also created a copy called App version
three before we started extracting all the custom hooks.
So basically that we can keep our code before those custom hooks were implemented.
Okay.
But anyway, let's now export the function called use key.
No.
Okay, then let's just paste this here and import use effect from React.
Okay.
And so now what do we actually need as inputs to this custom hook?
Well, this one is actually the easiest one of all because this one doesn't need to return anything.
And all we need is to know what should happen.
So basically we need a callback function here and we also need the user of this custom hook to tell
us on which key the effect here should actually be executed.
So not the effect, but the callback that they will pass in.
So we want the key.
For example, in this case here, that would be the escape key.
So here, instead of escape, we will have.
Just the key.
And then we want some callback for an action.
So just like this.
And then instead of calling of course on close movie, we.
Just call the action that the user passed in.
And here we also need the key.
And so again, never lie to react about your dependencies and always make sure to include every single
variable that is used here into your effect.
Okay, now here we just need one small fix, so to say, because the user might pass in this key like
in different formats.
So they might write escape like this or maybe all in lowercase or maybe by mistake they write like this.
And so what we should do here is to just transform this key that they pass in to lowercase.
And then also the code that we get from the event to lowercase as well so that we can then correctly
compare them.
And that's a pretty normal thing to do when we compare strings.
And so this should at this point already be working.
So let's come back here and then let's use use key.
So again, make sure that the file was correctly imported.
And if it didn't, then go ahead and do this line of code yourself now.
And so here we now need to pass in the key.
So that's in this case, the escape key.
So we want to replace this effect right here.
And so that's again, the escape key and the action will be on close movie.
So this function right here with the difference that of course now we do not call the function, but
instead we will allow react to call this function at a later point.
So basically, when this event happens and the key is the escape key.
So this whole functionality is now inside that function.
And so just to make sure, let's reload.
Let's open up some movie.
Hit the escape key and nice.
So our custom hook is working, and so let's now immediately reuse it in this search component.
So where is that?
And of course, if I were writing this application for myself, I would have long divided this file
into multiple components.
So this is the last one.
We will have one big file with everything.
But anyway, let's now again use use key here.
And so this time, the key that we are looking for is the enter key.
Like this.
But now, as for the callback function, this is actually a little bit more tricky because what at what
we have here as the callback function.
So we have all this where this part here, of course, is already in the custom hook.
So where it compares the pressed key with the key that we're interested in here.
So basically this action here is corresponding to this part.
So we could.
Pass in a callback function like this only with these two pieces.
But then we would miss out on this part.
So we also need to include that there.
So this would then be like cutting it from here and pasting it here, which would not alter the functionality
of this code at all.
And so let's do the same thing here.
So basically what we have here should now be just the callback function here.
All right.
And so then we can get rid of all this here once again.
And also of this comment, since we also have this in that other file that I stored.
And so let's see if this works again.
So hitting the enter key and yes, that works just as well.
So here the callback function.
So this action, as we called it in our hook, is a little bit different.
So a bit longer than before.
But all it does is to just describe what we want to happen when the enter key is pressed.
Nice.
So with this, we finished this part about custom hooks and actually we finished this entire application.
So we are done with this app.
Let's just see why there are some problems here.
Let's reload that.
Okay, so that was from something else.
But anyway, we finished.
Now this application and this section as well.
And so just like always, all there's left to do is one more coding challenge where you will now practice
to build your own custom hook on your own.
So don't skip that video because it's pretty important that you start getting into the habit of writing
these hooks on your own.