In this challenge, let's practice creating a custom hook based on some code that is already working.
So here we have a very simple application, which all it does is to get your position using geo location
as soon as you click on this button.
So when you click here, your browser will automatically ask for your permission and then when you allow,
it will give you your position and the link which you can click and which will bring you to the OpenStreetMap
application on your location.
No.
Okay.
Also, the app then clicks how many times you have requested your position.
And so if I click here again, then it changes to two and it loads again.
Okay.
And as I was saying in the beginning, I already have all of this code working here in your starter
file.
So the application again is already working just fine.
And you can of course check out all the code that I wrote here.
But what matters is this other code.
So all of this here outside of the JS return.
So my task for you now is to extract this logic into a custom hook called use geolocation and then use
that custom hook to make this component work again.
So working in the exact same way as before.
Now I want you to think about the fact that a custom hook should be as reusable as possible.
And so, of course I want you to write a use geolocation hook that you could then use in any other app
that you will ever build.
So if we think about this, then maybe those future apps where you might need this custom hook, they
don't want to count how many times we have clicked on the button here.
Right?
And so this state right here might not really be relevant to this custom hook.
So this custom hook should really only contain the logic that is about getting the position from geolocation.
And so that's what I want you to think about while you are doing this exercise.
So again, basically make sure to not include this state here, which indicates how many times the button
has been clicked.
So that's a small additional challenge, but I'm sure you can do it.
And again, the goal is to then have the application in the end look and work exactly as it is working
right now.
So take all the time that you need and then see you back here with my quick solution.
So let's get to work.
And so let's grab all the logic that is related to the geolocation.
So that's all the state.
And also this event handler here, except for this counter here.
And for now, also, except this part here, although that is debatable.
But let's just comment this out for now.
So let's grab all this code right here.
Cut it and then paste it here.
But of course now we will need to adjust a few things.
And the first one is that, of course, now this counting logic here is no longer part of Getposition.
So let's cut that from here.
And paste it into some function here.
So let's say handle click.
And then let's do that here.
And so then here we will actually call that other function, because inside Handleclick is where we
will then update the count clicks state and also actually get the position.
So let's say for now.
But of course, we are now missing all of these variables here.
And so just like we did previously, we now need to return all those variables from our hook.
So that is actually pretty easy.
So let's just return an object.
So it is loading with position.
With the error and then also with the get position function.
All right.
And then we see here we have no longer any yellow underlinings.
All we have now yellow is this function because we are not using it anywhere.
So let's change that.
So use geolocation.
And then this will, of course, return an object with these names here.
So let's just copy that.
That's a bit easier.
So we will destructure all of that right here into these four variables.
Now, you could also have done this destructuring here, right here inside the geolocation.
And then instead of returning the position, you could have returned the latitude and the longitude
separately.
But here I just returned all of them at once and we can now actually do nested destructuring so we can
also immediately destructure the position right here.
Let and LNG and they are called this way because here we are constructing that position object with
these exact property names.
Okay, then we don't need this anymore.
And then here all we have to do is to also call get position.
And with this we should be good to go.
So let's just reload here.
And there we go.
So the state updating works here and here as well.
And of course, our link is also still working.
Nice.
So that's actually already it.
So this was a fast one, but also a very important challenge, which hopefully made it even more clear
how we create our own custom hooks.
So basically we take all the non-visual logic, so all the logic that contains some react hooks and
which is relevant to a certain thing.
And so in this case, that thing is to use geolocation.
So then we took these three state variables and also this event handler function and then returned all
of that from here and used it here.
And so then we encapsulated all of those states and all the logic inside this custom hook.
Then of course, this state we left outside, which then forced us to do a couple of changes here in
the event handler for the button.
But all that is pretty simple.
And so I hope that you had some fun with this and that you're now ready to move to the section.
That is coming up next.
So see you there.