We have already used a few different react hooks at this point of the course, but we have never really
learned what a React hook actually is and how they work.
And so let's now do that in this lecture.
So react hooks are essentially special functions that are built into react and which allow us to basically
hook into some of react's internal mechanisms.
Or in other words, hooks are basically APIs that expose some internal react functionality such as creating
and accessing state from the fiber tree or registering side effects in the fiber tree as well.
So again, the fiber tree is somewhere deep inside react and usually not accessible to us at all.
But using the Usestate or the Useeffect hook, we can essentially hook into that internal mechanism.
Now, hooks also allow us to manually select and store Dom nodes, access context and many, many other
things.
Now, what all hooks have in common is that they all start with the word use in order to make it easy
for us and for react to distinguish hooks from other regular functions.
And in fact, we can even create our own so-called custom hooks, which will also start with the word
use.
And this is actually one of the greatest things about hooks in general, because custom hooks give us
developers an easy way of reusing non-visual logic.
So logic that is not about the UI.
Now, you might be aware of this or not, but there was a time when we had to use components based on
JavaScript classes.
If we wanted to give component state and access to the component lifecycle.
However, this came with a few problems which let the React team to introduce hooks.
And so now with hooks, our components based on functions can have their own state and also run side
effects.
And so this was a huge step forward for React and made it even more popular than it already was.
Now, we only used two hooks so far, but React actually comes with almost 20 built in hooks.
And so let's get a quick overview of them here.
So use state and use effect are of course, some of the most important hooks and therefore the most
used ones along with Usereducer and Usecontext that we will actually study pretty soon.
Then we have this huge list of some less used hooks, but where some of them are actually still quite
important, like use ref, use callback and use memo.
So some of these are actually worth learning, but others are a bit more obscure I would say.
And so they are not part of the curriculum of this course.
And finally, there are a few hooks that are intended only for library authors.
And so of course we will also not bother looking at those.
Now in order for hooks to actually work as intended, there are two very simple rules of hooks that
we must follow.
The first rule is that hooks can only be called at the top level.
In practice, this means that we cannot call hooks inside conditionals like if statements and also not
inside loops or functions nested inside the component.
We can also not call hooks after an early return because that's also similar to a condition.
But why?
Why is this such an important rule?
Well, it's because hooks only work if they are always called in the exact same order, which can only
be ensured if we only call them at the top level.
And we will look at this in more detail in the next slide.
And now the second rule is actually a bit simpler.
All it says is that hooks can only be called from React functions.
In practice, this means that hooks can only be called from function components or from custom hooks,
but not from regular functions or even class components.
Now, the great news is that you actually won't have to worry about these rules at all if you're using
a linter because these two rules are automatically enforced by React's Eslint rules.
So you really won't be allowed to break these rules even if you try, like we will in the next video.
So if you want, you can actually just forget about the rules and finish the video right here.
But if you're curious about the deeper reason why, React needs rule number one, then let's move on
to the final slide of this lecture.
So let's now try to answer the question of why do hooks need to be called in the same order on every
render?
And let's actually start from the very beginning based on all the knowledge that we already have at
this point.
So remember that whenever an application is rendered, react creates a tree of react elements also called
the virtual Dom on the initial render.
React also builds a fiber tree out of the virtual dom where each element is a fiber.
Now, each of these fibers contains a lot of stuff like the received props, a list of work, and crucially
for us, a linked list of all the hooks that were used in the component instance.
So to understand how hooks work behind the scenes, let's build ourselves a linked list of used hooks
based on this hypothetical code example.
And I say hypothetical because this code actually doesn't work.
And can you spot why that is?
That's right.
This code actually violates the first rule of hooks because it conditionally defines state here.
But by breaking this rule, we will understand why hooks rely on the order in which they were called.
And speaking of this order, our list will be built based on the call order of the used hooks.
So first, this use state call, then another use state call, and then finally this use effect call.
So this is our list of hooks, but it's not a linked list yet.
But what does Linked actually mean?
Well, it means that the first list element contains a reference to the second element, which in turn
has a link to the third list element.
So all the list elements are linked together, which is actually a common data structure in computer
science.
But anyway, moving back to our code example, let's now imagine that a rerender happened because State
A was updated from 23 to 7.
But this now creates a huge problem.
Notice how State B was only created initially because the condition a equal 23 was true.
Right.
However, after this rerender, the condition is now false, which means that this use state would not
be called and so State B would then no longer exist in this linked list of hooks after the render.
But what's the problem with that, you might ask?
Well, the problem is that the first hook is still pointing to the original second hook, so to state
B, but that link is now broken.
So State A is now linking to a hook that no longer exists and nothing is pointing to the effect Hook
Z, meaning that the linked list has been destroyed.
It works this way because fibers are not recreated on every render, and so this list is also not recreated.
So if one of the hooks just disappears from the list, then the order of the list will get completely
broken.
So in conclusion, if we conditionally use the hook like we did here, that will completely mess up
the list of hooks between renderers which will leave, react, confused and unable to correctly track
all the hooks that were used.
And so this is the reason why hooks need to be called in the same order on every single render.
And the only way in which we can assure that is by only calling hooks at the top level, which is exactly
what the first rule of hooks says.
So following this rule, the code and the list of hooks would look just like this.
So without any conditionals in the code and with the list of hooks always in the same order.
Now, of course, this opens up the question of why even bother having this linked list if it requires
this strange rule to exist?
Well, the big reason is that a linked list which relies on the hook call order is the simplest way
to associate each hook with its value.
So basically, the order in which the hook is called uniquely identifies the hook.
For example, React knows that hook number one has a state of 23 and a hook number two has the state
of empty string.
So the value is associated with the call order.
And this is very convenient because by using the call order, we developers don't have to manually assign
names to each hook, which would create multiple problems that we don't need to get into at this point.
All right.
So I hope that you didn't mind yet another deep dive into some of React's internals.
I personally find these really interesting and fascinating, which is why I keep getting excited to
share this stuff with you.
But now it's time to get back into writing some code.