Let's now actually break the main rule of hooks that we just learned about, which is that hooks can
only be called at the top level.
And here I still have the Use Popcorn app open both in VS code and in the browser.
And so that's because we will keep working on this app in this section.
And so if for some reason you closed the application, then make sure to just open it up again here.
Now, just like before.
I will again duplicate this file here and then I'm going to copy or actually, I'm going to call it
V two.
And so again, with this, we then can keep our previous versions of the code and let's actually get
rid now of this dummy data.
Just like this and also of this comment.
So cleaning up the code a little bit.
But now let's break some rules here, which, as I mentioned before, is always a great way of learning
why the rules exist in the first place.
So coming here to our movie Details component, this is where we will now write some code to break that
rule.
But let's actually start by again searching for some movies here.
And then I will open this one up.
So that we can check out the hooks that we actually have right now in this component.
So in the dev tools, check out the movie Details component, which is this one.
And so down here we have the list of hooks that we just saw in the previous lecture.
Let's make this even bigger.
And so indeed you see that the hooks are actually numbered.
So in fact, each of the hooks is identified by React by their order number, not some name or anything
like that, but really only the number.
So this first hook here is exactly this movie.
Then we have the Isloading State, which is currently false.
Then we have the user rating, which is this one.
And then we have our three effects.
All right.
So the three effects down here.
Okay.
Now, if we did call a hook outside of the top level, so basically, if we called a hook conditionally,
that would mess up this entire order here.
And so that's where we would then run into problems.
And that's exactly what we want to do now.
So let's experiment here and let's say if.
The IMDb rating is greater than eight.
Then we want to create two new variables.
Called is top and set.
Is top and then equals use state.
Set to true.
Now as we save this vs code will immediately complain and tell us that here we are not allowed to use
use state conditionally.
Okay, but we can actually disable this eslint rule.
So just write this comment here.
Eslint disable.
Just like this.
And then it should work.
I mean, at least here in VS code, we no longer get the problems that we had before.
So let's reload here.
Then Let's again search for Interstellar.
Okay.
And now I will first select this one here, which has a rating that is not greater than eight.
And well, here we already have some problem.
It's because.
This actually must be after the Destructuring.
So of course, at this point the IMDb rating variable is not even defined yet.
So let's just try that again.
And again, let's select this one here.
And so for now, we don't have any problems.
So let's again check out this state here or the list of hooks.
And so indeed, we have our six hooks.
So the same three states as before and the three effects.
So that's because the rating in this case is just 1.7.
And so then this use state here was not called.
But now let's check out what happens with Interstellar, where the rating is greater than eight.
So as we click well, our application immediately stops working.
So let's come here to the console and then react immediately tells us that it has detected a change
in the order of hooks called in this component.
So it tells us here actually some helpful information.
So in the previous render there were three usestate hooks and then the number four was an effect.
So this effect right here was hook number four before in the previous render.
And that previous render actually happened after we clicked on the movie.
But while the movie data had not been fetched yet, so at that point the IMDb rating here was still
undefined.
And so then this use state hook was not called.
But then as soon as the data arrived, the IMDb rating was indeed greater than eight.
And so then React called use state here.
And so then on the next render, the fourth hook was no longer the use effect but this state right here.
And so therefore now clearly we can see that our linked list of hooks is different.
And so React is not happy about that at all.
So let's, of course, turn this off and then it should go back to working.
So this one is pretty obvious that we shouldn't use it.
And also, as you saw, Eslint immediately warned us of that problem that we were creating.
However, in certain situations you might not have eslint installed.
And so in those cases, you really need to be very careful.
Now, one more subtle thing that can happen is an early return.
So if we say.
If IMDb rating greater than eight, then let's immediately return some JSX here.
Let's say.
Greatest.
Ever.
And so if we do the same thing as before Interstellar.
Then here the IMDb rating is less than eight, but as we click here, then we run into exactly the same
problem.
Now.
This time, the error message doesn't contain the previous list of hooks.
But still, it tells us that this time fewer hooks were actually rendered.
And so that's because right now we only have the movie.
And so these three states, but then the effects, so the three effects that we had, they are now no
longer created.
So instead of the six hooks, we now only have three hooks.
And so therefore this again creates a big problem because like this, we cannot guarantee that all the
hooks are always called in the same order.
So be very careful of that.
And so now after this small experiment, you know what these error messages here mean.
And so hopefully you enjoyed this small experiment.
Let's just turn this off.
And also let's remove this line right here, because of course, we want Eslint to work so that it can
warn us before we create a bug like this.