Let's now look at the super important use state hook again and review some important details that we
have already talked about as well.
So we have been using the use data since almost the beginning of the course because this is in fact
the most important hook in React.
So we have used it in many different ways and we know pretty much how it works at this point.
However, I want to again review some important parts of it, and I want to draw your attention to one
very important detail, which is the fact that these initial values that we pass into use state only
really matter on the initial render.
So let's see an example of that.
And let's say that we actually wanted something like this here to work.
So we wanted a piece of state called a stop, which is true if the IMDb rating is greater than eight.
Now, we cannot do this as we already learned in the previous lecture, but we might think that this
works.
So basically.
Doing this.
So IMDb.
Greater than eight.
So let's see if that works actually.
And let's then log this state to the console.
Okay.
Let's search for a movie, as always.
And then let's wait for it.
And we see that this log here coming from line 266, which is this one here, is indeed false, even
though the rating here is actually greater than eight.
And if we take a look at our list of hooks, then we also see that this one is set to false.
So why is that?
Well, it is because of the reason that I just mentioned before, which is the fact that whatever we
pass into use state is the initial state.
And react will only look at this initial state on the initial render.
So when the component first mounts.
However, when the component first mounts here, the IMDb rating will still be undefined.
And so this here is then false.
And so it will stay false forever because nowhere we update the state and on the second render.
So when we then finally get the movie data, this will not be executed again.
And so therefore again, it will stay false forever.
Now, one way of fixing this would be to use a use effect.
So if we did use effect.
Passing in a function.
And then we wanted to run this effect each time that the IMDb rating updates.
And so each time that does happen, then we want to call set is top.
And then we can do IMDb rating greater than eight.
And so in this case, this should then work.
And let's see.
And indeed, now it is true.
And if we take a look again here at or.
Yeah, at our different hooks we see that now indeed is top is true.
So our fourth hook here and so that is simply because of this use effect.
Now, of course, in this situation, we shouldn't even use a piece of state in the first place.
So if this here was the functionality that we really wanted, then what we should do is derived state.
So we shouldn't create a real state with the use state hook, but instead we should just do const.
Is.
Top and then simply IMDb rating greater than eight.
So let's comment all of this here out.
Gave it a safe.
And if we then lock that again to the console.
You see that?
This simple code works seamlessly.
So let's wait for it here.
Cleaning or console.
And so it is true.
And so that's because this variable here is, of course, regenerated each time that the function here
is executed.
So after each render.
And so this is the power.
And one of the great advantages of derived state, which is that it updates basically as the component
gets re rendered.
And this is really as simple as it can get right.
So this is pretty important to understand so that the initial state value here is only been looked at
by react in the very beginning.
So only on component mount.
So never forget that.
And now I want to come back to this function right here to give you yet another example or another proof
that updating state really is asynchronous and that we need to use a callback function to update state
in certain situations.
So let's say that when we add a new movie to our watch list right here, we want it to display the average
of the rating that we gave and the rating that is coming from IMDb.
So we wanted that to be displayed right here instead of closing the movie immediately.
So let's first of all here remove this part and then let's create a new piece of state.
Because if we want to display something on the screen, well, then we need a new piece of state.
So let's call this average rating and set average.
Rating.
And your state.
And let's just set it to zero.
And then we want to render that here.
Really somewhere it doesn't really matter because we will remove this here in a minute anyway.
So this is just to give you another demonstration of updating state asynchronously.
So where is that function?
Uh, here it is.
Okay.
And so now here we should see the zero.
And I used the value of zero here and not the current IMDb rating because again, this will just be
undefined in the beginning and so there's no need to place that there.
No.
Right.
But then as we click on this button here.
Then this function here is executed.
And so let's then actually set that state.
So set average rating.
And let's say that first we wanted to set it to the actual current IMDb rating, which is a string.
So let's convert that to a number.
So IMDb rating.
And now watch what happens if we lock this to the console or maybe even if we alert this.
So then it becomes really visible.
So.
Rating.
So let's see.
And so the AVG rating should now be 8.6 because we set it to IMDb rating, which is 8.6.
So watch what happens.
Well, it is still zero.
And so that's again, because the state is set asynchronously here.
Or in other words, we do not get access to the updated state right after doing that.
So right after we call the state updating function.
So only once React is done processing this event handler, it will then update all the state and rerender
the UI.
All right.
But anyway, let's now do another one.
So set AVG rating.
And so let's now attempt to calculate the average.
So taking IMDb rating or actually we want the average rating.
So average rating plus the user rating and then divide it by two.
So let's see.
Let's delete this here.
And let's use ten this time.
And then we get a wrong average here.
So our average is not correctly being calculated.
So this five here is really just ten divided by two.
So the reason for that is that here the average rating is still at zero.
And so then zero plus ten divided by two is indeed the five.
But why is the average rating still at zero here, even though we have updated it before?
And by now, you already know the answer.
So it's asynchronous state setting, which means that at this point here, the average rating has not
been set yet.
So it's still at zero, which is the initial value right here.
And so because of that, we say that the average rating state is stale at this point.
So we have stale state right here.
But luckily for us, we already know how to solve this, which is by passing in a callback function.
And so that callback will get access to the current value.
And so let's again call that average rating.
But of course, it could be called anything.
So let's try one more time.
Again.
Ten and beautiful.
So now we get the correct average.
Nice.
So this time what happened was that the average was again set to the IMDb rating, so the 8.6.
But then in the next line here, we already got access to that new value.
And then here the 8.6 plus the ten gave us the correct average.
And again here this could be really called anything and it would always work in the exact same way.
So if we do that again, then yeah, we will still get 9.3.
And so that's because this is simply the name of the argument of the callback function that react will
pass into the function.
So it will simply pass the current state value into the function.
But we can then of course give it any name that we want, but let's put it back and indeed let's actually
remove all of this that we just wrote.
So this was just yet another experiment.
But I hope that it was a helpful one.
So here.
Actually, no, I thought I saw some error there.
So let's put it back.
And so now the application should work just like before.
All right.
And now there's just one final thing to learn about the use state took, which is that besides using
a callback like this to update state, we can also use a callback to initialize state.
And so let's learn how to do that in the next lecture.