In this lecture, we're finally going to build a brand new feature for our app, which is to persist
the watch list in local storage.
So right now, if we have some movies here in our watch list, and if we then reload the page, then
you see that of course our movies are going to be gone.
So they're not persisted, so they're not stored anywhere.
And so that's why in this lecture we will now use local storage to store this watched data information
in the browser.
So we're going to do this in two parts.
First, each time that the watch list state is updated, we will update the local storage.
So we will store that data into local storage and then each time that the application loads.
So when the app component first mounts, we will read that data from local storage and store it into
the watched state.
So let's do that starting with the first part, which is to store the watched movies here into local
storage each time that they are updated.
And we can actually do that in two different ways or in two different places.
So the first option is to store that data into local storage each time that a new movie is actually
added.
So basically right here in this event handler function that is responsible for adding new movies to
the watch list.
So each time that happens, we can then store the new watch list into local storage.
So that's the first option.
And the second option is to simply do it in an effect.
And so let's actually do both of them starting here in this event handler function.
Now, by the way, if you're not familiar with local storage, it's basically just a very simple key
value pair storage that is available in the browser and where we can store some data for each domain.
So basically the data that we store in local storage now will only be available to exactly this URL
right here, not for example, in this other one.
All right.
And the way we use local storage is simply calling local storage, which is a function available in
all browsers.
And then we set item.
Then we pass in the name of the key.
So basically the name of the data that we want to store and then second, the actual data.
Now here we can not simply use the watched array like this because it has just been updated here.
And so, as we already know, this updating happens in an asynchronous way.
And so therefore right here, this is still stale state.
So it's basically still the old version before a new movie has been added.
And so we need to basically do the same thing as here.
So we need to build a new array based on the watched.
So the current state.
Plus the new movie.
And then finally, we need to convert all of this into a string because in local storage we can only
store key value pairs where the value is a string.
And so let's use the built in Json dot stringify.
All right.
And this should now actually work.
Let's try some different movies now.
Here.
So let's try this one, which is actually one of my all time favorite movies.
So let's add that to the list and maybe another one.
All right.
And so now we have our two movies in the list.
But of course, if we reload the page now, they will not magically appear back in the UI, but we can
still check if they have been stored into local storage.
So in the dev tools, again, we just come here to application and then here on the left side you should
have this local storage thing.
And so indeed here we see that our array of watched movies has indeed been stored into local storage.
Great.
So that's working.
But as I was saying, we can also do it right inside an effect.
So instead of doing it here in the event handler function and we will actually do it in an effect instead
of here in this event handler function, because later in the section we will want to make this storing
data into local storage reusable.
So let's just comment this out and then let's come down here and create a new effect.
So you see that I like to have always the states here in the beginning of the component.
Then the event handler functions which update some of the state and then in the end, the effects.
So let's create a new effect.
With a function.
And then as we were just saying, we want this effect to run each time that the watched movies are updated.
And so then here we can very easily let's just grab this first part here or actually all of it.
So let's paste that here and now.
We don't have to create any new array because this effect here will only run after the movies have already
been updated.
So after Watched is already the new state.
And so we can then simply use that here.
All right, let's reload.
And we see that our local storage has already been updated.
And that's because this effect here run when the component was first mount.
And so at this point, the watched state is by default still this empty array.
And so then react, set that here to the empty array.
So let's just try.
Well, that's not correct.
And for some reason here, the loading state is no longer working.
But let's take a look at that later.
So as we add new movies to the list now we should see our local storage being updated.
Nice.
So that part is working.
And so now we need to take care of the second part, which is to read this data back into the application
as soon as the app component mounts.
So the component that owns this watched state.
Now, how can we do that?
Well, we might think that we should use another effect in order to get the data from local storage
on the initial render and then store that data in the watched state.
However, there is actually a better way.
And so let me show that to you.
So let's deactivate this watch state here.
And maybe let's move it down here.
And then duplicate it, because we still need this state.
Of course.
So what we're going to do now is to, instead of just passing in a value, is to pass in a callback
function.
And so that's because the use state hook also accepts a callback function instead of just a single value.
And so we can then initialize the state with whatever value this callback function will return.
And so let's try that out.
So let's pass in a function here.
So creating a brand new function.
And so then let's create a new variable.
Let's say, stored.
Value and then we can just read.
From local storage with the get item method.
So get item.
And then the key that we used before to store the data in local storage.
So that's this key right here.
And so then we just need to return this value.
And so again, React will then call this function here on the initial render and we'll use whatever
value is returned from this function as the initial value of the state.
And this function here actually needs to be a pure function and it cannot receive any arguments.
So passing arguments here is not going to work.
So just a very simple, pure function that returns something and that something will be used by React
as the initial state.
And also, just like the values that we pass in React will only consider this function here on the initial
render.
So this function is only executed once on the initial render and is simply ignored on subsequent rerenders.
Now, apparently there is some problem here, so let's check that out.
So what?
The map is not a function.
And I actually saw that coming because right now the local storage here is a string.
So remember that we stored the data as a string by doing json.stringify.
And then when we get the data back, we need to convert it back by doing Json.
Dot parse.
All right.
And beautiful.
So here the movie that we added to our watch list before is now indeed back in our watch list after
reloading the page.
So we successfully stored the data in local storage and retrieved it as the application loads.
So our callback function here is doing its job.
And so this creates a much better experience for the user.
So whenever the initial value of the state depends on some sort of computation, we should always pass
in a function like this.
So function that react can execute on its initial render.
So we should not call a function inside the state.
So we should not.
Do this.
Okay.
So this is very different.
Here we are calling a function, not passing a function in.
And so this we should not do because even though React would ignore the value of this, it would still
call this function on every render, which is not good.
So never do this and instead pass in a function that react can then call later.
Okay.
Now let's again go back to our application tab here, because now we want to see what happens when we
delete a movie from here.
And you see that it actually automatically got removed here from the local storage as well.
So why is that?
Well, it's because thanks to our effect here, we have effectively synchronized the watched state with
our local storage.
So when the watched state changes, our local storage changes as well.
And so this is a great advantage of having used the Useeffect hook instead of setting local state right
here in the event handler.
Because if we had done it like this here, then we would also have to manually set the local storage
here as we deleted a movie.
So here we would then also have to do the exact same thing and use all this here as the new local storage.
But so now since we have basically synchronized the two of them, we no longer need to do that.
All right, Now let's just see what happens when we reload the page.
And everything's working fine.
Let's just do one more test.
Add a few more movies to our list.
And of course, this is a ten, not some other value.
No.
Okay.
Now, see, we are getting some errors here, but maybe that was.
Yeah, that's because of the image not loading.
And now when I reload the beautiful, both our movies are still in the list.
So we learned here yet another way of using the state took.
So now we know that besides passing in a single value, we can also pass in a callback function.
So this all can be a little bit confusing with all these different options that we have.
And so in the next lecture we will basically summarize everything that we know about the use state hook,
since that is such an important talk in React development.