Let's quickly summarize everything that we know about the use state hook in one single slide so that
you can keep it as a handy reference.
So we use the use state took to first create state and then the setter function that results from creating
state to update state.
Now we can create a state variable in the simple way, which is what we do most of the time, but we
can also create state based on a callback function.
So whenever the initial state depends on some computation, for example, reading data from local storage,
we can pass in a callback function like this instead of just a single value.
And this process is sometimes called lazy evaluation.
Now this callback function is only called on the initial render of the component, so on subsequent
renders it will simply be ignored.
Also, this callback needs to fulfill two requirements.
First, it must be a pure function and second, it should require no arguments in order to work.
And that's actually it.
That's how we create state variables using usestate.
And now about updating state, we can again update state in a simple way just by passing a single value
into the returned setter function as the next state.
So in this example, the next state would be 1000.
On the other hand, in many situations we actually want to update state based on the current state.
For example, increasing a counter by one.
So if that's the case, we can give the setter function a callback function like this.
So a function that is pure and returns the next state based on the current state.
And this is, in my opinion, the preferred way of updating state whenever it makes sense.
Now, one important rule to keep in mind about updating state is that you should never mutate objects
or arrays.
Instead, you must create a new object or a new array which incorporates the changes that you want to
make and then pass that new object into the setter function.
And we have done that multiple times already.
But I just wanted to mention this here in the summary lecture as well.
Okay.
So in conclusion, both for creating and for updating state, we have both a simple way and a way that
requires a callback function.
So this can be a little bit confusing, which is why I decided to create this overview.
So I hope that this makes everything crystal clear and that you have now mastered the use state hook
once and for all.