The soul with the topic of youth state now behind us.
Let's turn our focus on something called refs.
And so in this lecture, let's manually select a Dom element so that you see why we actually need refs
in React.
So as an experiment, let's try to automatically give this input element here.
Focus each time that the search component mounts.
So basically, each time the application mounts, we will automatically focus on this input field.
Okay.
And in order to do that, we actually need to select this element.
And so let's try to do that with the tools that we already have.
So we come here into our search component, which is where that input field is located.
And so then we can basically use a use effect and then manually select this Dom element right here.
So let's try that out.
And then let's execute this effect as soon as this component mounts.
So let's create some element by simply doing document dot query selector.
And then we can just use the class name that is already here on the element.
So dot search.
No.
Okay.
Just to see if this works.
Let's lock this to the console.
And you see that indeed there is our input field.
And so now what we can do is to just say L so just this element and then call the focus method on that.
And so this is just some straightforward, typical Dom manipulation.
Okay.
And so now if we load the application and so you see as the application first loaded, this input field
automatically got focused.
So our code here is basically doing its job.
However, as we learned at the very beginning, React is all about being declarative and so manually
selecting a Dom element like this is not really the react way of doing things.
So it's not in line with the rest of our React code.
So in React, we really don't want to manually add event listeners like this And also having to add
classes or IDs just for the purpose of selecting is not really nice.
And again, not really the react way of doing things.
So here we already had the class name of course, but if we didn't, then we would have to now add that
class name or ID here to then use it in the effect to select the element.
Also, if for some reason we would need some dependency here.
For example, if this code should rerun each time the query changes, then that would mean that we would
select the element here over and over again, which is also not ideal.
Okay.
And so to solve all these problems and to make the action of selecting an elements more declarative,
such as everything else in React, we need the concept of refs.
And so that's what we're going to learn about in the next video.