It's time to introduce yet another react hook.
And this time it's the use rev hook.
And fortunately for us, this is one of the easiest hooks of all.
And so let's now take a look.
So we use the use ref hook to create something called a ref.
But what actually is a ref?
Well, ref stands for reference and essentially it's like a box into which we can put any data that
we want to be preserved between renderers.
Now, in technical terms, when we use Useref, react will give us an object with a mutable current
property and we can then write any data into this current property and of course also read from it.
So in this small example, the current property was first set to the initial value of 23 and we then
changed it to 1000.
So as you can see, this current property is actually mutable.
So unlike everything else in React.
But what's really special about refs is that they are persisted across renders so their current property
value stays the same between multiple renders.
So just like state and this gives us two big use cases for refs.
First, as we just said, we can use refs to create variables that will stay the same between renders
and useful.
Examples of this are preserving the previous state or storing the ID of a set timeout function.
Now, the second use case is actually far more important, which is to select and store Dom elements.
So this is what we attempted to do in the last lecture and which actually brought us to this lecture.
So just like the ID of a set timeout, a Dom element is also a piece of data that we want to store and
preserve across renders.
And so refs are perfect for this.
Now, Revs are usually for data that is not rendered in the visual output of the component.
So usually revs only appear in event handlers or effects, but not in the JS.
Now of course we can use revs inside JS too, but usually that's not the place for them.
If you need data that participates in the visual output of the component, that's usually a good sign
that you actually need state and not a ref.
And speaking of state, just like with state, you are not allowed to write or to read the current property
in render logic as that would create an undesirable side effect.
Instead, we usually perform these mutations inside a useeffect hook.
Okay, now I've hinted a couple of times at all the similarities between refs and state, which is because
these two are in fact quite similar.
So let's now analyze what they have in common and what's different between them.
So in a way, we can say that refs are like state but with less powers.
So what they have in common is that they are both persisted across renders.
So the component remembers these values even after rerendering.
The big difference is that updating state will actually cause the component to rerender while updating
refs does not.
So the big takeaway from this is that we use state when we want to store data that should rerender the
component and refs for data that should only be remembered by the component over time but never rerender
it.
And this is basically also what we already learned back in the lecture on the fundamentals of state
management.
So remember that this diagram is taken from that lecture.
Now, back then, we didn't know what a ref was, but now we do.
Now, going back to the examples of preserving previous state and storing the ID of a set timeout.
These are pieces of data that we want to react to remember between renders, but we don't want them
to rerender the UI whenever we update them.
And so that's why we use refs for this kind of data.
So this is the main distinction between state and refs, but there are also some minor ones.
So as we also just learned, state is immutable, but refs are not.
Also, state is updated asynchronously, which means that we cannot use the new state immediately after
updating it with the refs.
On the other hand, updates are not asynchronous and so we can actually read a new current property
immediately after updating it.
So basically just like any other regular JavaScript object.
Now, okay.
And that does it for this video.
So see you back in VS code.