So let's now do the same thing that we did before, which was to automatically focus on the input element,
but this time using RF.
And so let's start by getting rid of this way of doing things.
And so again, let's now use a ref instead.
So using a ref with a Dom element happens in three steps.
First of all, we create the ref.
And so for that we use the use ref hook as we just learned before.
So we just write use ref.
And then we need to again, make sure that it is now correctly imported from React.
Okay, so let's go back.
So we call the use ref hook.
And then here we pass in the initial value that we want to be in that current property that we just
talked about.
Now, in this case, when we work with a Dom element that is usually just null.
Now.
Right.
And so this will simply return a ref that we can give any name to.
And so let's now store this into a variable called input element, because that's what we will want
to store inside this ref.
So we have our F, and now as a second step, let's actually come to the element that we want to select.
And so all we have to do is to use the ref prop and then we just pass in the ref that we just created.
So that's input.
L And so now these two are basically connected in a declarative way, so there is no need to manually
do some query selection like this here.
So all we are doing is to tell react that the ref that will contain this input element here should be
well, this input element ref that we created.
And so now in order to use this ref in the third step we can use again the use effect hook.
So a new function that simply runs on mount.
So we need to use an effect in order to use a ref that contains a Dom element like this one, because
the ref only gets added to this Dom element here after the dom has already loaded and so therefore we
can only access it in an effect which also runs after the Dom has been loaded.
So this is the perfect place for using a ref that contains a Dom element.
And so now if we want to do the same thing as before, we just use our input element and then remember
that we need to read the current property, which is basically like that box where whatever we store
in the ref will get stored.
So input element dot current.
And so this here is now really the Dom element itself.
And so this is where we can then call the focus method on.
And just to show you, we can also lock this to the console, of course.
So input element dot current.
Give it a save.
And let's manually reload here.
And so you see that just like before our input field got automatically focused.
And also the Dom element itself was rendered here to the console.
All right.
And so, again, this means that we successfully connected the ref that we created here with this Dom
element.
So simply by passing this ref into the ref prop.
And so then in a use effect, after the Dom has been loaded, we can use this dom element inside the
ref dot current property now.
Right.
But now I actually want to do something a little bit more interesting.
So to show you the new feature that we now want to implement, let's come to our demo here.
And now when I'm anywhere in the application, I will hit the enter key.
So I just did that.
And then automatically this input field got focused.
And so that's a really nice feature so that we can very easily search for movies.
So let's say that I had just searched for this movie.
Then I took a look at this one and now at a certain point again I hit the return key.
So the enter key.
So you see that selected the field and it also removed all the search query text that was still in there.
So let's implement that.
And so for that, the first thing that we need to do is to listen for that key press event.
And in fact, we already did something similar before.
So in the movie detail, we already listened here to the Key Down event.
Right now.
In this case, we do actually need to manually select here this document and then add an event listener
there.
So there we cannot use a ref, but that's just the way that things work in React.
So let's do that.
So document dot add Event listener.
And then on the key down event.
And here let's actually again specify a callback function which we will then.
Uh, create here.
And we need to call it callback and it gets access to the event object.
And let's place that here.
And so the reason why we place this in a separate callback function was so that we could clean up after
our event.
So return and let's use an arrow function here now.
Make it a bit shorter.
Add event listener.
Key down and then the callback.
Okay.
But now, of course, this will work on any key press.
So whenever any key is pressed, it will call this callback function and then our element will get focused.
But we only want that to happen when the enter key is pressed.
So let's say E dot.
Code needs to be equal.
Enter.
And it really needs to be uppercase here.
And so in that situation.
Then focus here on the input field.
So let's see if that works.
Going to hit the enter key now.
And yeah, beautiful.
But now let's say that I already had a search here for something.
And so if I hit the return key now, then of course it will simply focus here, but it will not delete
the text yet.
But that's very easy to solve.
We just say set query, which we already get access to here in this component.
So we just set that to an empty string.
And so that should now work as I hit the enter key again.
And indeed, there it is.
There's just one final problem, which is let's say that I'm writing this and then I hit the enter key
again.
And so this will then delete the text that we have.
So basically, we don't want all of this here to happen when the element is already focused, so when
it's already active.
But luckily for us, we can easily check which element is currently active thanks to the document dot
active element property.
And so.
Thanks to that we can say if document dot active element, which again is the element that is currently
being focused.
So if that is equal.
To our input element.
So input l don't current.
Then just return.
So in this case, basically just don't do anything.
All right, let's try that again.
So that just works fine.
But then if I write something and hit enter, well then actually that still doesn't work.
So let's try to reload our page.
Maybe that will fix it.
So let's try that again.
So here it still works.
And now, ah, now it's actually fixed.
And with this we actually finish building this small feature.
So it was just a minor feature, but it was very helpful to understand how we use Hrefs to select Dom
elements in the React way.
Now, there's just one small thing that I'm noticing here, which is that React is complaining about
a missing dependency.
And so, yeah, this is once again really helpful because it tells us immediately what we have to do.
So here we have to also place the set query function.
And so that's because the set query function is indeed a prop to this component.
And so therefore, since we are using it here in the effect, we then need to declare it in the dependency
array.
Now this function is not really ever going to change, but React still needs this to be here in the
dependency array.